[
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "If you were to see people touching a bronze statue’s shoes, the building Sever Hall, and the color crimson, you would realize you were at what university hosting this Certamen competition?",
    "answer": "HARVARD (UNIVERSITY)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What man, whose shoe people touch, is the mascot of Harvard?",
    "answer": "JOHN HARVARD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "This tournament’s opening meeting at Sever Hall featured a wonderful talk by what Professor? Moderator should say: “Subsequent questions will count for points. Good luck and have fun!”",
    "answer": "NAOMI (A.) WEISS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, whose “maiden’s song” for Juno won honor for the collēgium scrībārum histriōnumque, wrote plays like Ajax Mastigophorus and a Saturnian-meter translation of Homer’s Odyssey?",
    "answer": "LIVIUS ANDRONICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin term for Livius’ position in Rome as a teacher of Latin and Greek.",
    "answer": "GRAMMATICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "In whose entourage was Livius brought to Rome following the end of the war between Rome and Tarentum in 272 B.C.?",
    "answer": "LIVIUS SALINATOR(’S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Who recounted how he hid among seals with his men to capture Proteus, the sea god who told him about the fates of the other Greek leaders and how he could safely return to Sparta?",
    "answer": "MENELAUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What daughter of Proteus helped Menelaus capture him?",
    "answer": "EIDOTHEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Proteus lived on Pharos, an island off the coast of what modern day country?",
    "answer": "EGYPT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "A future participle agreeing with the subject, a relative clause after a verb like mittō, an accusative gerundive with ad, and a simple ut clause are all ways to express what concept in Latin?",
    "answer": "PURPOSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a relative clause of purpose, say in Latin “He sent an ambassador to look at the enemies’ camp.”",
    "answer": "LĒGĀTUM MĪSIT QUĪ HOSTIUM CASTRA SPECTĀRET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence adapted from Livy, which uses a surprising tense for an ut purpose clause: “Dictātor, nē frūstrā creātus esset, in pāce aliquid facere cupiēbat.”",
    "answer": "SOMETHING IN PEACE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "At what Thracian city, named after the husband of Vibia Sabina, did a group of dispossessed Goths in the late 4th century win a deadly battle against the emperor Valens?",
    "answer": "(H)ADRIANOPLE / (H)ADRIANOPOLIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What emperor defeated Maximinus Daza, sometimes called Daia, at Adrianople in 313 A.D., only to lose to Constantine there about a decade later?",
    "answer": "(VALERIUS LICINIANUS) LICINIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "The Goths had initially fled from their homes due to the raids of what tribe?",
    "answer": "HUNS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin word, in various forms, fills in the blanks in these phrases: “caelī ēnārrant [blank] Deī”; “ad maiōrem Deī [blank]”; “sīc trānsit [blank] mundī.”",
    "answer": "GLŌRIA / GLŌRIAM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Catholic religious order has the motto “ad maiōrem Deī glōriam”?",
    "answer": "JESUIT(S) // SOCIETY OF JESUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the four-word Latin name of the hymn whose name means “glory to God in the highest.”",
    "answer": "GLŌRIA IN EXCELSĪS DEŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Caesar’s phrase “cīvitās maximam habet opīniōnem virtūtis” — along with “vacātiō labōrum,” “dēsīderium ōtiī,” and “amor pācis” — shows what genitive use often contrasted with subjective?",
    "answer": "OBJECTIVE (GENITIVE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What use of the genitive is found in the phrases “ubinam gentium sumus?” and “parum ōtī”?",
    "answer": "PARTITIVE (GENITIVE) // (GENITIVE) OF THE WHOLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What use of the genitive is found in Horace’s lines “magnī formīca labōris ōre trahit quodcumque potest”?",
    "answer": "(GENITIVE OF) {DESCRIPTION / QUALITY}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What city, whose rivers Asterion, Cephissus, and Inachus were periodically dry for not choosing Poseidon over Hera as the patron, sent champions against Thebes and had kings including Perseus?",
    "answer": "ARGOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What famous Argive city did Perseus found after trading Argos for Tiryns?",
    "answer": "MYCENAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What descendant of Io, fleeing his brother, came from Egypt to claim his right to the Argive throne?",
    "answer": "DANAUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "A foundation of stones called the statūmen and a nine-inch layer of concrete called the rūdus were both used to make what sort of object, examples of which include the Aemilia and Salāria?",
    "answer": "ROAD(S) / VIA(E)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What was the final layer of the road, which was a six-inch bedding of fine concrete?",
    "answer": "NUCLEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What curbstones were used to set bounds on the road on both sides?",
    "answer": "UMBŌNĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author destroyed his signet ring and removed Nero from his will before his suicide, though he had been the emperor’s arbiter elegantiae and used his experience with debauchery to write the Satyricōn?",
    "answer": "PETRONIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Who is the protagonist of the Satyricōn, traveling with Ascyltos and Giton?",
    "answer": "ENCOLPIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "The devolution of the relationship between Petronius and Nero took place over only a few years. In what year had Nero elevated Petronius to the consulship?",
    "answer": "62 A.D."
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What conflict saw brothers nicknamed the “Thunderbolts of War” die near the Baetis River in the same year that the so-called “Sword of War” recaptured Syracuse — 211 B.C.?",
    "answer": "SECOND PUNIC WAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What battle did these “Thunderbolts of War” — the Scipio brothers — win in Spain a year after the Battle of Cannae?",
    "answer": "DERTOSA / IBERA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "In what year did Fabius Maximus Cunctator, the so-called “Shield of War,” recapture Tarentum?",
    "answer": "209 B.C."
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What people, who later lost a battle at Silva Malitiōsa, attended a festival of Neptune or Consus in a newly-founded city, enabling their Roman hosts to seize their women for themselves?",
    "answer": "SABINES"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What was the capital city of the Sabines, the birthplace of Romulus’s successor?",
    "answer": "CURES"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What Sabine chief managed to seize the Capitoline citadel in 460 B.C., though he was quickly dislodged by Gaius Claudius and Publius Valerius?",
    "answer": "(APPIUS) HERDONIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin verb, with what meaning, is at the root of a word describing a pause in the middle of a poetic foot, as well as the words “scissors,” “cement,” and “precision”?",
    "answer": "CAEDŌ – TO CUT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What derivative of caedō is a tool used for carving material such as wood?",
    "answer": "CHISEL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The pause in the middle of a foot is a caesura. In hexameter poetry, a pause between the fourth and fifth feet is a “bucolic diaeresis.” From what Latin words with what meanings is “bucolic” derived? ",
    "answer": "BŌS – COW and COLŌ – CULTIVATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of the words testis, virga, pollex, vīmen, and pollen, which is being described here? Index est quī crīmina aliōrum in iūdiciō dēmōnstrat.",
    "answer": "TESTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of the words latex, virga, pollex, vīmen, and pollen, which two are most closely synonymous? ",
    "answer": "VIRGA and VĪMEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of the words latex, pollex, discrīmen, and pollen, which is most synonymous with perīculum?",
    "answer": "DISCRĪMEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Either by pretending to be a priestess of Hyperborean Artemis, or by rejuvenating her father-in-law Aeson, what woman’s trickery caused Pelias to die and Jason to become king of Iolcus?",
    "answer": "MEDEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "In some sources, Aeson is forced to kill himself by drinking the poisonous blood of what animal?",
    "answer": "BULL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Medea, out of jealousy, murdered what daughter of Creon after Jason said he would marry her?",
    "answer": "GLAUCE / CREUSA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What poet, central to the pagans’ talks in Macrobius’s Sāturnālia, accidentally appealed to Christians by showing a child ushering in a golden age in the 4th poem, known as “Messianic,” of his Eclogues?",
    "answer": "(PUBLIUS) VERGIL(IUS MARO)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Vergil was born near what town, whose status as a victim of Augustus’s land confiscations is alluded to in the Eclogues?",
    "answer": "MANTUA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What poet makes an appearance in Poem 10 of the Eclogues, which puts the pastoral landscape in dialogue with the world of elegy?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) CORNELIUS GALLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "In Ovid’s Metamorphoses, the story of what river-goddess is told within the tale of Persephone, since she saw the Underworld during her flight from Greece to Sicily to escape the clutches of Alpheus?",
    "answer": "ARETHUSA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Arethusa’s story in the Metamorphoses is the culmination of a large series of nested narratives, since the story of Persephone is in turn narrated by the Muses during their contest with what mortals?",
    "answer": "PIERIDES // DAUGHTERS OF PIERUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Continuing this story-ception, the contest with the Pierides is narrated to Minerva by one of the Muses shortly after escaping the clutches of what evil Thracian king, who tried to rape them?",
    "answer": "PYRENEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Like Galba, what aged emperor gave the Praetorians only low pay and harsh discipline when Laetus and Eclectus raised him to power, kicking off an auction for the throne and a Year of the Five Emperors?",
    "answer": "PERTINAX"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What woman had worked alongside Laetus and Eclectus to kill Commodus?",
    "answer": "MARCIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What rogue Praetorian Prefect had promised the soldiers that Galba would give them a donative, making it all the more disappointing when he refused?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) NYMPHIDIUS SABINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What genre, whose first Roman practitioners actually wrote in Greek, was pioneered in Latin prose with a seven-book work by Cato the Elder and arguably reached its peak with Tacitus’s Annālēs?",
    "answer": "HISTORY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What work by Tacitus is his only non-historical work and is structured as a Ciceronian dialogue?",
    "answer": "DIALOGUS DĒ ŌRĀTŌRIBUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, who got his name because one of his ancestors had been a painter, was the first Roman to write history?",
    "answer": "(QUINTUS) FABIUS PICTOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Please translate this sentence from Latin into English: “Vergilius tam aeger est ut nōn possit librum perficere.”",
    "answer": "VERGIL IS SO ILL THAT HE CANNOT COMPLETE THE BOOK"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence from Latin into English: “Lēgāmus opus Ovidiī in quō loquitur dē mūtātīs fōrmīs.”",
    "answer": "TALKS ABOUT CHANGED FORMS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence from Latin into English: “Cum Nerōnem laudāvisset, Lūcānus tamen coniūrātiōnis particeps esse cōnstituit.”",
    "answer": "PARTICIPANT IN THE CONSPIRACY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What one-syllable Latin conjunction, which is sometimes joined with modo in a proviso clause, surprisingly always takes the present indicative when it has the meaning “while”?",
    "answer": "DUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What tense and mood would follow dum if it translated “for” in the sentence “The soldier was waiting for his commander to arrive”?",
    "answer": "IMPERFECT SUBJUNCTIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Lines consisting entirely of spondees and a line addressing Titus Tatius in excessive alliteration show what author’s willingness to experiment with the brand-new dactylic hexameter in his Annālēs?",
    "answer": "ENNIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What sound did Ennius express with the onomatopoeia “taratantara”?",
    "answer": "A TRUMPET BLARING"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Name either of the two comedies by Ennius, one about a wrestler and another about an innkeeper’s wife. ",
    "answer": "CAUPUNCULA or PANCRATIASTĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "How many words in the following English sentence are derived from Latin? “While avidly watching birds outside the national convention, I saw several ospreys.”",
    "answer": "FIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Who installed reflective marble in his palace shortly after Lappius Maximus barely ended the revolt of Saturninus, though this did not save him from a stab in the groin by his butler Stephanus?",
    "answer": "DOMITIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What famous generalissimo was the father of Domitian’s wife?",
    "answer": "(GNAEUS) DOMITIUS CORBULO"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Saturninus had tried to induce what German tribe to rebel and invade Roman borders?",
    "answer": "CHATTI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What woman remained with her father until he passed at Colonus, before returning to her home where she tried to bury her cursed brother Polynices in defiance of the decree of Creon?",
    "answer": "ANTIGONE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What fiancé of Antigone, a son of Creon, committed suicide upon learning of her death?",
    "answer": "HAEMON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Colonus was a suburb of what city, whose king secured the burial of the Seven Against Thebes?",
    "answer": "ATHENS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "The Halieutica is a minor work of what author, who gave voice to Briseis and other women, addressed Corinna in his Amōrēs, and wrote a 15-book epic poem called Metamorphōsēs?",
    "answer": "OVID"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "After being banished by Augustus, Ovid spent the last years of his life in what city, where he composed his Tristia and Epistulae ex Pontō?",
    "answer": "TOMI(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What minor work of Ovid, named after a bird, wishes several hundred terrible mythological punishments on an unnamed enemy?",
    "answer": "ĪBIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which two states are the only ones with one-word Latin mottos, one of which is a first-person verb meaning “I direct” and the other of which is a comparative adjective meaning “higher”? ",
    "answer": "MAINE and NEW YORK"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "There are three states with a four-word Latin motto. Identify one of them and give the motto.",
    "answer": "ASPERA // VERMONT – STĒLLA QUĀRTA DECIMA FULGEAT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "There are two states with a six-word Latin motto. Identify one of them and give the motto.",
    "answer": "MASSACHUSETTS – ĒNSE PETIT PLACIDAM SUB LĪBERTĀTE QUIĒTEM"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "According to Polybius, famous paintings were used as gaming tables after what city, which raised Critolaus as its dictator, was sacked by Lucius Mummius in 146 B.C.?",
    "answer": "CORINTH"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Which Roman general, fresh off victories against Andriscus in 148 B.C., left Macedonia in order to deal with Critolaus?",
    "answer": "(QUINTUS CAECILIUS) METELLUS MACEDONICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "According to Livy, what Corinthian noble fled to Italy early in Rome’s history, and had a son whose name reflected the Etruscan city he settled in?",
    "answer": "DEMARATUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Nereus alone knew how to find what wedding gift of Gaea, a place defended by the serpent Ladon, tended to by a few sisters, and breached by either Atlas or Heracles during a labor?",
    "answer": "GARDEN OF THE HESPERIDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Sometimes the location of the Hesperides was near what tribe that lived in the far, far north?",
    "answer": "HYPERBOREANS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "On his way to the Hesperides, Heracles had killed what king of Egypt who tried sacrificing him, alongside other strangers, to Zeus?",
    "answer": "BUSIRIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What city acted as the eastern terminus of the via Egnātia, was split into two by a strait called “Bosporus,” and was the capital of the Eastern Roman Empire before it was renamed “Istanbul”?",
    "answer": "BYZANTIUM / CONSTANTINOPLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Give the ancient name for the body of water that bordered Constantinople to the north.",
    "answer": "PONTUS EUXĪNUS // EUXINE SEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Give the ancient name for the Sea of Marmara, which bordered Constantinople to the south.",
    "answer": "PROPONTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Exiled for killing his half-brother Phocus, who went to Phthia, where he became king, welcomed men like Phoenix and Patroclus, and let them accompany his son by Thetis, Achilles?",
    "answer": "PELEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "After moving to Phthia, Peleus had to get purified again for killing his father-in-law, and sought out what king of Iolcus, who had previously been an Argonaut alongside Peleus in defiance of his father?",
    "answer": "ACASTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Give the reasons for why either Phoenix or Patroclus came to Phthia. ",
    "answer": "PHOENIX HAD SLEPT WITH HIS FATHER’S CONCUBINE AND GOT IN TROUBLE or PATROCLUS HAD KILLED A BOY (CLITONYMUS OVER A DICE GAME)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "According to a Roman poet, the existence of what objects removes any fear of death, accounts for free will through clīnāmen, forms the core of Epicureanism, and explains the rērum nātūra scientifically?",
    "answer": "ATOMS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "In Lucretius’s work, what deity personifies Nature’s generative force and the Epicurean ideal of ataraxy, or undisturbedness?",
    "answer": "VENUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What English word is often used to translate the idea of clīnāmen, as seen in the title of a book by Stephen Greenblatt on the history of Lucretius’s rediscovery by Poggio Bracciolini?",
    "answer": "SWERVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in Latin: “If I had come home, I would have seen you.” For this sentence, both verbs should be pluperfect subjunctive.",
    "answer": "SĪ DOMUM VĒNISSEM, TĒ VĪDISSEM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now say in Latin: “Would I see you tomorrow if I were to come again?”",
    "answer": "VIDEAMNE TĒ CRAS SĪ ITERUM VENIAM?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Finally, say in Latin: “If only I were able to run for ten hours to see you!”",
    "answer": "UTINAM POSSEM DECEM HORĀS CURRERE {UT TĒ VIDĒREM // AD TĒ VIDENDUM}"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Members of what people swore an oath in a linen-covered tent before joining battle at Aquilonia in 293 B.C., the last battle of a three-war conflict that also saw a defeat at Caudine Forks?",
    "answer": "SAMNITES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Though his epitaph claims that he took Samnium and subdued all Lucania, what early member of the Scipio family suffered a defeat at the hands of the Samnites at Camerinum?",
    "answer": "(LUCIUS CORNELIUS SCIPIO SCAPULA) BARBATUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "In the middle of the Second Samnite War, Fabius Rullianus also broke Etruscan power at what lake in 310 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(LAKE) VADIMO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What part of the body — on which a pecten might be employed to make it cōmptus, often in the hands of an ornātrīx — was known in Latin as crīnēs or capillī?",
    "answer": "HAIR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What celestial phenomenon is etymologically described as “hairy,” though it is related to a third word for “hair”?",
    "answer": "COMET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "How would a person’s hair look if they are described with the phrase crīnibus passīs?",
    "answer": "DISHEVELED / SCATTERED / IN DISARRAY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What literary device is found in the phrases “ex oculīs fūgit ceu fūmus in aurās,” “eam agnōvī obscūram, quālem quī per nūbila surgere lūnam videt,” and other phrases with sīcut or quasi?",
    "answer": "SIMILE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Opposing speeches by Caesar and Cato the Younger frame the second half of what work, which details the battle of Pistoria as part of its monographic treatment of a 63 B.C. conspiracy against the Republic?",
    "answer": "(SALLUST’S) BELLUM CATILĪNAE // DĒ CATILĪNAE CONIŪRĀTIŌNE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What other work of Sallust, left unfinished at his death, was a history beginning at 78 BC?",
    "answer": "HISTORIAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "The first Latin historical monograph may have been a work by Coelius Antipater on what conflict, which later received a 17-book epic poetic treatment?",
    "answer": "SECOND PUNIC WAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Hecate’s appearance on earth was often accompanied by what animals — which the queen Hecuba transformed into — though the most famous examples of these beasts were Orthrus and Cerberus?",
    "answer": "HELL-HOUND / DOG"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "The expression “a sop for Cerberus” stems from a scene in the Aeneid where what mythological figure throws a honey-cake to the guard dog?",
    "answer": "SIBYL (OF CUMAE) // DEIPHOBE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Hecuba’s transformation into a fiery-eyed dog happened because she murdered what king of the Thracian Chersonese for revenge?",
    "answer": "POLYM(N)ESTOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Shortly before his death, who chose Rufinus as Eastern Praetorian Prefect and Stilicho as the Western one, so that his sons Honorius and Arcadius would have guides in a now-divided empire?",
    "answer": "THEODOSIUS {I // THE GREAT}"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Before attempts at peace broke down, what man was chosen by Honorius to succeed Stilicho as magister utrīusque mīlitiae, while his brother-in-law Athaulf also received a prize position?",
    "answer": "ALARIC"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What daughter of Arcadius held real power during much of the reign of Theodosius II, her brother?",
    "answer": "PULCHERIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate into idiomatic Latin without using nōn or any such adverb: “Alexander’s soldiers said that they would not follow him.” [pause] To do this, you should use a verb for “denied.”",
    "answer": "MĪLITĒS ALEXANDRĪ NEGĀVĒRUNT SĒ EUM SECŪTŪROS (ESSE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate into good Latin: “Alexander said that the soldiers who were remaining would receive rewards.”",
    "answer": "ALEXANDER DĪXIT (EŌS) MĪLITĒS QUĪ (RĒ)MĀNĒRENT PRAEMIA ACCEPTŪRŌS (ESSE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "In the Aeneid, who prays to a tearful Hercules before hurling his spear at Turnus, unaware that he would shortly be killed and stripped of his sword-belt far from his father Evander?",
    "answer": "PALLAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What crime decorated Pallas’s sword-belt?",
    "answer": "THE DANAIDS MURDERING THEIR HUSBANDS (ON THEIR WEDDING NIGHT)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Pallas had originally planned to fight what son of Mezentius?",
    "answer": "LAUSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Menedemus forcing himself into a life of torment, a man disguising himself as the titular eunuch, and the successes of the parasite Phormio appear in the six palliātae of what comic playwright?",
    "answer": "TERENCE // (PUBLIUS) TERENTIUS (AFER)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What about Terence’s biography suggested to critics that his plays were actually by Scipio Aemilianus?",
    "answer": "HE WAS A FREED SLAVE // HE WAS FROM CARTHAGE AND HAD TO LEARN LATIN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "According to legend, Terence had to present his first comedy for approval to what other comic playwright, the author of Plocium?",
    "answer": "CAECILIUS STATIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What meaning is shared by the following four words: sospes, incolumis, tūtus, salvus?",
    "answer": "SAFE / UNHARMED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin verb with what meaning do we get the word tūtus?",
    "answer": "TUEOR – {WATCH (OVER) // PROTECT}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the more standard past participle of tueor?",
    "answer": "TUITUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "The lēx Ovīnia gave holders of what office the duty of revising senatorial lists, though one of its most famous holders in 312 B.C. used it to build an eponymous road and aqueduct during an 18-month term?",
    "answer": "CENSOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "The censorial elections were typically held by what assembly, which allotted a total of 193 votes among the citizens of Rome?",
    "answer": "COMITIA CENTURIĀTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What dictator authored a law requiring one censor to be plebeian in 339 B.C., just two years before becoming the first plebeian to hold the praetorship?",
    "answer": "(QUINTUS) PUBLILIUS PHILO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "From what author do we get the quotes “pulvis et umbra sumus,” “sapere audē” “aurea mediocritās,” and “dulce et decōrum est prō patriā morī”?",
    "answer": "HORACE // (QUINTUS) HORATIUS (FLACCUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What words complete the Horatian quote “quandōque bonus [blank]”?",
    "answer": "DORMĪTAT HOMĒRUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What two-word phrase of Horace looks back to the good old days — those days being 42 B.C., when Munatius Plancus was consul?",
    "answer": "CŌNSULE PLANCŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Plans for Roman borders along the Elbe and Vistula rivers had to be scuttled after what disaster, called the clādēs Variāna by an emperor who bashed his head against the wall and probably cursed Arminius?",
    "answer": "(BATTLE OF) TEUTOBURG FOREST // TEUTOBERGER WALD"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What blundering oaf of a general walked into this disastrous trap and gave his name to the disaster?",
    "answer": "(PUBLIUS) QUINCTILIUS VARUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Arminius, the warlord who engineered this stunning reverse for the Romans, was the head honcho of what tribe?",
    "answer": "CHERUSCI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Who punished Glaucus the horsekeeper by having his mares devour him, Tyndareus for neglecting her rites, Helios for revealing her affair, and Anchises for boasting of her love for him?",
    "answer": "APHRODITE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Glaucus was the father by Eurynome of what mythological hero?",
    "answer": "BELLEROPHON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Whom did Aphrodite cause Helios to fall in love with as punishment, though her father Orchamus did not allow the union?",
    "answer": "LEUCOTHOE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin verb is at the ultimate root of “squat,” which initially referred to “forcing” down your body’s weight and thus comes through the compound cōgō?",
    "answer": "AGŌ [PROMPT ON “CŌGŌ” BEFORE IT IS READ]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin word is at the ultimate root of “squad,” as well as “square”?",
    "answer": "QUATTUOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin verb with what meaning do we get “squash?” The “s” comes from the prefix ex-, which intensifies this verb.",
    "answer": "QUATIŌ / QUATERE = (TO / I) SHAKE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into alliterative Latin using a passive periphrastic: “Sextus must follow the seven allies.”",
    "answer": "SEXTŌ SEPTEM SOCIĪ SEQUENDĪ SUNT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into alliterative Latin using a gerund: “We will be able to gain the reward by fighting.”",
    "answer": "POTERIMUS PRAEMIŌ POTĪRĪ PUGNANDŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into alliterative Latin using a gerund: “A desire to run quickly to Corinth has seized Crassus.”",
    "answer": "{CUPĪDŌ / CUPIDITĀS} CELERITER CORINTHUM CURRENDĪ CRASSUM CĒPIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What figure in Latin literature, who “first captured” a “wretched” poet with her ocellī, may have had the real name Hostia and was the chief subject of the Monobiblos by Propertius?",
    "answer": "CYNTHIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Propertius declared himself the Roman version of what author from Cyrene, whose Aetia also inspired Catullus’s “Lock of Berenice”?",
    "answer": "CALLIMACHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "In poem sixteen of the Monobiblos, what type of object bewails its sorrowful fate at the hands of Cynthia in a reverse paraclausithyron?",
    "answer": "DOOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "The words “Ollus Quiris lētō datus…” preceded what sort of event, which featured a special lectus, actors wearing imāginēs, a dēsignātor who organized it, and a laudātiō fūnebris?",
    "answer": "FUNERAL (PROCESSION) // FŪNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Give the Latin word for the act performed when a Roman died at home, where the eldest son bent over the body and called the father by name.",
    "answer": "CONCLĀMĀTIŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What was the aptly named sort of funeral performed for very young children?",
    "answer": "FŪNUS ACERBUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "When she objected to her son’s divorce of Octavia, who was invited onto a boat set up to collapse, an act which not even Burrus and Seneca could explain away on her son Nero’s behalf?",
    "answer": "AGRIPPINA THE YOUNGER"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Whom did Nero marry — though not for long — after divorcing Octavia, taking her from her previous husband?",
    "answer": "POPPAEA SABINA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Agrippina also objected to Nero’s affair with what freedwoman of Claudius?",
    "answer": "(CLAUDIA) ACTE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author disparages his father Patricius while praising his mother’s piety in an autobiography of his path from neo-Platonism and Manichaeism to Christianity, the Confessions?",
    "answer": "AUGUSTINE // (AURELIUS) AUGUSTINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Name Augustine’s mother.",
    "answer": "MONICA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What book by what author changed Augustine’s life and inspired him to pursue philosophy?",
    "answer": "CICERO’S HORTĒNSIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb adimō, give the 3rd person plural, perfect passive subjunctive, keeping in mind that it is a compound of emō and forms its fourth principal part with the same vowel as emō.",
    "answer": "ADEMPTĪ SINT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Because her son looked too much like his Thracian father, what Athenian princess murdered her son Itys before serving him to Tereus to get revenge for her sister Philomela?",
    "answer": "PROCNE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Pandion had married Tereus to Procne for helping him in a war against what city led by Labdacus?",
    "answer": "THEBES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Dēscrībāmus nunc proprietātēs dictiōnum in hāc sententia: “dīs genite et genitūre deōs.” Quō cāsū sunt et “genite” et “genitūre”?",
    "answer": "VOCĀTĪVŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What use of the ablative is exemplified by the word dīs?",
    "answer": "(ABLATIVE OF) {SOURCE / ORIGIN}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What modern English letter is orthographically descended from the Greek letter which gives its name to the rhetorical device in that quote?",
    "answer": "X"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, who cites his father’s participation at Bedriacum for an anecdote, goes per speciēs in a gossipy and rumor-heavy style through the lives and personalities of twelve Roman rulers?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) SUETONIUS (TRANQUILLUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Under what emperor was Suetonius employed in the imperial archives, giving him a wealth of material with which to compose his biographies?",
    "answer": "HADRIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What later work, purporting to be by six different authors, imitates Suetonius’s style but is so unreliable that many scholars have assumed it has to be a joke or parody?",
    "answer": "HISTORIA AUGUSTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What name is shared by a senator whose support of the lēx Sempronia Agrāria got him a spot on the Gracchi’s land commission, and the co-consul of Junius Pullus who failed to heed the chickens?",
    "answer": "CLAUDIUS PULCHER"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Tiberius Gracchus came to prominence while on the staff of Gaius Hostilius Mancinus during the siege of what city, which was finally defeated in the year of his tribunate?",
    "answer": "NUMANTIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Claudius Pulcher also had family ties to the Gracchi. What was his relationship with Tiberius?",
    "answer": "FATHER-IN-LAW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following exclamation into English: “Quam pulcher est homō quī virtūtem habet!”",
    "answer": "HOW BEAUTIFUL IS A MAN WHO HAS VIRTUE!"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into English: “Quotiēns mūlus aquam bibit, totiēns ego vīnum.”",
    "answer": "AS OFTEN AS A MULE DRINKS WATER I DO (DRINK) WINE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Finally, translate this one: “Tantō mē pauperior eris quantō tē sapientior sum.”",
    "answer": "YOU WILL BE AS MUCH POORER THAN I AS I AM WISER THAN YOU"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What king, who lived with his 6 sons and 6 daughters that were married to one another, refused to help Odysseus when he returned 10 days later after his crew had opened the bag of winds?",
    "answer": "AEOLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "In the Aeneid, what goddess commands Aeolus to try sinking Aeneas’ ships with his winds?",
    "answer": "JUNO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Works in what form were famously discovered by Petrarch after being posthumously published by Tiro, revealing their author’s relations with Lucceius and other familiārēs as well as his best friend Atticus?",
    "answer": "EPISTLES / LETTERS / EPISTULAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author’s disappointingly mediocre letter-collection, which includes a reference to a historical work on the Parthian wars of Lucius Verus, was rediscovered in the 19th century?",
    "answer": "(M. CORNELIUS) FRONTO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Identify and correct the mistake, if any, in the following Latin sentence: Līberōs meōs īrātus rogāvī quō pridiē īverint et quid fēcissent.",
    "answer": "ĪVERINT SHOULD BE ĪVISSENT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Identify and correct the mistake, if any, in the following Latin sentence: Adeō magistrum timeō nē eum alloquī audeam.",
    "answer": "NĒ SHOULD BE UT NŌN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Identify and correct the mistake, if any, in the following Latin sentence, which is intended to have a purpose clause: Fugiō ut nēmō mē inveniat.",
    "answer": "UT NĒMŌ SHOULD BE NĒ QUIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "The capture of Vetera was the high point of whose revolt, which was incited by Fonteius Capito’s false accusations and saw him pretend to support Vespasian before Cerealis defeated his Batavian forces?",
    "answer": "JULIUS CIVILIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Cerealis also fought in Britain and seems to have dealt with a revolt by Venutius, the former husband of what Brigantian queen who once turned Caratacus over to the Romans?",
    "answer": "CARTIMANDUA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What island, which saw a sacrifice to Apollo, Artemis, and Leto after the murder of Thersites, was the birthplace of the pirate-fleeing, dolphin-riding Greek singer Arion, and the home of Orpheus’s lyre?",
    "answer": "LESBOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Why did Achilles murder Thersites?",
    "answer": "FOR MOCKING HIM FOR LAMENTING AFTER MURDERING PENTHESILEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Arion had spent most of his life at the court of what tyrant of Corinth?",
    "answer": "PERIANDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What type of object are all of the following: phasēlus, scapha, ratis, and — by metonymy — puppis?",
    "answer": "BOAT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Navēs onerāriae taedā et pice et stuppā complētae sunt. Quid Anglicē significat “pix”?",
    "answer": "PITCH / ASPHALT / TAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Navis in syrtim incessit. Quid Anglicē significat “syrtis”?",
    "answer": "SANDBANK / SHOAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What mythological man was depicted “on his knees,” or en gonasin, after he fought the Ligurians in a return journey that also saw the birth of Scythes, the defeat of Eryx, and the death of Cacus?",
    "answer": "HERACLES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Engonasin is not the only constellation that commemorates Heracles. The constellation Ophiuchus portrays him killing what sort of animal at Omphale’s behest?",
    "answer": "SNAKE / SERPENT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "When Heracles was wounded and fell to his knees while battling the Ligurians, what miraculous event did Zeus send to save him, which explains the terrain around the city of Marseilles?",
    "answer": "A RAIN OF STONES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author’s “Tale of the Tub” was potentially inspired by Aristides and the fābulae Milēsiae, which he combines with knowledge about the cults of Osiris and Isis in an 11-book narrative about Lucius?",
    "answer": "(L.) APULEIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Republican historian, a so-called ēmendātor sermōnis ūsitātī, penned a Latin collection of fābulae Milēsiae?",
    "answer": "(L. CORNELIUS) SISENNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Lucius Domitius Ahenobarbus failed to obtain the consulship of what year B.C., which saw Caesar’s first crossing of the English Channel and the fulfillment of deals discussed in the previous year at Luca?",
    "answer": "55 (B.C.)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What law of 55 B.C. was one such deal, as it procured governorships in Syria and Spain for Crassus and Pompey, respectively?",
    "answer": "LĒX TREBŌNIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Ahenobarbus, a staunch opponent of Caesar, attempted in 49 B.C. to intercept Caesar’s forces at what city, which previously served as a rebel base until it was abandoned for Bovianum Vetus?",
    "answer": "CORFINIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into Latin: “I do not know what children he is the father of.”",
    "answer": "NESCIŌ QUŌRUM {FĪLIŌRUM / NĀTŌRUM / LĪBERŌRUM} PATER SIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this one using dēsum: “I never thought I would lack words.”",
    "answer": "{DĒFŪTURA (ESSE) // DĒFORE}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence, using two different non-indicative forms of caveō: “Don’t beware big dogs more than small ones.”",
    "answer": "PARVŌS (CANĒS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of the words “roulette,” “round,” “adroit,” “enroll,” and “rotate,” which does NOT belong by derivation, since it is from regō rather than rota?",
    "answer": "ADROIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin verb is at the root of “routine” and “route”?",
    "answer": "RUMPŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin noun is at the root of the Spanish word “arroyo” meaning “ravine” and the French word “rue” meaning “street,” as well as an English word meaning “shaped into alternate ridges and grooves”?",
    "answer": "RUGA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "New alluvial deposits allowed what man to find respite from his madness after anger at the effects of Harmonia’s necklace and robe led him to kill his mother Eriphyle and avenge his father Amphiaraus?",
    "answer": "ALCM(A)EON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "These alluvial deposits were found at what river, whose god gave Alcmaeon his daughter Callirhoe in marriage?",
    "answer": "ACHELOUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Alcmaeon’s tomb, surrounded by tall cypress trees, was found near what city, where he was murdered at the command of king Phegeus?",
    "answer": "PSOPHIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "In what field of study might one use two similar three-letter abbreviations, one ending with F and one with D, that feature passive periphrastics with faciendum and dēmōnstrandum?",
    "answer": "MATH(EMATICS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Description acceptable. In what field of work within Classics might one find abbreviations like ed. pr. and MSS., as well as phrases like falsa lectiō?",
    "answer": "FROM MANUSCRIPTS [ACCEPT EQUIVS.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The abbreviation ed. pr. refers to the first publication of a particular text. What does it stand for?",
    "answer": "ĒDITIŌ PRĪNCEPS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "In his criticism of epigrammatic sententiae and the Senecan style, who advocates for a focus on rērum pondera and the old ideal of the vir bonus dīcendī perītus in a 12-book work on an orator’s education?",
    "answer": "(M. FABIUS) QUINTILIAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "About what Flavian epic poet, who adapted Apollonius of Rhodes, did Quintilian write “multum nūper amīsimus”?",
    "answer": "(C.) VALERIUS FLACCUS (BALBUS SETINUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What megalomaniacal rhetorician was a notorious example of the fear of corrupt teachers passing on their morals to their students?",
    "answer": "REMMIUS PALAEMON"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "The reports of an enslaved man named Vindicius forced what consul to preside over the execution of his own sons, before he simultaneously killed and was killed by his opponent at Silva Arsia in 509 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(L. JUNIUS) BRUTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Shortly after this battle, Publicola earned the people’s favor by moving his house off of what hill?",
    "answer": "VELIA // VELIAN (HILL)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "The battle of Silva Arsia was inconclusive at first, but what supernatural event proved that the Romans had defeated the Etruscans?",
    "answer": "ETRUSCANS HAD SUSTAINED ONE MORE LOSS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of the words ter, quater, pater, alter, and ūter, how many of them can you add an “e” at the end of to get a legitimate Latin verb form?",
    "answer": "FOUR (ALL EXCEPT ALTER)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "How many of those four verb forms – that is, tere, quatere, patere, and ūtere – could be imperative?",
    "answer": "ALL FOUR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Identify which of these verb forms, if any, would still be legitimate verb forms if the first “e” were lengthened, and parse the resulting forms.",
    "answer": "ŪTĒRE – 2ND SINGULAR FUTURE (OF ŪTOR)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Premiering in 191 B.C. but later revived with the actor Roscius, what Plautine play features the pimp Ballio outsmarted by an enslaved man whose name is derived from the Greek for “fake”?",
    "answer": "PSEUDOLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Plautine play, where a man tries to convince his daughters to divorce their husbands, premiered at the Plebeian games of 200 B.C. and is known for its remarkable lack of dramatic events?",
    "answer": "STICHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "In what play of Plautus does Saturio sell a pretend Arabian captive to a pimp so that he can buy a good meal?",
    "answer": "PERSA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Helios nightly rode the currents of what river, which was believed to issue from the Underworld and to circle around the flat earth, marking the furthest boundaries of the world?",
    "answer": "OCEANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What peculiar vessel did Helios use to complete his daily journey on the river Ocean? A description is fine.",
    "answer": "(GOLDEN) CUP"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Prometheus Bound, the river Oceanus appears as a character and rides on what animal, which fought the Arimaspians for gold at the northern limits of the world?",
    "answer": "GRIFFIN"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage about scenes of horror during the civil war, which I will read twice, then answer in English the question that follows. Paucī, cum prīmum cīvium sanguis effūsus est, vīsū ipsō perterritī diffūgēre. Alius autem, ut corpus frātris impūne spoliāre posset, abscīsum caput longē mīsit; alius, ōra parentis lacerāns, nimiā probābat spectantibus īrā eum quem iugulāret nōn esse patrem. The question: What caused a few soldiers to flee the battlefield?",
    "answer": "THE SIGHT OF CITIZENS’ BLOOD BEING SHED [ACCEPT CLOSE EQUIVS.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How did one soldier manage to take spoils from his own brother’s body without the body being recognized?",
    "answer": "HE {CUT OFF // HURLED / KICKED AWAY} HIS BROTHER’S HEAD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What did the soldier who killed his father attempt to prove to the spectators, and how?",
    "answer": "DISPLAYED TOWARD THE BODY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Efforts against what phenomenon provoked a revolt on the Caelian Hill by Felicissimus, saw the creation of the Antoniniānus, and led to an ineffectual 301 A.D. Edict by Diocletian?",
    "answer": "PRACTICAL EFFECT OF THAT ACTION?”; DO NOT ACCEPT “PRICE GOUGING”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When the emperor Constans failed to quell inflation, what man usurped rule of the West in 350 A.D. until Constantius II in turn defeated him?",
    "answer": "MAGNENTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What term refers to the new gold coin that replaced the aureus during the reign of Diocletian and was stabilized at 72 to the Roman pound by Constantine?",
    "answer": "SOLIDUS / NOMISMA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin word appears in the ancient names of Chaves in modern-day Portugal, Baden-Baden in modern-day Germany, Aix-en-’ in modern-day France, and Bath in modern-day Britain?",
    "answer": "AQUA(E)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the modern name of Germany’s city of Aquae Granni, which was Charlemagne’s capital?",
    "answer": "AACHEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what modern-day country is the city of Aquae Regiae located, like Hadrumentum and Thysdrus?",
    "answer": "FINAL ROUND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "In the Iliad, elm trees were planted around the burial mound of what king, who ruled a city at the foot of Mt. Placus, and, after being killed alongside his 7 sons, was buried in full armor by Achilles?",
    "answer": "EETION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was the apt name of Eetion’s city that he ruled?",
    "answer": "HYPOPLACIAN THEBES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "During another of Achilles’ excursions, he captures what son of Priam, while he worked in an orchard, and sold him and his brothers Isus and Antiphus for ransom?",
    "answer": "LYCAON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following, if any, would an Ancient Roman likely NOT have recognized as a profession? caupō, tortor, abūtor, lignārius.",
    "answer": "ABŪTOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following, if any, would an Ancient Roman likely NOT have eaten? trīticum, pāvō, caepa, olea.",
    "answer": "NONE OF THE ABOVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following, if any, would an Ancient Roman likely NOT have recognized as a color? līvidus, cānus, prasinus, hirsūtus.",
    "answer": "HIRSŪTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Titles meaning “Night Watch” and “Battle on the Ships” — Nyctēgresia and Epinausimachē — were coined by what eminent figure in the collegium poētārum, a native of Pisaurum and prolific tragedian?",
    "answer": "ACCIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "For what nobleman and fellow tragedian did Accius notably refuse to rise in a meeting of the collegium poētārum?",
    "answer": "(C. JULIUS) CAESAR STRABO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Accius wasn’t the only tragedian with difficult Greek titles. Name either the tragedy of Ennius whose name contains a Greek noun meaning “ransom,” or his tragedy whose name contains a Greek noun meaning “prisoner of war.” HECTORIS LUTRA or ANDROMACHA AECHMALŌTIS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What conflict, at whose sites archaeologists found sling bullets labeled “Piso,” saw Rupilius defeat a supposed fire-breather and prophet in 132 B.C. during a large Sicilian revolt co-led by Cleon? 2023 Harvard Certamen Adv. Finals Visual",
    "answer": "FIRST SERVILE WAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Inscriptions on sling bullets, sometimes with insulting messages or obscene drawings, were common in Roman combat. For instance, these 11 sling bullets were all found around what Italian city?",
    "answer": "PERUSIA / PERUGIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the nōmen of the man referred to in sling bullet 8, whose praenōmen was Quintus?",
    "answer": "SALVIDIENUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What exact Latin form completes these blanks: “sed vetant [blank] Iovis”; “corruptissimā rē pūblicā plūrimae [blank]”; “quid [blank] sine mōribus vānae prōficiunt?”; “silent [blank] enim inter arma.”",
    "answer": "LĒGĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Fill in the following sentence with Latin of your own making that idiomatically explains the relevant phrase: “Prōverbium ‘ab asinō lānam’ dictum est dē eīs hominibus quī [blank].”",
    "answer": "SAMPLE ANSWER: ALIQUID FACERE CONANTUR QUOD FIERI NON POTEST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now do the same for this sentence: “Prōverbium ‘Acheruntis pābulum’ dictum est dē eīs hominibus quī [blank].”",
    "answer": "SAMPLE ANSWER: MORTE DIGNI SUNT OB NEQUITIAM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Who ensured the survival of Latin literature when he began the tradition of scriptōria in his monastery at Vivarium, to which he retired in 554 after writing a history of the Goths and befriending Boethius?",
    "answer": "CASSIODORUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Both Boethius and Cassiodorus served in what position at the culmination of their political careers?",
    "answer": "MAGISTER OFFICIŌRUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author from Seville made an essential contribution to the preservation of classical knowledge in medieval times with his Orīginēs sīve Etymologiae, a monumental encyclopedic work?",
    "answer": "ISIDORE (OF SEVILLE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When recognized by the spotter, perform the following commands: tendēns manum ad vultum sociī, interpōne pollicem duōbus digitīs et clāmā Anglicē tē nāsum eius cēpisse.",
    "answer": "BETWEEN THEIR INDEX AND MIDDLE FINGERS, AND SHOUT “GOT YOUR NOSE!”"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now perform these commands: Simulā tē invēnisse nummulum aureum post aurem sodālis, et dīc Anglicē tibi in animō esse illum nummum moderātōribus prō quīnque punctīs trādere.",
    "answer": "THAT THEY PLAN TO GIVE IT TO THE MODERATORS IN EXCHANGE FOR FIVE POINTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now perform these commands: ūtrāque manū facite circulum pollice et indice; deinde, manibus inversīs, tenēte circulōs iūxtā oculōs quasi persōnam gerās.",
    "answer": "THEIR HANDS UPSIDE DOWN AND HOLD THE CIRCLES AGAINST THEIR EYES LIKE A MASK"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What event, where judges wore dark-coloured clothing in mourning, rewarded victors with parsley, and was founded by Adrastus to honor an infant nicknamed Archemorus?",
    "answer": "NEMEAN GAMES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Right after these games, the Seven Against Thebes reached Thebes where Tydeus met what man, who was sent alongside Polyphontes and 50 other men to challenge him?",
    "answer": "MAEON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was the father of the 4 leading defenders of Thebes, most notably Melanippus, whose brains were eaten?",
    "answer": "ASTACUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in derivation, if necessary, between “decoy” and “coy,” the first of which is cognate with “cage” and the second of which is cognate with “acquit.” CAVUS / CAVEA and QUIĒS / QUIESCŌ / QUIĒTUS, RESPECTIVELY",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in derivation, if necessary, between “chinch” and “cinch.” CIMEX and CINGŌ, RESPECTIVELY",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in derivation, if necessary, between “colony” and “colonel.” COLŌ / COLŌNUS and COLUMNA, RESPECTIVELY",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What city, the site of Hadrian’s death, was connected to Puteoli with a pontoon bridge by Caligula, as he sought to disprove an astrologer’s prediction by riding across the Bay of Naples on horseback?",
    "answer": "BAIAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Republican commander died of a massive hemorrhage in Puteoli after retiring from power?",
    "answer": "SULLA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was the name of the astrologer of Tiberius who had cast doubt on Caligula’s imperial prospects?",
    "answer": "THRASYLLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What honor was a gold crown awarded to the first person to enter a besieged town?",
    "answer": "CORŌNA MŪRĀLIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What was the second highest honor, awarded for saving the life of a citizen?",
    "answer": "CORŌNA CĪVICA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage adapted from Augustine, which I will read twice, then answer in English the question that follows. Cum parārem recitāre imperātōrī laudēs, in quibus mentientī favērētur ā scientibus, aspexī pauperem iocantem. Ingemuī, quod omnibus cōnātibus nihil vellem aliud nisi laetitiam nancīscī, quō mē mendīcus ille praecessisset numquam illūc fortasse ventūrum. The question: Augustine fears he may never reach what goal despite all his efforts, even though the beggar had achieved it easily?",
    "answer": "(ACHIEVING) HAPPINESS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How does Augustine describe what happens as someone is reciting an imperial panegyric?",
    "answer": "THE SPEAKER LIES, BUT THE AUDIENCE FAVORS HIM EVEN THOUGH THEY KNOW HE’S LYING"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The passage continues. Sī quis autem rogāret utrum tālis esse māllem quālis ille, an quālis ego tunc essem, ēligerem mē ipsum cūrīs cōnfectum — perversitāte, nōn vēritāte. The question: What question is Augustine unable to provide a logical answer to?",
    "answer": "WHETHER HE WOULD RATHER BE LIKE THE BEGGAR OR IN HIS CURRENT STATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Crassicius Pasicles wrote a commentary on what author, a native of Brescia who wrote a propempticon to Asinius Pollio and labored for 9 years to write the story of Myrrha and Cinyras in his Zmyrna?",
    "answer": "CINNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What fellow neoteric wrote an epicēdion for his wife Quintilia?",
    "answer": "LICINIUS CALVUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Cinna may have brought what Greek author to Rome, a friend of Cornelius Gallus whose Erōtica Pathēmata was supposedly written as a source of obscure myths for elegists?",
    "answer": "PARTHENIUS (OF NICAEA)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Objects of what type were recovered from Maenalus by the Mantineans, found near a forge in Tegea by the Spartans, and brought to Troy after Helenus demanded that they be taken from the body of Pelops?",
    "answer": "BONES / SKELETONS (OF DEAD HEROES)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Around 475 B.C., on what island did the Athenian general Cimon claim to find the bones of Theseus, accurately reflecting their likely mythological location?",
    "answer": "SCYROS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What mythological figure’s bones were recovered from Maenalus by the Mantineans?",
    "answer": "ARCAS(’S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What foreign ruler landed at Demetrias and was beaten by Acilius Glabrio despite Aetolian support, forcing him to retreat home and eventually agree to the Treaty of Apamea after losing at Magnesia?",
    "answer": "ANTIOCHUS {III // THE GREAT}"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "During the Roman-Seleucid War, a Roman fleet off the coast of what town defeated a Seleucid fleet under the command of the Rhodian admiral Polyxenidas?",
    "answer": "MYONESSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Rhodian admiral fought on the Roman side at Myonessus after defeating a Phoenician navy under Hannibal at Side a month earlier?",
    "answer": "EUDAMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence: “Manifestum est paucissimōs esse quī ratiōne quōquō modō ūtī possint.”",
    "answer": "IT IS {CLEAR / PLAIN} THAT THERE ARE VERY FEW (MEN) WHO CAN USE REASON IN ANY WAY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence adapted from the Dē Bellō Cīvilī: “Ita loquitur Afrānius: nōn esse mīlitibus suīs ab eīs suscēnsendum, quod fidem ergā Pompēium cōnservāverint.”",
    "answer": "SOLDIERS FOR PRESERVING THEIR FAITH TOWARDS POMPEY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After he dreamt that a woman asked him to give her a home at Anaphe, who threw the Triton-given gift of a clod of earth into the sea, then returned home with the Argonauts he had once saved with a dove?",
    "answer": "EUPHEMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Euphemus was originally from what town at the tip of the Peloponnesus, which was celebrated as an entrance to the Underworld?",
    "answer": "TAENARUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Spartan leader led Euphemus’ descendants to the island Calliste, which he later renamed after himself?",
    "answer": "THERAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What ruler was slain by an Amal chieftain at the orders of the Eastern emperor who had made him patricius — Zeno — when his reign over Italy became troublesome in the 480s A.D.?",
    "answer": "ODO(V)ACER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Zeno had previously tried to take advantage of Theoderic the Amal by sending him against another Theoderic with what surname?",
    "answer": "STRABO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name any of the Ostrogothic rulers who came after Theoderic and sought to prevent Justinian’s generals from recapturing Italy.",
    "answer": "THEODAHAD / VITIGIS / ILDEBAD / ERARIC / TOTILA / TEIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What fate was inflicted on Grunnius Corocotta in the Testāmentum Porcellī and on a gigantic gift given to Domitian, though he had to call a council to figure out just how to do so in Juvenal’s Fourth Satire?",
    "answer": "(BEING) {COOKED / EATEN}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What contemporary of Tiberius describes an ideal where “at the table no one will recognize what he is eating”?",
    "answer": "(M. GAVIUS) APICIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work of Ausonius includes a description of the narrator giving instructions to a cook?",
    "answer": "EPHĒMERIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Used once after the verb form pudet by Tacitus, rarely with opus est, and often with the adjective dignus, what specific type of verb form is often found after adjectives like foedus and mīrābilis?",
    "answer": "ABLATIVE SUPINE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a form of pudet, say in Latin “A shameful crime has been committed.”",
    "answer": "PUDENDUM {SCELUS / FACINUS} {COMMISSUM / FACTUM / PATRĀTUM} EST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using the most common construction with dignus, say in Latin: “She is worthy of being spared, but not forgiven.”",
    "answer": "DIGNA EST CUI PARCĀTUR, SED NŌN (CUI) IGNOSCĀTUR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid est nōmen tibi? That is, what is your name?",
    "answer": "PLAYER SHOULD SAY THEIR NAME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid est nōmen moderātōrī?",
    "answer": "PLAYER SHOULD SAY THE MODERATOR’S NAME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid est nōmen magistrō tuō? Moderator should say: “Subsequent questions will count for points. Good luck and have fun!”",
    "answer": "CORRECT-SOUNDING]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Scattered nuts and coins, a spelt cake called the farreum lībum, and a basket carried by a boy called the camillus are all objects found at what type of Roman marriage ceremony?",
    "answer": "CONFARREĀTIŌ [PROMPT ON “WEDDING” BEFORE “WHAT TYPE”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the Roman confarreātiō, two children walked on each side of the bride and one in front, all of whom were required to be patrīmī et mātrīmī. What does this condition mean?",
    "answer": "THEIR FATHER AND MOTHER NEEDED TO BE LIVING"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "During the dēductiō of the bride, what early form of Italian poetry was sung to the Sabine god Talassio?",
    "answer": "FESCENNINE VERSES // VERSŪS FESCENNĪNĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Excluding prefixes, the English word “kerchief” derives from what two Latin words, one of which means “to cover” and the other of which is at the root of “chief,” “precipitate” and “capitulate”? OPERIŌ and CAPUT",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what two Latin nouns do we derive “jeopardy”? IOCUS and PARS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what two Latin words do we derive “hidalgo”? (ALI)QUIS and FILIUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who had to retrieve water from the Styx, fetch the beauty of Proserpina, and sort a room full of grain into piles, desperate to prove her love for her husband Cupid?",
    "answer": "PSYCHE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Psyche was unable to organize the cereals by herself and instead relied on the help of what animals? Advanced — Round 1",
    "answer": "ANT(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What object instructed Psyche on how to fetch Proserpina’s beauty from the Underworld?",
    "answer": "(A TALKING) TOWER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Works in what genre include a 135-section work by Jerome and the extant corpus of both Cornelius Nepos and Suetonius, all of whom wrote a Dē Virīs Illūstribus?",
    "answer": "BIOGRAPHY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "According to one of the biographies included in Suetonius’s collection, what author was born at Volaterrae and studied under Cornutus before publishing six works?",
    "answer": "PERSIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "According to one of Jerome’s biographies, what early Latin Christian author “wrote a dialogue representing a discussion between a Christian and a Gentile,” the Octāvius?",
    "answer": "MINUCIUS FELIX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Deterred from adding new centuries of knights when a whetstone was cut with a razor, what king saw another miracle in his own house happen to a son of Ocrisia, an omen interpreted by Tanaquil?",
    "answer": "TARQUINIUS PRISCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The original three centuries of knights had been created by Romulus. Two of them were the Titiēs and Lūcērēs; what was the third?",
    "answer": "RAMNĒS / RAMNĒNSĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Tarquinius Priscus claimed the throne, he won the people’s favor with a speech defending his right to rule; in this speech, he mentioned the example of what man, who was killed at Lavinium?",
    "answer": "TITUS TATIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What object indirectly caused a son of Portheus’s death, was built by Epeius, and was deceptively described as an offering to Minerva by Sinon, persuading Priam to welcome it?",
    "answer": "TROJAN HORSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What name is shared between this son of Portheus and the most famous of the Spartoi, who fathered Pentheus by Agave?",
    "answer": "ECHION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "During Sinon’s story, he claims that he was persecuted by Ulysses in alliance with what son of Thestor, who would later die of envy at a rival’s superior skill?",
    "answer": "CALCHAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Biological experiments are described as conducted either in vīvō or with what other Latin phrase, which denotes that they take place under artificial conditions and literally means “in glass”?",
    "answer": "IN VITRŌ [ACCEPT ENGLISH PRONUNCIATION]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin and English for the medical abbreviation q.s.",
    "answer": "{QUANTUM SATIS // QUANTUM SUFFICIT} – AS MUCH AS IS ENOUGH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "While reading Caesar, you encounter the word hīberna and wonder how it means “winter-quarters.” You check the dictionary and find that part of the entry for hībernus reads “hīberna, ōrum, n. (sc. castra), winter-quarters.” What is the Latin for the abbreviation sc., and what does it mean in context? Advanced — Round 1",
    "answer": "SCĪLICET, UNDERSTAND THAT THE FOLLOWING WORD IS IMPLIED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who occupied Cappadocia and Bithynia, executed Aquilius with molten gold, and ordered a massacre of 80,000 Romans in Asia in 88 B.C., leading to three wars against him and his kingdom of Pontus?",
    "answer": "MITHRIDATES {VI // THE GREAT // EUPATOR}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What general did Mithridates appoint to capture Greece on his behalf?",
    "answer": "ARCHELAUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What city did Archelaus capture with the help of a revolutionary named Aristion?",
    "answer": "ATHENS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Possibly from Pedum or Gabii, what “terse and elegant” author describes his love for Marathus and Nemesis in his elegies, which are often contrasted with those of Propertius?",
    "answer": "(ALBIUS) TIBULLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Tibullus’s most famous lover is Delia, though. What was her real name?",
    "answer": "PLANIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Tibullus’s corpus also contains six poems addressed to Neaera by what man?",
    "answer": "LYGDAMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following quote by Augustine into English: “Melius est reprehendant nōs grammaticī, quam nōn intellegant populī.” [pause] In Classical Latin this would have ut after melius est.",
    "answer": "// IT IS BETTER FOR THE GRAMMARIANS TO … THAN FOR THE PEOPLE TO …"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Rewrite that sentence to use infinitives rather than subjunctive verbs.",
    "answer": "MELIUS EST REPREHENDERE NŌS GRAMMATICŌS QUAM NŌN INTELLEGERE POPULŌS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate this punning sentence by Augustine, expressing a similar sentiment: “In nostrā disertitūdine vōs dēsertī eritis.” Keep in mind that disertus and facundus are synonyms.",
    "answer": "IN OUR ELOQUENCE YOU (ALL) {WILL BE // WILL HAVE BEEN} {DESERTED / ABANDONED}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who covered the years 78 to 67 B.C. in a work that showed the fullest development of the inconcinnitās and Thucydidean style of his monographs, Bellum Iugurthīnum and Bellum Catilīnae?",
    "answer": "(C.) SALLUST(IUS CRISPUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What work of Tacitus takes remarkably direct inspiration from a battle depicted in the Bellum Iugurthīnum while describing the Battle of Mons Graupius?",
    "answer": "AGRICOLA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which work of Tacitus is noteworthy for having far less inconcinnitās and a much more smooth and flowing style than any of his other works?",
    "answer": "DIALOGUS DĒ ŌRĀTŌRIBUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, a protege of Claudius Pompeianus and former schoolteacher, was asked to take the throne by Aemilius Laetus and Eclectus after his predecessor, Commodus, was murdered?",
    "answer": "PERTINAX"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Commodus was killed on the evening of December 31 in what year? Advanced — Round 1",
    "answer": "192 A.D."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Claudius Pompeianus had previously chosen to stay out of a plot against Commodus by Ummidius Quadratus, Appius Claudius Quintianus, and what woman?",
    "answer": "LUCILLA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in Latin using a gerund: “Nobody seemed to surpass Atalanta in running.”",
    "answer": "SUPERĀRE / VINCERE // ATALANTAE PRAESTĀRE / EXCELLERE}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in Latin using a gerund: “Nothing is more useful for learning than leisure.”",
    "answer": "NIHIL DISCENDŌ ŪTILIUS EST {ŌTIŌ // QUAM ŌTIUM}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using two compounds of eō — one as a gerund, the other as a gerundive — say in Latin: “With hope of returning having been removed, we will be prepared to undergo dangers.”",
    "answer": "PARĀBIMUR} AD PERICULA SUBEUNDA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What two Latin adjectives are technically neither singular nor plural, but dual, as evidenced by endings like -ōbus and their meanings of “both” and “two,” respectively? AMBŌ and DUO [ACCEPT IN EITHER ORDER]",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "If I say that I have ter dēnī of something, how many do I have?",
    "answer": "30 / THIRTY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Using the same formula for multiplication, say “four times two.”",
    "answer": "QUATER BĪNĪ [ALSO ACCEPT BIS QUATERNĪ]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Courted by both Poseidon and Apollo, what deity rejected their advances and swore an oath of chastity that earned her the right to be worshiped in every home and temple’s hearth?",
    "answer": "HESTIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Why is Hestia known as both the first- and last-born of Cronus and Rhea?",
    "answer": "SHE WAS THE FIRST TO BE BORN BUT LAST TO BE DISGORGED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Similarly, what daughter of Daedalion was pursued by both Apollo and Hermes?",
    "answer": "CHIONE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of the following verbs, which describes an action most likely performed by a stella: pugnō, luctor, micō, hiemō?",
    "answer": "MICŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of these represents an action most likely undertaken by an ancilla: equitō, mīlitō, dīmicō, dēspoliō, ministrō?",
    "answer": "MINISTRŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of the following verbs, which two represent an action most likely undertaken by a medīcus: sānō, medeor, lacessō, sepeliō, flagellō? SĀNŌ and MEDEOR",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What victor at Idistaviso, after being sent to Asia and quarreling with the governor of Syria, suddenly died in 19 A.D., leaving his wife Agrippina the Elder to bring his ashes to his uncle Tiberius? Advanced — Round 1",
    "answer": "GERMANICUS (JULIUS CAESAR)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was this governor of Syria?",
    "answer": "(CN. CALPURNIUS) PISO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Shortly before his death, Germanicus had provoked controversy by going on a tour of what place, which Augustus had forbidden senators from entering?",
    "answer": "EGYPT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author was an informer for Nero and the last man he appointed consul, but later began worshiping busts of Vergil and slavishly imitating him in a 17-book epic, Pūnica?",
    "answer": "(TIB. CATIUS ASCONIUS) SILIUS ITALICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Flavian poet composed an epic poem on frāternae aciēs with the aim of following its model, the Aeneid, “at a distance”?",
    "answer": "(P. PAPINIUS) STATIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What poet hailing from Setia was a decemvir who adapted the work of a Hellenistic epic poet?",
    "answer": "(C.) VALERIUS FLACCUS (BALBUS SETINUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What god fell hopelessly in love with Orchamus’s daughter Leucothoe and spurned Clytie, who transformed into a heliotrope pining after him?",
    "answer": "SOL / APOLLO / HELIOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Leucothoe was buried alive by her father for her love, but Sol transformed her into what type of tree after sprinkling her grave with nectar?",
    "answer": "FRANKINCENSE (TREE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The story of Sol and Leucothoe was told by what king’s daughters, who scorned the orgiastic rites of Bacchus in favor of their weaving?",
    "answer": "MINYAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When recognized by the spotter, perform the following command: Surge et ambulā in angulum pariētum.",
    "answer": "PLAYER GETS UP AND WALKS INTO A CORNER OF THE ROOM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now perform the following command, in celebration of the return of in-person spotter questions: Dīc esse bibendum et tunc pede līberō pulsā tellūrem.",
    "answer": "BEATS THE GROUND WITH THEIR FOOT}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now perform the following command: Fūnēs māchinae signatōriae leviter quatite. Advanced — Round 1",
    "answer": "ROUND TWO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What sort of animal prevented Ancaeus from tasting his wine, forced Nestor to spear-vault into a tree, gave a scar that Eurycleia recognized on Odysseus, and terrorized Mt. Erymanthus?",
    "answer": "BOAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Odysseus had gotten his scar while hunting with what maternal grandfather of his?",
    "answer": "AUTOLYCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How did Heracles manage to capture the Erymanthian boar?",
    "answer": "CHASED IT INTO SNOW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author depicted the complaint of a walnut tree in Nux, invoked a coprophilic bird in the Ībis, and wrote Epistulae ex Pontō — Letters from the Black Sea — and Trīstia to lament his exile at Tomi?",
    "answer": "(PUBLIUS) OVID(IUS NASO)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What work of “civil poetry” by Ovid is a poetical calendar meant to illustrate the myths and customs of Latium?",
    "answer": "FĀSTĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The Fāstī may have drawn on the research of what grammarian from Praeneste?",
    "answer": "(M.) VERRIUS FLACCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin noun, a cognate of the first part of Iuppiter, is regularly feminine when used of a specific or fixed time, but is otherwise one of the only fifth-declension nouns to be masculine?",
    "answer": "DIĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What grammatical term refers to nouns that vary in gender, such as diēs and epulum?",
    "answer": "HETEROGENEOUS / HETEROGENE(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What masculine noun regularly becomes neuter in the plural except when it means “topics of argument” or “passages from books”?",
    "answer": "LOCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin term for the system, made official in 180 B.C. by the Lēx Villia, which was circumvented by ambitious generals like Pompey who ignored the established prerequisites for holding offices.",
    "answer": "CURSUS HONŌRUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, who had started his career well before the minimum age requirements, was found mysteriously dead in 129 B.C., perhaps due to foul play from his wife Sempronia?",
    "answer": "(P. CORNELIUS) SCIPIO AEMILIANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Pompey was able to flout age and rank requirements due to the personal loyalty of his army, many of whom came from what specific region in Northeast Italy?",
    "answer": "PICENUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following Latin sentence into English: “Nisi Iūnōnem laesisset, Aenēās tot labōrēs nōn subīsset.” Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": "UNDERGONE SO MANY {LABORS / TOILS / HARDSHIPS}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of conditional would be used to say “If he were to hurt Juno, Aeneas would go through many labors”?",
    "answer": "HURTING… WOULD BE GOING…”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate the following sentence: “Sī quaerās cur vēnerim, nihil aliud dīcam quam mē vēnisse ut certāmen lūderem.”",
    "answer": "OTHER THAN THAT I CAME TO PLAY CERTAMEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What poet popularized a philosopher from Messina, criticized the faunī vātēsque who had written in Saturnians, and used his Hedyphaegetica and Annālēs to introduce dactylic hexameter?",
    "answer": "(QUINTUS) ENNIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Ennius versified the Aetolian campaign of Fulvius Nobilior with what fābula praetexta, his only known one aside from Sabinae?",
    "answer": "AMBRACIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What controversial claim did that philosopher from Messina, Euhemerus, make about the gods?",
    "answer": "FROM STORIES OF MORTALS [ACCEPT EQUIVS.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the Iliad, what Trojan ally tells a story involving the Solymi and the treachery of Anteia, then exchanges his 100-oxen-worth golden armor with the bronze armor of Diomedes?",
    "answer": "GLAUCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Diomedes opens their conversation by telling the story of how Lycurgus persecuted what god and his “nurses,” beating them with an ox-goad?",
    "answer": "DIONYSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What woman, surnamed Alcyone, features in a story about her husband and the Curetes told by Phoenix in Book 9 of the Iliad?",
    "answer": "CLEOPATRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin verb do we derive “jocund,” “aid,” and “adjutant,” the latter two of which are also clearly related to it in meaning?",
    "answer": "IUVŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Iuvō is at the root of the second half of “Gatorade,” whose spelling was changed to avoid marketing it as a medicinal beverage. What Latin noun gives us the first half of “Gatorade” and the word “lizard”?",
    "answer": "LACERTUS / LACERTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "“Gatorade” is a near rhyme with “Renegade,” the name of a popular TikTok song. “Renegade” obviously derives from negō, which is cognate with what defective Latin verb?",
    "answer": "AIŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb oblīviscor, give the 3rd person singular, imperfect subjunctive.",
    "answer": "OBLĪVISCERĒTUR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb ulciscor, give the 2nd person plural, pluperfect subjunctive. Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": "ULTĪ ESSĒTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb ōrdior, give the same form.",
    "answer": "ŌRSĪ ESSĒTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Disgruntled at his treatment in Antioch, what late emperor unwisely hastened across the Tigris River to face Shapur II, only to be killed near Ctesiphon, possibly by a Christian in his own ranks?",
    "answer": "JULIAN (THE APOSTATE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To what philosophical school, promoted by Plotinus and Porphyry and common among pagans in the late Empire, did Julian adhere?",
    "answer": "NEO-PLATONISM"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Julian’s predecessor, Constantius II, had won a major battle at Mursa against what usurper, who had overthrown his brother Constans?",
    "answer": "MAGNENTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What two Latin forms, which can be found before adjectives like necessārius to form their two-word comparatives and superlatives, are the comparative and superlative adverbs of magnus? MAGIS and MAXIMĒ",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Make the comparative adjective prior superlative.",
    "answer": "PRĪMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What are the two superlatives for the comparative adjective īnferior? ĪNFIMUS and ĪMUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, whose work was parodied by Eumolpus in the Satyricon, condemns the protagonists of his epic while praising Cato the Younger as a Stoic hero in the war between Caesar and Pompey?",
    "answer": "(M. ANNAEUS) LUCAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What protagonist, traveling alongside Giton, hears Eumolpus’s poetry in the Satyricon?",
    "answer": "ENCOLPIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "One of Lucan’s sources may be the lost Histories of what grandfather of his?",
    "answer": "SENECA THE ELDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who executed his predecessor’s architect Apollodorus of Damascus and generals Palma and Quietus, set up a cult for a drowned Bithynian youth, and connected the Solway Firth to the Tyne with a wall?",
    "answer": "HADRIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Hadrian was said to have become emperor thanks to the intervention of what woman, Trajan’s wife?",
    "answer": "(POMPEIA) PLOTINA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Apollodorus of Damascus angered Hadrian by criticizing what large temple, whose construction the emperor supervised between the Colosseum and the Temple of Peace?",
    "answer": "(TEMPLE OF) VENUS AND ROME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Note to players: This question has an extra clue. Which of these provinces was located furthest west: Pannonia Superior, Galatia, Crēta et Cȳrēnaica, and Armenia Maior? It bordered Dalmatia.",
    "answer": "PANNONIA SUPERIOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What modern-day country did the Romans call Cȳrēnaica? Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": "LIBYA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name either of the Roman provinces that lay to the south of Galatia, bordering on the Mediterranean Sea, when the empire was at its furthest extent around 117 A.D.. LYCIA & PAMPHYLIA or CILICIA",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What deity, mocked for the obscurity of her father Coeus by a sister of Pelops, was most offended by the idea that seven sons and seven daughters were better than her twins, Apollo and Artemis?",
    "answer": "LETO [ACCEPT “LATONA” BEFORE “ARTEMIS,” SINCE THE STORY IS FROM OVID]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Ovid’s account, Niobe interrupted a sacrifice to Latona that was set up by what daughter of Tiresias, said to rival her father in the gift of prophecy?",
    "answer": "MANTO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Coeus also fathered what other deity, who was pursued by Zeus and turned into a quail?",
    "answer": "ASTERIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who defeated Egyptians at Panium, alarming Pergamum, and allied with the Aetolians against Rome, though defeats at Myonessus and Magnesia severely harmed his Seleucid Empire?",
    "answer": "ANTIOCHUS {III // THE GREAT}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What consul, under whom Cato served as military tribune, defeated Antiochus at Thermopylae?",
    "answer": "(M.’) ACILIUS GLABRIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What naval commander from an island off the coast of Anatolia was put in command of Antiochus’ main fleet during the subsequent war?",
    "answer": "POLYXENIDAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "The words “tolle, lege” encouraged what author to abandon Manichaeism, which he had pursued after reading Cicero’s Hortēnsius, and write his Christian autobiography, the Confessions?",
    "answer": "(ST.) AUGUSTINE // (AURELIUS) AUGUSTINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what work does Augustine respond to accusations after Alaric’s sack of Rome that Christianity was causing the Roman Empire’s disintegration?",
    "answer": "DĒ CĪVITĀTE DEĪ / CITY OF GOD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name both of Augustine’s parents, one a pagan local official at Thagaste, the other a devout Christian whose death is told very movingly in Book 9 of the Confessions. PATRICIUS and MONICA",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What mythological pair, who met at Marathon when one tried to steal the other’s cattle, together carried off the queen Antiope and were trapped in the underworld by the Chairs of Forgetfulness? THESEUS and P(E)IRITHOUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was the wife of Pirithous that was abducted by the centaur Eurytion at their wedding?",
    "answer": "HIPPODAMIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Theseus and Pirithous kidnapped Helen, to what city in Attica did they take her?",
    "answer": "APHIDNAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Phrases meaning “from that point,” and “at that time,” “what news?,” and “two thousand soldiers” — inde locī, id temporis, quid novī, and duo mīlia mīlitum — all exhibit what use of the genitive? Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": "PARTITIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the genitive is often seen in words like capitis, maiestātis, and repetundārum?",
    "answer": "CHARGE / PENALTY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the genitive can be replaced by a prepositional phrase with ergā?",
    "answer": "OBJECTIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Vergil describes Dido’s flight from Tyre in book 1 of the Aeneid, he emphasizes her remarkable ability to organize the plan with what three-word phrase meaning “a woman was the leader of the deed”?",
    "answer": "DUX FĒMINA FACTĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "In book 6, the Sibyl warns Aeneas that entering the underworld is much easier than escaping with what three-word phrase? Nowadays, it idiomatically means “once you do this, there’s no turning back.”",
    "answer": "FACILIS DĒSCENSUS {AVERNŌ / AVERNĪ}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What far-north island fills in the blank of the Vergilian phrase ultima [blank], which is used today to describe any place that feels like an exciting or novel frontier? Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": "ROUND THREE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work, in which Photis bungles a potion, features the inset tale of Cupid and Psyche as heard by its protagonist, Lucius, while in the form of a donkey?",
    "answer": "(APULEIUS’S) METAMORPHŌSĒS / ASINUS AUREUS / THE GOLDEN ASS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Metamorphōsēs has a surprise ending where Lucius is initiated into the cult of what deity?",
    "answer": "ISIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Apuleius was persuaded to marry Pudentilla by what friend of his, who was her son?",
    "answer": "PONTIANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence from Latin to English: “Sīs fortior patre meō, cuius digitus in bellō caesus est.”",
    "answer": "(MAY YOU) BE BRAVER THAN MY FATHER, WHOSE FINGER WAS CUT (OFF) IN WAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this one: “Cum crūs amīsisset, tamen decem mīlia passuum Rōmam cucurrit.”",
    "answer": "ALTHOUGH HE HAD LOST HIS LEG, NEVERTHELESS HE RAN TEN MILES TO ROME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence adapted from Pliny the Elder: “Multum ad tuam glōriam rēfert, in quālēs tua virtūs casūs inciderit.”",
    "answer": "INTO WHAT SORT OF CIRCUMSTANCES YOUR VIRTUE HAS FALLEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who wondered why his head-sheep was lagging behind the rest of the flock, not realizing that the sheep was hiding his antagonist Outis, or “No-one,” who had blinded him?",
    "answer": "POLYPHEMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To weaken Polyphemus, Odysseus used the wine he got from what priest of Apollo at Ismarus?",
    "answer": "MARON"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What son of Eurymus had warned Polyphemus that someone named Odysseus would wound him?",
    "answer": "TELEMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What city, where a massacre was perpetrated in 215 A.D. by Caracalla, saw so-called “Donations” to Alexander Helios and the other children of Marc Antony by its queen, Cleopatra?",
    "answer": "ALEXANDRIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name both Alexander Helios’s twin sister and their brother who was born a few years later. CLEOPATRA SELENE and PTOLEMY PHILADELPHUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What general of Antony won a victory at Mt. Gindarus against the Parthians in 38 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(P.) VENTIDIUS (BASSUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What meaning is shared by the words dēlūbrum, fānum, aedēs in the singular, and templum?",
    "answer": "TEMPLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin noun, mostly synonymous with nemus, is used to refer to a grove or consecrated wood?",
    "answer": "LŪCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Etymologically, what is a nūmen, which metaphorically refers to divine power? Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": "A NOD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Reproached for a style of “sand without lime” by Caligula, who nearly condemned him to death, what author described the daily practice of Stoicism to his friend Lucilius in 124 Epistulae Mōrālēs?",
    "answer": "SENECA THE YOUNGER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Seneca wrote nine surviving works of what type of fābula, which are the only extant representatives of the genre, since Pacuvius and Accius are lost?",
    "answer": "FĀBULA(E) {COTHURNĀTA(E) / CRĒPIDĀTA(E)}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of Seneca’s tragedies, which shares its title with Ennius’s final work, is the only one without an extant Greek model?",
    "answer": "THYESTĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of the verbs suādeō, dēficiō, ignoscō, īrascor, and faveō, which does NOT take the dative, even though its meaning of “fail” might suggest that?",
    "answer": "DĒFICIŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in good Latin using parcō: “They are not spared.” You will need an impersonal passive.",
    "answer": "EĪS NŌN PARCITUR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in good Latin using mīnor: “I threaten them with death.”",
    "answer": "EĪS MORTEM MĪNOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Though he did nothing for his wife and daughter Prisca and Valeria, who was forced into a conference at Carnuntum in 308 when Galerius requested that he come out of retirement at Split?",
    "answer": "DIOCLETIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What modern day country was the home of Diocletian during his retirement?",
    "answer": "CROATIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After Diocletian’s death, Valeria and Prisca soon ended up at the court of what Caesar, who was defeated by Licinius and died in 313 A.D.?",
    "answer": "MAXIMINUS {DAIA / DAZA}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the classical equivalent of the form dūcier, which could be used in the sentences “He believed that he was being led to his death” or “He did not want to be led to his death.”",
    "answer": "DŪCĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the primary Latin form equivalent to the alternate form abūtēre, which appears in a famous Latin sentence.",
    "answer": "ABŪTĒRIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the primary Latin form equivalent to the alternate form levassō.",
    "answer": "LEVĀVERŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What group, which applied a name meaning “Beginner of Death” to an infant, included a man who tried to cannibalize Melanippus and a seer whose wife Eriphyle forced him to join Adrastus?",
    "answer": "SEVEN AGAINST THEBES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was this infant, who died at Nemea when he was left in a bed of parsley?",
    "answer": "OPHELTES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What old king of Argos, the father of Evadne, advised Polynices to bribe Eriphyle with the necklace of Harmonia? Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": "IPHIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin noun, in two very similar quotes by Vergil and Terence, follows either audentīs or fortīs and is said to “favor” them?",
    "answer": "FORTŪNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Give the idiomatic meaning of the Juvenalian quote frontis nulla fidēs. Note that frontis is an objective genitive.",
    "answer": "YOU SHOULDN’T TRUST APPEARANCES [ACCEPT EQUIVS.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the idiomatic meaning of this quote from Horace about the nature of travel: caelum nōn animum mūtant quī trans mare currunt.",
    "answer": "[ACCEPT EQUIVS.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Greek work inspired the plot of Niptra by Pacuvius and was translated after 272 B.C. by a Tarentine grammāticus named Livius Andronicus?",
    "answer": "ODYSSEY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What schoolteacher in the late Republic was known for forcing his students to learn Livius Andronicus and beating them when they failed?",
    "answer": "(L.) ORBILIUS (PUPILLUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which other play of Pacuvius also featured Ulysses as a key character?",
    "answer": "ARMŌRUM IŪDICIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Marcius Rex built the first high-level variety of what piece of infrastructure in 140 B.C., whose other examples include the Appia and the Tepula, known for its lukewarm waters?",
    "answer": "AQUEDUCT(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Augustus built the Aqua Alsietīna to host mock naval battles known by what Latin term?",
    "answer": "NAUMACHIA(E)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What name is shared between two aqueducts, one made during the reign of Claudius, which are surnamed Vetus and Nōvus?",
    "answer": "(AQUA) ANIŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who escaped to Camicus but was revealed when he passed a thread through a seashell, showing the same ingenuity as when he designed a hollow bull for Pasiphae and built the Labyrinth?",
    "answer": "DAEDALUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was the king of Camicus who sheltered Daedalus? His daughters soon killed Minos by scalding him in his bath.",
    "answer": "COCALUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Another account says that, after Icarus’s death, Daedalus arrived in what city, where he decorated a temple with the story of his life, though “his fatherly hands twice fell” when he tried to paint Icarus?",
    "answer": "CUMAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What name is shared between a consul who died at Cape Telamon and the co-consul of Manlius Vulso who invaded Africa but was soon locked in a spiky box and killed by the Carthaginians? Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": "(ATILIUS) REGULUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Cape Telamon came a year after the Romans signed a treaty with the Carthaginians setting their Spanish borders at what geographical feature?",
    "answer": "{EBRO / HIBERUS} RIVER"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "After what naval battle in 255 B.C., the year of Regulus’s capture, was the victorious Roman fleet annihilated by a storm?",
    "answer": "(BATTLE OF) CAPE HERMAEUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man was accused of trying to murder an Alexandrian envoy and poison his lover Clodia, leading to a slew of invective being delivered against her when Cicero defended him in a 56 B.C. speech?",
    "answer": "(M.) CAELIUS (RUFUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Cicero’s skill with invective was also displayed in his attacks on what freedman of Sulla in one of his early speeches?",
    "answer": "CHRYSOGONUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what speech, delivered in the interim between two of the Catilinarians, does Cicero humorously parody Cato the Younger’s Stoic beliefs while defending a client accused of electoral corruption?",
    "answer": "PRŌ MŪRĒNĀ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What river, a dry imitation of which was seen at Buthrotum, earned the wrath of Hephaestus and was scorched because it tried to drown Achilles on the Trojan plain?",
    "answer": "SCAMANDER / XANTHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Why had Scamander tried to drown Achilles?",
    "answer": "ACHILLES WAS FILLING HIS WATERS WITH CORPSES [ACCEPT OBV. EQUIVS.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Scamander was actually the progenitor of the Trojan race through what son, said in other accounts to have immigrated from Crete?",
    "answer": "TEUCER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What derivative of a Latin word for “to fold” refers to a person who assists or partners with another in committing a crime?",
    "answer": "ACCOMPLICE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What derivative of plicō is a synonym of the English word “braid”?",
    "answer": "PLEAT/PLAIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the words “comply,” “supply,” “reply,” and “apply,” which two derive from plicō? REPLY and APPLY",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Note to players: there will be an extra clue. Say in the best classical Latin: “I ran to the Forum of Augustus to see bigger temples.” Know that purpose clauses with a comparative are introduced by quō.",
    "answer": "TEMPLA VĪSUM // AD MAIŌRA TEMPLA VIDENDA}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A purpose clause introduced by quō is really a relative clause of purpose, where quō exemplifies what use of the ablative? Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": "DEGREE OF DIFFERENCE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now say in the best classical Latin: “I do not doubt that there are more temples in the Forum than in the Campus Martius.”",
    "answer": "TEMPLŌRUM SIT} IN FORŌ QUAM (IN) CAMPŌ MARTIŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "By wearing a cast to conceal a dagger and falsely promising to give the emperor a list of conspirators before stabbing him in the groin, what former butler was able to assassinate Domitian?",
    "answer": "STEPHANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "This conspiracy also may have involved Domitian’s wife Domitia. She was the daughter of what man, a star general in the East under Nero?",
    "answer": "(CN. DOMITIUS) CORBULO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The conspiracy also involved what Praetorian Prefect, whom Nerva reluctantly executed? Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": "SEMIFINAL ROUND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What case and number is lacking in words like faex and cor, has two possible forms in words like aetās or cīvitās, and in one of the declensions features the same vowel repeated twice in a row?",
    "answer": "GENITIVE PLURAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the Greek genitive plural ending, which is sometimes used with titles of works like the Georgics or the Metamorphoses?",
    "answer": "-ŌN / -ΩΝ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the Greek genitive singular ending of Styx?",
    "answer": "STYGOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A man with what cognōmen wrote a Saturnian line beginning “dabunt malum” before securing the exile to Utica of the author who had claimed that his family became consuls by fate?",
    "answer": "METELLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Naevius’s line “fātō Metellī Rōmae fīunt cōnsulēs” is preserved in a commentary on Cicero’s Verrines falsely ascribed to what scholar, who wrote five extant commentaries on Cicero speeches?",
    "answer": "(Q.) ASCONIUS (PEDIANUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which Plautine play alludes to an imprisoned poet, perhaps referencing Naevius?",
    "answer": "MĪLES GLŌRIŌSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who asked Zeus to make her son’s body never decay, even though his desire to marry a princess from Pessinus caused her to drive her son Attis mad and make him castrate himself?",
    "answer": "CYBELE / AGDISTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "From what sort of tree, which also grew on the grave of a Thracian princess loved by Demophon, was Attis’s mom Nana impregnated?",
    "answer": "ALMOND (TREE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Tantalus carved an image of Cybele on a rock near Mt. Sipylus?",
    "answer": "BROTEAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What woman, the mother of Iullus and Antyllus, navigated a trifecta of political marriages to populāris partisans before allying with her brother-in-law Lucius Antonius during the Perusine War?",
    "answer": "FULVIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name the first and second husbands of Fulvia, in order. (P.) CLODIUS PULCHER and (C.) SCRIBONIUS CURIO",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Scribonius Curio had died when he was sent to Africa to fight Juba I and what Roman governor?",
    "answer": "(P.) ATTIUS VARUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To what general category of meaning do the words conger, fiber, ēricius, pāpiliō, and ānser belong?",
    "answer": "ANIMALS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What meaning is shared by pērniciēs and strāgēs? Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": "DESTRUCTION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What meaning is shared by adȳtum and penētrāle?",
    "answer": "SANCTUARY // INNER CHAMBER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work, of which Pseudaeneas, Crās Crēdō Hodiē Nihil, and Sexagēsis are parts, was inspired by a philosopher from Gadara and written in 150 books of mixed prose and verse by Varro Reatinus?",
    "answer": "(VARRO REATINUS’S) SATURAE MENIPPEAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What group was attacked in the Trikaranos, one of the Menippean Satires?",
    "answer": "FIRST TRIUMVIRATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What woman, a personification of an abstract concept, appears in a Menippean Satire composed shortly after the fall of the Western Empire, wearing a garment that many people have torn pieces from?",
    "answer": "PHILOSOPHY / PHILOSOPHIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of soldiers proved ineffective at Panormus in 250 B.C. and later at Naragarra, where lanes were opened to allow these “Lucanian oxen” to harmlessly charge, unlike at Heraclea under Pyrrhus?",
    "answer": "ELEPHANT(S) // MEN CONTROLLING ELEPHANTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "As the Carthaginians marched towards Lake Trasimene in 217 B.C., how many elephants did Hannibal have left in his force?",
    "answer": "ONE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Livy, what Roman consul in 169 B.C. had to devise a complicated contraption to get elephants down Mount Olympus during a perilous 11-day march in the Third Macedonian War?",
    "answer": "(Q.) MARCIUS (PHILIPPUS) // (Q. MARCIUS) PHILIPPUS [LIVY AUC 44.5]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin word is the first word in the official Roman name of Gloucester, as well as that of Colchester and that of Cologne, referring to their status as Roman settlements in captured territory?",
    "answer": "COLŌNIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the shortened, one-word name of Gloucester.",
    "answer": "GLEVUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What county town in today’s East Midlands was known to the Romans as Colōnia Lindum?",
    "answer": "LINCOLN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What literary device is seen in the phrase “quod ā cultū atque hūmānitāte prōvinciae longissimē absunt,” where the nouns cultū atque hūmānitāte are like the noun-adjective pair hūmānō cultū? [cf. Amm. 15.11.4, which paraphrases the sentence and says “ab hūmāniōre cultū”]",
    "answer": "HENDIADYS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Besides the fact that cornus is metonymy for “javelin,” what literary device is seen in the line “pariter effūdit lacrimās cornumque sonantem”?",
    "answer": "ZEUGMA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What literary device is seen in the lines “nātumque in valle reductā [...] tālibus adfāta est dictīs sēque obtulit ultrō”?",
    "answer": "HYSTERON PROTERON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What land, through which the Phasis river flows, has a capital at Aea where a Thessalian foreigner fought men who sprung out of the ground and yoked two bulls who breathed fire? Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": "COLCHIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The night before Jason, the Thessalian foreigner, completed the tasks, he performed a sacrifice to Hecate, calling her by what name?",
    "answer": "BRIMO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After Medea had completely dismembered Absyrtus, Aeetes picked up the various body parts and buried them in what city, whose name derives from the “cuttings” of his body? TOMI [FROM τέμνω, CUT]",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What man, granted commission over a revolt in Faesulae to stop him from undoing Sulla’s reforms in his 78 B.C. consulship, started a revolt soon suppressed by Lutatius Catulus at Milvian Bridge?",
    "answer": "MARCUS AEMILIUS LEPIDUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, the loser at Lauro River, absorbed the remnants of the Lepidus rebellion?",
    "answer": "(QUINTUS) SERTORIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where was Lepidus’s ally, Junius Brutus, defeated by Pompey in 77 B.C.?",
    "answer": "MUTINA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author of a historical work spending 41 books on Augustus’s reign and a treatise proposing three new letters for the alphabet studied under a native of Patavium — Livy — before becoming emperor?",
    "answer": "CLAUDIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Claudius also defended Cicero against the son of what author, a notoriously critical native of Teate?",
    "answer": "(C.) ASINIUS POLLIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Who was the protagonist of Nero’s Troica, a retelling of the Trojan War?",
    "answer": "PARIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence from English into Latin: “Are you afraid to trust the words of the witness?”",
    "answer": "TIMĒS(NE) VERBĪS TESTIS CRĒDERE?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in the best Latin: “I said these things so that you would never think that you had been betrayed.”",
    "answer": "HAEC DĪXĪ NĒ UMQUAM PUTĀRĒS TĒ PRODITUM ESSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in the best classical Latin: “It will be allowed for me to be lazy provided that I work today.”",
    "answer": "MODO // TANTUM / ITA UT} HODIĒ LABŌREM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who gave the Balyra river its name after he threw an instrument into it, since after he lost a contest at Dorium in an attempt to lie with the Muses, he was stripped of his musical talent and sight??",
    "answer": "PHILAMMON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in derivation between “amenity” and “amenable,” the second of which is cognate with “demeanor” and “promenade.” AMOENUS (PLEASANT) and {MĪNOR (THREATEN) / MĪNAE (THREATS)}, RESPECTIVELY Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in derivation between “toil” meaning “hard work” and the rare word “toil” meaning “net,” the second of which is cognate with “toilet.” TUNDŌ (BEAT) and {TEXŌ (WEAVE) / TĒLA (WEB)}, RESPECTIVELY",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in derivation between “scourge” and “scour,” the second of which is cognate with “proxy.” CŌRIUM (SKIN) and CŪRA (CARE), RESPECTIVELY",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following sentences adapted from Cicero, which I shall read twice, then answer in Latin the question that follows. There will be another clue after the question. Putō Crassum nōn moritūrum fuisse, sī huic ōminī pāruisset: cum ad Syriam proficīscerētur, quīdam mercātor, fīcōs vēndēns urbe Caunō dēlātās, clāmitābat “Cauneās! Cauneās!” Monitus est hōc ōmine Crassus, cavēret nē īret. The question: Quid ēvēnisset Crassō, sī ōminī pāruisset? [pause] Your answer should contain a verb in the pluperfect subjunctive.",
    "answer": "[ALSO ACCEPT “NN MORITŪRUS FUIT // VĪCTŪRUS FUIT” ETC. BEFORE THE HINT]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The word shouted by the merchant, Cauneae, is a proper adjective used as a substantive. What did the merchant intend for it to mean?",
    "answer": "FIGS FROM (THE CITY OF) CAUNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The last sentence of the passage suggests that the exclamation of “Cauneās!” was taken as an omen because it sounded like what three-word phrase addressed to Crassus? You have forty seconds.",
    "answer": "CAVĒ NĒ EĀS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In a 170-chapter work, who gives charms to cure a dislocation and advises selling both scrap metal and old slaves, showing rustic wisdom mixed with the ultra-conservative values he displayed as censor?",
    "answer": "(M. PORCIUS) CATO THE ELDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What imperial author extensively draws upon the Catonian ideal of a vir bonus dīcendī perītus in the 12th and final book of his magnum opus?",
    "answer": "(M. FABIUS) QUINTILIAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Though Cato refused to name major commanders in his Orīginēs, he did name what valiant soldier, whose brave deeds he compared to Leonidas in one of the extant fragments of the work?",
    "answer": "(Q.) CAEDICIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Macareus exclaimed “Why does a Trojan vessel now carry a Greek?” on seeing what son of Adamastus, who joined Aeneas’s crew after Ulysses left him at Polyphemus’s island?",
    "answer": "ACHAEMENIDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Near the land of the Cyclopes, the crew notices smoking Mt. Etna, which was said to have buried what giant struck down by Athena after fleeing Sicily during the Gigantomachy?",
    "answer": "ENCELADUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After sailing away from the Cyclopes, the crew immediately arrives at what island at the entrance to the bay of Syracuse, to which the river Alpheius had once found a way from Elis to pursue Arethusa? Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": "ORTYGIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What military office created by Gallienus, which Probus and Aurelian held before becoming emperor, shares its name with a position held by Aebutius Elva in 496 B.C. and by Minucius Rufus in 217 B.C.?",
    "answer": "COMMANDER” BEFORE “SHARES ITS NAME”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the late empire, Stilicho rose to what supreme military office, which commanded both the cavalry and the infantry?",
    "answer": "MAGISTER UTRĪUSQUE MĪLITIAE // MASTER OF EACH ARMY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Alaric first threatened Rome, he was similarly made magister utrīusque mīlitiae, while what brother-in-law of his became Count of the Domestics? Moderator should say: “All challenges on toss-ups 1 through 19 must be resolved before toss-up 20 is read. If any players or coaches would like to lodge a challenge, please speak up now.”",
    "answer": "ATHAULF"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which of the following Latin phrases is most similar to clāvam extorquēre Herculī in its idiomatic meaning: oleum addere camīnō, ab asinō lānam, in flagrante dēlictō, cum tacent clāmant?",
    "answer": "AB ASINŌ LANAM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Latin phrase plays off of dating systems to express that something is not possible and emphatically means “never”?",
    "answer": "AD KALENDĀS GRAECĀS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What other Latin phrase, which literally means “you are weaving a little rope out of sand,” is also used to indicate the pursuit of something impossible? Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": "FINAL ROUND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "“Who was Hecuba’s mother?” was a trivia question proposed to guests by what emperor, whose reign saw the revolt of Florus and Sacrovir and the victories of Dolabella and Blaesus over Tacfarinas?",
    "answer": "TIBERIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What 3-word Latin phrase, similar but not identical to a famous quote from tragedy, did Tiberius supposedly use as his motto?",
    "answer": "ODERINT DUM PROBENT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Like Julius Florus and Julius Sacrovir, what two chiefs of the Treveri, both of whom have Julius in their name, later worked with Julius Civilis to rebel against Vespasian? JULIUS CLASSICUS and JULIUS TUTOR",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the words “parody,” “disparage,” “apparel,” and “pair,” which does not belong, because it does not even derive from Latin?",
    "answer": "PARODY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the words “satire,” “imposthume,” “affidavit,” “ague,” and “ditty,” which does not derive from Latin?",
    "answer": "IMPOSTHUME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the military ranks “admiral,” “colonel,” “sergeant,” “commodore,” and “lieutenant,” which does not derive from Latin, since it comes from an Arabic word for a military leader?",
    "answer": "ADMIRAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the Iliad, who vowed to sacrifice a hundred lambs before striking a dove to win the archery contest at Patroclus’ funeral games, after which he returned to his homeland Crete alongside Idomeneus?",
    "answer": "MERIONES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What item from Eleon did Meriones give to Odysseus, which was originally stolen by Odysseus’ grandfather Autolycus?",
    "answer": "AMYNTOR’S HELMET [PROMPT ON “HELMET”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Meriones was responsible for some of the most cruel wounds in the Iliad. Who was the builder of Paris’ ship who was struck in the right buttock?",
    "answer": "PHERECLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Writing perhaps to celebrate Claudius’ invasion of Britain, what author provides fabulous descriptions of distant or scarcely known regions in his Dē Sitū Orbis or Chōrographia?",
    "answer": "POMPONIUS MELA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Upon what first-century Greek geographer from Amasea did Pomponius base much of his work?",
    "answer": "STRABO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What historical figure, who is better known for his military and political exploits, drew up a gigantic map of the entire world accompanied by commentāriī? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "(MARCUS VIPSANIUS) AGRIPPA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the words spūma, glaeba, manicae, plānitiēs, and alvus, which is being described in the following sentence: Cum salum aestuet, hanc māteriem albam in marī videās.",
    "answer": "SPŪMA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the words frūx, favīlla, formīdō, frūstum, and fūcus, which is being described in the following sentence: Est māteriēs ātra et saepe incandēscēns quae post incendium superest.",
    "answer": "FAVĪLLA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the words ammentum, acerra, anhēlitus, annōna, and antemna, which is being described in the following sentence: Hoc saepe, ut Ovidiānīs verbīs ūtar, “ē lassō venit ōre” Harvard 2022 Adv Fin Customs Visual",
    "answer": "ANHĒLITUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "I will now hand out materials for a visual question. At my signal, you will have 15 seconds to open and examine them, after which I will read the question. Pictured are examples of four types of Roman wall construction techniques, which are all named a different type of opus. Please identify the type of opus exemplified by panel A, named for its resemblance to a net.",
    "answer": "(OPUS) RĒTICULĀTUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Identify the type of opus exemplified by panel B, named for the haphazard placement of the uncut stones that make it up.",
    "answer": "(OPUS) INCERTUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Identify the type of opus exemplified by panel D, named for a Roman province featuring many examples of it on monumental works.",
    "answer": "(OPUS) AFRICĀNUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What genre did Cicero hope would be an opus ōrātōrium maximē, criticizing writers such as Gaius Fannius and Licinius Macer while giving higher praise to Coelius Antipater’s 7-book monograph?",
    "answer": "HISTORY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Gaius Fannius was the son-in-law of what man, a member of the Scipionic Circle who, like Scipio himself, was accused of writing Terence’s comedies for him?",
    "answer": "(C.) LAELIUS (SAPIENS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "In the same passage of Cicero, he remarks that what Roman historian “endeavors at something childish, such that he seems to have read only Clitarchus and no other Greek”?",
    "answer": "(L. CORNELIUS) SISENNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What office, aided by the curātor dē Minuciā, was abused to cause Cleander’s death and held by Gaius Turranius, whose time as prefect of Egypt taught him the supply chain that helped Rome’s poor?",
    "answer": "PRAEFECTUS ANNŌNAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To what prefecture, which originated in the monarchy and was held by Lucretius Tricipitinus, did Augustus appoint Messalla, only to have him retire after six days?",
    "answer": "PRAEFECTUS URBĪ // URBAN PREFECT(URE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, who may have been praefectus urbī but is listed by Livy as a praefectus annōnae, exposed Spurius Maelius for treason while making his own distribution of grain in a public capacity? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "(L.) MINUCIUS (ESQUILINUS AUGURINUS) [NO RELATION TO CURĀTOR DĒ MINUCIĀ]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Note to players: there will be an extra clue after two readings. Say in Latin: “That sea is too wide to be crossed.” You can translate this sentence using a “quam ut” construction.",
    "answer": "ILLUD MARE LĀTIUS EST QUAM {UT / QUOD} {TRANSEĀTUR / TRANSICIĀTUR}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using the word ante, say in good classical Latin: “She will not return home until she finds her brother.”",
    "answer": "NŌN ANTE DOMUM {REDĪBIT / REVERTĒTUR} QUAM FRĀTREM {INVENIET / INVĒNERIT}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence from English into Latin, using the equivalent within indirect discourse of a future perfect indicative: “He said that whoever caught a dove would receive a reward.”",
    "answer": "{ACCEPTŪRUM / RĒCEPTŪRUM} (ESSE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What island — home to Hyllus’s mother, Melite — served as the refuge of a Euboean woman who had nursed Dionysus and the adopted homeland of natives of Hypereia who were led by Nausithous?",
    "answer": "SCHERIA / DREPANE / PHAEACIA / CORFU"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Nausithous led the Phaeacians from Hypereia since they were being harassed by what neighbors?",
    "answer": "CYCLOPES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Nausithous died to Apollo on the day of his wedding?",
    "answer": "RHEXENOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What region was the destination of a 417 A.D. voyage described in the poem Dē Reditū Suō, featured a river described in an epyllion by Ausonius, and was the site of Ausonius’s birth?",
    "answer": "GAUL / GALLIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Namatianus’s Dē Reditū Suō claims that what man burned the Sibylline Books, even though his contemporary Claudian calls him a general as great as Scipio Africanus in the Dē Bellō Gothicō?",
    "answer": "STILICHO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What other late Christian author spent most of his life in Gaul, studying at Bordeaux and living for a time in Tours, where he met St. Martin and wrote his Life?",
    "answer": "SULPICIUS SEVERUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Paid 10,000 talents to restore Ptolemy Auletes to the throne, what client of Pompey became consul in 58 B.C. as a reward for actions as tribune in 67, when he passed a law to deal with the scourge of piracy?",
    "answer": "(A.) GABINIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What explanation had the Senate earlier given for forbidding Pompey from restoring Auletes to the throne with Roman military power?",
    "answer": "THEY SAID THE SIBYLLINE BOOKS FORBADE IT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Also in 67 B.C., another tribune, Gaius Cornelius, passed a law mandating that holders of what position follow the edicts they were required to lay down when they took office?",
    "answer": "PRAETOR(SHIP)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What three-letter Latin word ending, derived from a one-word Latin fraction, is used in other one-word fractions that have a denominator of twelve in their simplest form, like the words for 5/12 and 7/12? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "-UNX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Just as deunx is derived from dē and uncia – subtracting 1/12 from 1 – the fraction dōdrāns is ultimately derived from dē and what other one-word fraction?",
    "answer": "QUADRĀNS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Count from 1/12 to 11/12 in one-word Latin fractions. Your answer will include the fractions uncia, quadrāns, dodrāns, and deunx. You have 60 seconds.",
    "answer": "SEPTŪNX, BĒS / BESSIS, DŌDRĀNS, DEXTĀNS, DEUNX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who won his kingdom after defeating the invading Idas, was suckled by a doe and named for the animal, and seized the infant Orestes to force the Greeks to heal a wound from Achilles’ spear?",
    "answer": "TELEPHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Telephus originally had come to Teuthrania in search of what woman, his mother?",
    "answer": "AUGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What king’s shepherds found the infant Telephus on Mount Parthenius and gave him his name?",
    "answer": "CORYTHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following sentences adapted from Tacitus’s Agricola, which I shall read twice, then answer in English the questions that follow. Domitiānus hunc rērum cursum, quamquam nūllā verbōrum iactantiā in epistulīs Agricolae auctum, fronte laetus, pectore ānxius excēpit. Sciēbat dērīsuī fuisse nūper falsum ē Germāniā triumphum, ēmptīs hominibus quōrum habitūs in captīvōrum speciem fōrmārentur: at nunc vēram victōriam ingentī fāmā celebrārī. The question: What was Domitian’s mood when he heard of Agricola’s victories?",
    "answer": "HAPPY ON THE OUTSIDE, NERVOUS ON THE INSIDE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What had been the reaction to Domitian’s triumph over the Germans?",
    "answer": "IT HAD BEEN RIDICULED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How did Domitian fake his triumph?",
    "answer": "BY BUYING PEOPLE AND DRESSING THEM LIKE CAPTIVES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What work rejects the “words that persecuted Lycambes” of the Parian poet that inspired it, but wishes a shipwreck on a bad poet, depicts the witch Canidia, and playfully mocks Maecenas, its author’s patron?",
    "answer": "(HORACE’S) EPODES / IAMBĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Who is this poetaster who receives an inverted propempticon in the Epodes?",
    "answer": "MAEVIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "About what man does Horace write that his whole life “stands before one’s eyes, as if it were painted on a votive tablet”?",
    "answer": "(C.) LUCILIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin noun is the O in Frederick III’s motto A.E.I.O.U. — Austriae est imperāre [blank] universō — and appears in papal blessings addressed “urbī et [blank],” “to the city and to the world”?",
    "answer": "ORBĪ / ORBIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Catholic depictions of the crucifixion of Jesus often bear a titulus on the cross reading simply INRI. What is the full Latin for this abbreviation? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "IĒSUS NAZARĒNUS RĒX IUDAEŌRUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin abbreviation used in place of the English abbreviation B.C. for expressing the year relative to Jesus’s birth.",
    "answer": "A.C.N."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What deity was supposed to be the heir to Zeus until he was distracted with toys and carried away, after which Athena could only rescue his heart from the Titans who had torn him into pieces?",
    "answer": "ZAGREUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was abandoned by his mother because she feared her father Crotopus, and was eventually shredded to pieces by dogs?",
    "answer": "LINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In order to overtake Arcadia, Pelops pretended friendship with what king, whom he had dismembered and scattered his limbs across the land?",
    "answer": "STYMPHALUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Note to players: there will be an extra clue after two readings. Translate the following line of poetry: “Exoritur clāmorque virum clangorque tubārum.” Note that virum is genitive plural.",
    "answer": "(BOTH) THE SHOUTING OF MEN AND THE CLANG OF TRUMPETS (A)RISE(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Translate the following lines of poetry, which I will hand out on paper. Keep in mind that a classicum is a war trumpet. You have sixty seconds. “Sēcūrōs cēpisse pudet cum coniuge somnōs, / ēque tuō, quatiunt miserum cum classica mundum, / surrēxisse sinū.”",
    "answer": "RISEN FROM YOUR BOSOM, WHEN WAR TRUMPETS SHAKE THE MISERABLE WORLD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The sentence “Coeperat trepidus īnvīsā terrā dēcēdere” can be rearranged into a well-formed hexameter line that has no elisions and begins with coeperat. Do so. You have eighty seconds. Moderator should say: “All challenges on toss-ups 1 through 19 must be resolved before toss-up 20 is read. If any players or coaches would like to lodge a challenge, please speak up now.”",
    "answer": "COEPERAT INVĪSĀ TREPIDUS DĒCĒDERE TERRĀ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After defeating Victor to recover Gaul, what Frankish general found the hanging corpse of the young emperor Valentinian II and decided to raise the rhetorician Eugenius to the purple?",
    "answer": "ARBOGAST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Victor was the son of what other usurper, who was surrendered by his own troops in 388 A.D.?",
    "answer": "MAGNUS MAXIMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Early in Valentinian II’s life, his regents were his mother and another Frankish general. Name either. ",
    "answer": "JUSTINA or MEROBAUDES Advanced — Finals"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man’s kidnapping of Pelops’s son Chrysippus cursed him to die at the Cleft Way at the hands of his own son, Oedipus?",
    "answer": "LAIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Oedipus encountered Laius, he was ironically fleeing from what city in order to avoid murdering the people he thought were his parents?",
    "answer": "CORINTH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Before kidnapping Chrysippus, Laius had spent his time teaching the boy what skill, which Amphitryon is also said to have taught to Heracles?",
    "answer": "CHARIOT-DRIVING [ACCEPT OBV. EQUIVS.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in Latin: “Let it snow today.”",
    "answer": "HODIĒ NINGAT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in Latin, with only two words: “The dew will fall tomorrow.”",
    "answer": "CRĀS RŌRĀBIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in good Latin, using four words: “It has been thundering for three days now.”",
    "answer": "TRĒS IAM DIĒS TONAT [MUST BE PRESENT TENSE]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work provides 29 reasons not to fear death, describes how dreams come from simulācra, and expounds on the atomic theory of Epicurus in six books of didactic poetry by Lucretius?",
    "answer": "DĒ RRUM NTR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What other Latin noun describes the random “swerve” in atoms that accounts for free will?",
    "answer": "CLĪNĀMEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To what man is the Dē Rērum Nātūrā dedicated?",
    "answer": "(C.) MEMMIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between ter and vēr. THRICE // THREE TIMES and SPRING (RESPECTIVELY)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between ōrō and ovō. PRAY / BEG / PLEAD and EXULT / REJOICE / TRIUMPH (RESPECTIVELY)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between pix and vix. PITCH / TAR and HARDLY / SCARCELY / BARELY (RESPECTIVELY) Advanced — Round 1",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Saoterus, Perennis, and Cleander all effectively controlled the empire during the reign of what man, who preferred to kill ostriches and other animals in the arena while impersonating Hercules?",
    "answer": "COMMODUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name any two of the people who participated in Commodus’s assassination: his mistress, his chamberlain, his wrestling partner, or his praetorian prefect.",
    "answer": "ANY TWO OF: MARCIA; ECLECTUS; NARCISSUS; (Q. AEMILIUS) LAETUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How many consulships was Cleander said to have sold in one day?",
    "answer": "TWENTY-FIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whose banishment to Corsica by Claudius — where he wrote two consolations — probably inspired his mocking description of the emperor’s deification in the Apocolocyntosis?",
    "answer": "(L. ANNAEUS) SENECA THE YOUNGER [PROMPT ON “SENECA”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Despite his bad relationship with Claudius, Seneca the Younger became the tutor of Nero and wrote what work advising Nero to act with philanthropic benevolence towards his subjects?",
    "answer": "DĒ CLĒMENTIĀ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Some, however, believe that Seneca the Younger loosely alludes to Nero’s ungratefulness in what seven-book work dedicated to Aebutius Liberalis?",
    "answer": "DĒ BENEFICIĪS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After refusing to make peace at Nicaea, what king was defeated at a site known as “Dog’s Heads,” showing the inferiority of the phalanx to the maniple and ending the Second Macedonian War?",
    "answer": "PHILIP V (OF MACEDON)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "After his victory at Cynoscephalae, Flamininus declared freedom for all Greeks at what festival?",
    "answer": "ISTHMIAN GAMES"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What consul of 200 B.C. had started the Second Macedonian War, but suffered a defeat at Lyncestis the very next year?",
    "answer": "(P. SULPICIUS) GALBA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin noun with what meaning is at the root of “pilgrim,” “peregrination,” and “agrarian”?",
    "answer": "AGER – FIELD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin noun with what meaning is at the ultimate root of “age” and “eternal”?",
    "answer": "AEVUM – AGE / LIFETIME / GENERATION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin verb with what meaning is at the root of “aim”?",
    "answer": "AESTIMŌ – ESTIMATE / RECKON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What couple’s marriage was arranged at the cave of Macris by Arete after her husband, Alcinoüs, vowed to protect them from the pursuing Colchians on the condition that they got married? JASON and MEDEA",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What aunt of Medea purified the couple for the murder of Medea’s brother, Absyrtus?",
    "answer": "CIRCE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "While some accounts credit Medea with killing the bronze giant Talos, others give this honor to what Malian archer, the father of Philoctetes? Advanced — Round 1",
    "answer": "POEAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Rēctor, cūstōs, and monitor are all alternative names of what enslaved person, who would keep their assigned boy out of harm and accompany him to and from school?",
    "answer": "PAEDAGŌGUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The enslaved people usually enlisted as a paedagōgus would be expected to know what language, to prevent the children from forgetting what their nurse had taught them?",
    "answer": "GREEK"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What word would a boy use to address his paedagōgus? This may be related to the fact that a paedagōgus had the right to compel obedience by mild punishments.",
    "answer": "DOMINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of clause is used as an alternative to the future passive infinitive — where it is introduced by fore ut — but more often comes after fīō, ēveniō, or accidō?",
    "answer": "SUBSTANTIVE CLAUSE OF RESULT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the phrase “sciō fore ut vincar,” “fore” stands in for what two-word form?",
    "answer": "FUTŪRUM ESSE [MUST BE NEUTER]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What word can regularly introduce a substantive clause meaning “the fact that,” which explains why it often introduces indirect speech in post-classical Latin?",
    "answer": "QUOD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Because Sisyphus saw the abduction of Aegina, Zeus sent what god to carry him off to the Underworld, only for Sisyphus to tie him up and prevent all mortals from dying?",
    "answer": "THANATOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Sisyphus later avoided death again by having what wife of his not perform the proper burial rites for him? She is sometimes said to be the dimmest star of the Pleiades.",
    "answer": "MEROPE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Another story of Thanatos takes place in what Thessalian city, where he took a woman to the Underworld in place of her husband?",
    "answer": "PHERAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "During what conflict was Marius’s advice ignored by both Rutilius Lupus and Lucius Cato, causing them to succumb to the Marsi, one of many Italian tribes struggling for equal citizenship?",
    "answer": "SOCIAL / MARSIC WAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Marsic leader led the aforementioned attacks against Lupus and Cato?",
    "answer": "(Q.) {POPPAEDIUS / POMPAEDIUS} SILO"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Marius’s unwillingness to simply be put out to pasture was demonstrated clearly in 87 B.C. when he convinced what tribune to transfer Sulla’s Mithridatic command to him?",
    "answer": "(P.) SULPICIUS RUFUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give a Latin adverb meaning “little by little.”",
    "answer": "[SEE BELOW] [DO NOT READ ANSWERS UNTIL AFTER B1]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give another. Advanced — Round 1",
    "answer": "PAULĀTIM / GRADĀTIM / PEDETEMPTIM / PEDETENTIM / SĒNSIM / MODERĀTIM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin noun and verb, along with their meanings, at the root of the adverb pedetentim, one of the words meaning “little by little.” PĒS – FOOT and TENDŌ – STRETCH / REACH",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What scholar, to whom Trajan granted the iūs trium līberōrum, spoke of various poets in his Dē Vīrīs Illūstribus and delved into the lives of 12 emperors in his Dē Vītā Caesarum?",
    "answer": "(C.) SUETONIUS (TRANQUILLUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "To what praetorian prefect and patron did Suetonius dedicate his Dē Vītā Caesarum?",
    "answer": "(C.) SEPTICIUS CLARUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Suetonius’s Life of Vergil seems to have been a major source for what 4th-century commentator, a teacher of Jerome and Servius?",
    "answer": "(AELIUS) DONATUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What empire defeated Roman forces at Rhandeia in 62 A.D. and placed Tiridates I on the throne of Armenia, a region that often served as a buffer between them and Rome to the west?",
    "answer": "PARTHIANS // PARTHIAN EMPIRE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What star general of Nero in the East, and future father-in-law of Domitian, avenged the defeat at Rhandeia and made peace with the Parthian king Vologeses I?",
    "answer": "(CN. DOMITIUS) CORBULO"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "During the reign of which Roman emperor did the Parthian Empire give way to the Sassanids?",
    "answer": "SEVERUS ALEXANDER // ALEXANDER SEVERUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which of the following mottoes, if any, is NOT associated with U.S. currency: “Novus ōrdō saeclōrum,” “Annuit coeptīs,” “Ē plūribus ūnum,” or “Fideī dēfēnsor”?",
    "answer": "FIDEĪ DĒFĒNSOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What was the Latin motto of the Royal Stuart dynasty of Scotland, appearing on coins minted in 1578 and 1580?",
    "answer": "NĒMŌ MĒ IMPŪNE LACESSIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What two-word phrase, an expression of stability, integrity and tranquil equanimity, was the motto of Elizabeth I?",
    "answer": "SEMPER EADEM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Chloreus’s golden armor and Arruns’ prayer to Apollo sealed the fate of what ally of Turnus, a warrior queen who led the Volsci?",
    "answer": "CAMILLA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Camilla had been under the protection of Diana ever since what father of hers prayed to Diana before throwing her across the Amasenus river?",
    "answer": "METABUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What nymph did Diana have immediately avenge Camilla’s death by killing Arruns?",
    "answer": "OPIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, the subject of a funeral epigram by Domitius Marsus, discussed conquering a puer dēlicātus named Marathus and came to prefer Nemesis to his original lover Delia? Advanced — Round 1",
    "answer": "TIBULLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Horace, Tibullus had an unhappy love for what woman, though we never hear of her in Tibullus's own corpus?",
    "answer": "GLYCERA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the so-called Corpus Tibulliānum are 5 poems of Sulpicia which are addressed to what man?",
    "answer": "CERINTHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: “Audendō virtūs crēscit, morandō timor.”",
    "answer": "{VIRTUE / BRAVERY / MANLINESS} GROWS BY DARING, FEAR (GROWS) BY DELAYING"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: “Sapientiā nōbīs opus est ad regendōs animī mōtūs.”",
    "answer": "CORRECT} THE {MOVEMENTS / IMPULSES / PASSIONS} OF THE MIND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English, keeping in mind that posse is a subjective infinitive: “Multīs hominibus timendī causās attulit timērī posse.” Advanced — Round 1",
    "answer": "ROUND TWO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following ancient cities was located farthest west: Massilia, Hadrumetum, Aquae Sulis, Aquincum, Olympia?",
    "answer": "AQUAE SULIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of those same cities was located farthest south?",
    "answer": "HADRUMETUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following ancient cities, if any, was NOT located in Gaul: Cenabum, Genava, Bibracte, Arelate, Gesoriacum?",
    "answer": "ALL IN GAUL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What native of Arezzo gave a farm in Sabine country to Horace and requested that Vergil compose the Georgics while acting as an influential patron of the arts during the reign of Augustus?",
    "answer": "(C. CILNIUS) MAECENAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, who first loved Lycinna, then turned to Hostia, was also patronized by Maecenas?",
    "answer": "(SEX.) PROPERTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What minor author of Thyestes and Dē Morte, best known as the publisher of Vergil’s Aeneid, was also patronized by Maecenas?",
    "answer": "(L.) VARIUS RUFUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What use of the subjunctive is contained in the mottoes of the University of California, Amherst College, the state of Vermont, and the University of Chicago — crēscat scientia, vīta excōlātur?",
    "answer": "JUSSIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What use of the subjunctive is found in the motto of North Dakota?",
    "answer": "PURPOSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What use of the genitive is found in the motto of the University of Georgia?",
    "answer": "OBJECTIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Every year, after wetting their wings in the Aesepus river, flocks of birds sprinkled water on the grave of what Ethiopian king, whom Achilles killed during the Trojan War?",
    "answer": "MEMNON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What goddess of the dawn created dew when she shed tears over the death of her son, Memnon?",
    "answer": "EOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What son of Nestor did Memnon kill during the Trojan War?",
    "answer": "ANTILOCHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What series of conflicts are described here? The timely arrival of Archidamus kept the enemy busy during the first iteration. The second one began when Publilius Philo besieged Naples, and saw two major Roman defeats. The third one culminated in a dēvōtiō at Sentinum.",
    "answer": "SAMNITE WARS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Archidamus was the first of four kings summoned to Italy by what city, a colony of Sparta? Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": "TARENTUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "While besieging Naples, Publilius Philo held what office for the first time ever?",
    "answer": "PROCONSUL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Named for the springs of Oceanus, who carried the thunderbolts of Zeus after he threw off his rider on the way to Olympus because of the sting of a gadfly?",
    "answer": "PEGASUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What brother of Pegasus, whose name means “Golden Sword,” was born alongside him from Medusa’s severed head?",
    "answer": "CHRYSAOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On what mountain, home to the Muses, did Pegasus create a spring named Hippocrene with the stamp of his hoof?",
    "answer": "HELICON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What English word, when derived from sūs, means “tarnish” or “make dirty,” but when derived from solum, means “the upper layer of earth in which plants grow”?",
    "answer": "SOIL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What English word, when derived from a Latin word meaning “to fall,” refers to an example of a thing occurring, but when derived from a Latin word meaning “box,” refers to a container?",
    "answer": "CASE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What English word, when derived from the Latin word for “juniper tree,” refers to a beverage, but when derived from the word for “to beget,” refers to a machine?",
    "answer": "GIN"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Cranes, hydraulic devices, sundials, and machines of war all have a place in the magnum opus of what Augustan-age engineer and author of Dē Architectūrā?",
    "answer": "(M.) VITRUVIUS (POLLIO)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Into how many books was this work divided?",
    "answer": "TEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What structure outside the city limits of Rome is Vitruvius accredited with having constructed?",
    "answer": "BASILICA OF FANO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Executed at Archelais in Cappadocia, what equestrian lost the throne when the 3rd legion, stationed in Syria, defected and won a victory at Antioch in 218 A.D., allowing Elagabalus to take power?",
    "answer": "MACRINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What grandmother of Elagabalus was instrumental in initiating this revolt?",
    "answer": "JULIA MAESA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What lover of Julia Soaemias led the Severan forces at the battle of Antioch and was later executed by Elagabalus for attempting to temper the emperor’s vices?",
    "answer": "GANNYS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Excluding sound effects, what literary device can be found in the Ovidian lines “lātrātor Anūbis, sānctaque Būbastis, variusque colōribus Āpis, [...] sīstraque erant, numquamque satis quaesītus Osīris,” due to their repetition of the conjunction -que? Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": "POLYSYNDETON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "[Note to mod: emphasize the pause] Besides a rhetorical question, what literary device can be found in the Ovidian phrase “quōs equidem āctūtum—sed quid praedīcere poenam attinet”?",
    "answer": "APOSIOPESIS / ANACOLUTHON / PRETERITION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Excluding sound effects, what literary device can be found in the Ovidian phrase “manet imperfossus inque cruentātus”?",
    "answer": "TMESIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Sotades of Maronea, Archestratus of Gela, and Euhemerus of Messina were all inspirations for what early author, a native of Rudiae best known for his 18-book historical epic, Annālēs?",
    "answer": "(Q.) ENNIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the title of Ennius’s gastronomical epic inspired by Archestratus of Gela?",
    "answer": "HEDYPHAEGETICA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Along with the Euhemerus, Ennius also wrote a work based on what Sicilian comic poet turned philosopher, who interpreted the gods as allegories for natural substances?",
    "answer": "EPICHARMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: “Nēmō tē nēquior invenīrī potest.” [Brief pause] Note that nēquior is the comparative of nēquam, meaning “wicked”.",
    "answer": "NO ONE MORE {WICKED / WORTHLESS} THAN YOU CAN BE FOUND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence from Horace: “Vīlius argentum est aurō, virtūtibus aurum.”",
    "answer": "(AND / BUT) GOLD (IS CHEAPER) THAN VIRTUES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate this sentence, adapted from one of Cicero’s letters: “Velim sciās nēminem cuiquam cāriōrem umquam fuisse quam tē mihi.”",
    "answer": "BEEN MORE DEAR TO ANYONE THAN YOU (ARE) TO ME [ACCEPT EQUIVS.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Livy, a man with what nōmen, standing near the Porta Capēna, shouted “So perish any Roman woman who mourns for an enemy!” after his sister mourned for one of the Curiatii?",
    "answer": "HORATIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Description acceptable. What technique had this man used to defeat the three Curiatii after his two brothers had died in the conflict?",
    "answer": "DIFFERENT PACES), THEN KILLED THEM ONE BY ONE [ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Alba Longa was ultimately destroyed, what was the only type of building to be spared?",
    "answer": "TEMPLES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "[Note to mod: make the “o” sound clear, so players don’t hear pascō] For the verb poscō, give the 2nd person plural, pluperfect active subjunctive. Like pendō, this verb is reduplicative.",
    "answer": "POPOSCISSĒTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the same form for pascō.",
    "answer": "PĀVISSĒTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the same form for pergō. Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": "PERRĒXISSĒTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What king’s children-in-law include Andraemon by his daughter Gorge, Heracles by his daughter Deianeira, and Cleopatra by his son Meleager?",
    "answer": "OENEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Which of Oeneus’s children in the tossup has no divine parentage in any version of their myth?",
    "answer": "GORGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Though Tydeus is sometimes considered the product of an incestuous union between Oeneus and Gorge, his mother is more usually said to be what daughter of Hipponous?",
    "answer": "PERIBOEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What location in south-central Pontus saw Lucullus’s legate Triarius suffer a heavy defeat in 67 B.C., but is more known for the Caesarian victory in 47 B.C. that produced the quote “Vēnī, Vīdī, Vīcī”?",
    "answer": "ZELA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What Pontic king did Caesar defeat at the second battle of Zela?",
    "answer": "PHARNACES II"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After brushing aside Pharnaces, Caesar passed the Pontic throne to what improbable “son of Mithridates,” who had aided Caesar’s war efforts in Egypt?",
    "answer": "MITHRIDATES OF PERGAMUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of animal is described in the following sentences? This type of animal prevented Telephus from sleeping with his mom. After Admetus forgot to pay proper respects to Artemis during his marriage rites, he found his bedroom filled with this type of animal. Ares transformed Cadmus and Harmonia into this type of animal at their deaths.",
    "answer": "SNAKE(S) / SERPENT(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was Telephus’s mother, a daughter of Aleus?",
    "answer": "AUGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "During a disastrous plague, the Romans brought what deity from Epidaurus to Rome in the form of a huge snake?",
    "answer": "AESCULAPIUS / ASCLEPIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in good classical Latin: “I fear that the Romans will not win today.”",
    "answer": "{TIMEŌ / VEREOR / METUŌ} {UT // NĒ NŌN} RŌMĀNĪ HODIĒ {VINCANT / VICTŪRĪ SINT}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now say in good classical Latin, using fruor for “enjoy”: “If anyone defeats the Romans, he will enjoy eternal glory.”",
    "answer": "SĪ QUIS RŌMĀNŌS {VINCET / VĪCERIT}, {AETERNĀ / SEMPITERNĀ} GLŌRIĀ FRUĒTUR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now say in good classical Latin, using supersum for “survive”: “Nevertheless, I do not doubt that the empire will survive.”",
    "answer": "NŌN TAMEN DUBITŌ QUĪN IMPERIUM {SUPERSIT / SUPERFUTŪRUM SIT}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Complete the following analogy: tūtus : salvus :: scelus : .",
    "answer": "FACINUS / VITIUM / CRĪMEN / FRAUS / PECCĀTUM / NĒQUITIA / NEFĀS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now complete this analogy: sublīmis : celsus :: vacuus : .",
    "answer": "VĀNUS / INĀNIS / IGNĀVUS / LĪBER / VASTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Finally, complete this analogy: lassus : impiger :: prīscus : . Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": "NOVUS / REMISSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "After spending some time in Forum Corneli, what author took advantage of Pliny the Younger’s generosity to return to Bilbilis, despite winning the favor of Domitian at Rome through his epigrams?",
    "answer": "(M. VALERIUS) MARTIAL(IS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What work did Martial publish to celebrate the opening of the Colosseum?",
    "answer": "LIBER SPECTĀCULŌRUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "One of Martial’s most touching epigrams commemorates the death of what six-year-old enslaved girl, asking the spirits to let her “play in some Elysian glade”? Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": "ROUND THREE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What structure was replaced with a hastily constructed pontoon bridge, which gave way after an army was driven from the Sāxa Rubra by Constantine in the 312 A.D. battle to which it gives its name?",
    "answer": "MILVIAN BRIDGE // PŌNS MILVIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What proconsul had defeated the rebel Lepidus at the Milvian Bridge several centuries before?",
    "answer": "(Q.) LUTATIUS CATULUS (CAPITOLINUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Milvian Bridge had been rebuilt in stone by what censor of 109 B.C., a long-time Prīnceps Senātūs who presided over the Mamilian Commission during the Jugurthine War?",
    "answer": "(M.) AEMILIUS SCAURUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What people — who had a propensity to convey all men to safety — did Poseidon threaten to ring with a mountain chain after they brought Odysseus back to Ithaca?",
    "answer": "PHAEACIANS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What father of Alcinous had led the Phaeacians to the island of Scheria after they were driven out of Hypereia?",
    "answer": "NAUSITHOUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When the Phaeacians brought Odysseus to Ithaca, they dropped him off at the cove of what being, the father of the Gorgons and the Graeae?",
    "answer": "PHORCYS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The English noun biscuit, or, if you prefer, biscotti, is derived from what two Latin words — one a numeral adverb, the other a verb that is also at the root of “concoct” and “cuisine”? BIS (TWICE) and COQUŌ (COOK)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give an English adjective derived from the Latin prefix prae and the verb coquō.",
    "answer": "PRECOCIOUS / PRECOOKED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now, give a noun referring to a type of food that is derived from those same two words, though its form may also be influenced by a Latin word for “sunny.”",
    "answer": "APRICOT [INFLUENCED BY “APRĪCUS”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, whose death we use to date the eruption of Mount Vesuvius, was a famous naturalist and philosopher who wrote the encyclopedic Nātūrālis Historia?",
    "answer": "PLINY THE ELDER // C. PLINIUS SECUNDUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To what man was the Nātūrālis Historia dedicated?",
    "answer": "TITUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Which work of Pliny the Elder was a history of the German wars in 20 volumes?",
    "answer": "BELLA GERMĀNIAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The phrases “multō sanguine ea victōria stetit” and “exsilium patriā sēde mūtāvit” demonstrate what use of the ablative, more commonly found with numerical quantities like “pānis tribus sēstertiīs cōnstat”? Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": "(ABLATIVE OF) PRICE // (DEFINITE) VALUE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the idiomatic meaning of “tantī,” a genitive of indefinite value, in phrases like “sunt iūrgia tantī”?",
    "answer": "WORTH IT // WORTHWHILE // WORTH THE PRICE [ACCEPT IDIOMATIC EQUIVS.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a genitive of indefinite value and the verb rēfert, say in good classical Latin: “It is greatly in my interest to win.”",
    "answer": "MAGNĪ MEĀ RĒFERT VINCERE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The adjective mactus is almost exclusively used in what case, which is unattested in the singular for deus in classical Latin, and is exemplified by the forms Orpheu, Aenēā, and mī?",
    "answer": "VOCATIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What form is used as the vocative singular of deus in post-classical Latin, including the Vulgate?",
    "answer": "DEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the vocative of the name Capys?",
    "answer": "CAPY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who spent his time studying the Ācta of Tiberius after he dressed as a priest of Isis to escape from the Vitellian siege of the Capitoline, setting up the paranoid and autocratic atmosphere of his reign?",
    "answer": "DOMITIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What uncle of Domitian and brother of Vespasian was killed during the Vitellian siege of the Capitoline?",
    "answer": "FLAVIUS SABINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Description acceptable. Domitian’s father Vespasian was initially kicked from Nero’s inner circle after he displeased the emperor by what means?",
    "answer": "HE FELL ASLEEP DURING ONE OF NERO’S PERFORMANCES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Consider the following lines from Book 6 of Lucretius’s Dē Rērum Nātūra: “Dēnique quod longō venit impete, sūmere dēbet / mōbilitātem etiam atque etiam, quae crēscit eundō…” What state draws its motto from this excerpt?",
    "answer": "NEW MEXICO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Consider these lines from Horace’s Odes: “Sī nōn suppliciō culpa recīditur, / quid lēgēs sine mōribus / vānae prōficiunt…” What university draws its motto from these lines?",
    "answer": "UNIVERSITY OF PENNSYLVANIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Consider this excerpt from Cicero’s Ad Atticum: “Sōl [...] excidisse mihi ē mundō vidētur. Ut aegrōtō, dum anima est, spēs esse dīcitur, sīc ego, quoad Pompēius in Ītaliā fuit, spērāre nōn dēstitī.” What state draws its motto from this passage?",
    "answer": "SOUTH CAROLINA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author composed Aeterne rērum conditor and several other hymns, earning him the title “Father of Church Song,” though he is more known for his Dē Officiīs Ministrōrum and his historical activity as bishop of Milan? Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": "(ST.) AMBROSE // (AURELIUS) AMBROSIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Ambrose’s sermons at Milan played an important role in the conversion of what other author, who had obtained the chair of rhetoric there?",
    "answer": "(ST.) AUGUSTINE // (AURELIUS) AUGUSTINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which work of Ambrose is an exegetical work on the six days of creation in nine books?",
    "answer": "HEXAMERON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What group of animals was either stolen by a half-snake half-woman north of the Black Sea or a fire-breathing son of Vulcan named Cacus while Heracles herded them back to Eurystheus?",
    "answer": "CATTLE OF GERYON [PROMPT ON “CATTLE” WITH “WHOSE CATTLE?”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "During this labor, Heracles killed what herdsman and what guard-dog of Geryon? EURYTION and ORTH(R)US",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What herdsman of Hades caught sight of Heracles driving away Geryon’s cattle and alerted Geryon?",
    "answer": "MENOETES / MENOETIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What genre, pioneered by a native of Suessa Aurunca who established hexameter as its standard meter, was given a Stoic flavor by Persius, but most famously took up a tone of savage indignātiō in the hands of Juvenal?",
    "answer": "SATIRE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was this native of Suessa Aurunca?",
    "answer": "(C.) LUCILIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Though Romans claimed satire as “tōta nostra,” what Greek author from Gadara wrote satires in a mixture of prose and verse which were imitated by Varro?",
    "answer": "MENIPPUS (OF GADARA)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What was the Latin term for the young boy who carried the utensils down the aisle for the cōnfarreātiō’s wedding procession?",
    "answer": "CAMILLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What was the Latin term for the box which the camillus would carry?",
    "answer": "CUMERA / CUMERUM [NOT “CUMERUS”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What was the Latin term for the matron who would bring the husband and wife together during the cōnfarreātiō ceremony?",
    "answer": "PRŌNUBA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of object contained an inscription foolishly read aloud by Cydippe, was gathered at Tamasus by Aphrodite in order to help Melanion, and was most famously thrown into the wedding of Peleus and Thetis by Eris?",
    "answer": "APPLE(S) / FRUIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of object, first used during Acrisius and Proetus’s duel at Epidaurus, was made by the craftsman Tychius for Ajax the Greater?",
    "answer": "SHIELD(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Hera bribed Eileithyia to delay the birth of Heracles with a golden, thirteen-foot long version of what type of object? Alcmeon met his death after his wife, Callirhoe, asked him to give her one of these objects that had been crafted by Hephaestus. Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": "NECKLACE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following subordinate clause from Tacitus’s Annālēs: “quō facilius novum rēgnum tuērētur.” [Brief pause] Keep in mind that tueor is synonymous with servō or cūstōdiō.",
    "answer": "HE MIGHT MORE EASILY {GUARD // WATCH (OVER)} THE NEW KINGDOM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence, adapted from Tacitus’s Annālēs: “Morte prohibitus est nē bellum ultrā prōferret.”",
    "answer": "FORTH // EXTENDING} WAR {FURTHER / BEYOND}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence adapted from the Annālēs, keeping in mind that perōdī is basically synonymous with ōdī: “Plērīque superbiam Parthōrum perōsī datum ā Rōmānīs rēgem mālēbant.”",
    "answer": "A KING GIVEN BY THE ROMANS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who managed to destroy a siege device known as a sambūca, lift ships right out of the water with giant cranes, and possibly reflect the sun with giant bronze mirrors when he was called on to craft defenses for Syracuse around 213 B.C.?",
    "answer": "ARCHIMEDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Marcellus, the city’s captor, was eventually ambushed and killed in what year, which also saw a victory for Scipio at Baecula?",
    "answer": "208 B.C."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of king Hiero had provoked this siege when he allied himself with Carthage?",
    "answer": "HIERONYMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Cretan king Carmanor purified what deity for murder after the four-day old god killed the monstrous serpent Python at Delphi?",
    "answer": "APOLLO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Ovid’s Metamorphoses, Apollo’s arrogance after slaying the Python leads him to mock and provoke the anger of what other god?",
    "answer": "CUPID"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What spring did Apollo hide under great rocks because its nymph had tricked him into choosing Delphi, rather than the spring, as the site of his oracle? The seer Teiresias died after he drank from the waters of this same spring.",
    "answer": "TELPHUSA // TILPHU(S)SA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Described as “rērum Rōmānārum florentissimus auctor” by Tacitus, what man was twice expelled from the Senate for moral turpitude, only to write moralizing monographs on the Jugurthine War and the Catilinarian Conspiracy?",
    "answer": "(C.) SALLUST(IUS CRISPUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Two epistles attributed to Sallust address what man, who supported him throughout his political career and gave him the governorship of Africa Nova?",
    "answer": "(C.) JULIUS CAESAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Sallust was a native of what city in Sabine territory? Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": "AMITERNUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give a two word phrase used frequently in classical Latin for the superlative of senex, which literally means “greatest in birth.”",
    "answer": "MAXIMUS NĀTŪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What conqueror of Fregellae seized upon the murder of one of his servants by pro-Gracchan partisans as a pretext for receiving the first ever Senātūs Cōnsultum Ultimum, which declared Gaius Gracchus an enemy of the state?",
    "answer": "(L.) OPIMIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What supporter of Gaius Gracchus, who was declared an enemy in the same Senātūs Cōnsultum Ultimum, had proposed a law regarding Italian enfranchisement while consul in 125 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(M.) FULVIUS FLACCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What law proposed, with Gaius Gracchus’s support, the founding of a colony on the site of old Carthage?",
    "answer": "LĒX RUBRIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What base Latin verb, when compounded with ab-, means “to hide,” when compounded with per-, means “to destroy,” and, when compounded with vēnum, means “to sell”?",
    "answer": "DŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The passives of perdō and vendō are usually supplied by compounds of what other Latin verb with the same prefixes? One of these compounds is commonly listed as a neutral passive verb. EŌ [PEREŌ and VĒNEŌ]",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other compound, consisting of dō and two prefixes, also means “to hide”? Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": "PRELIMS TIEBREAKER (FOR 2ND/3RD SEED)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Wedding processions were arranged and the sportula was doled out in which part of the house, a courtyard with pavement running from the street entrance to the ātrium?",
    "answer": "VESTIBULUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Before receiving the sportula, clients would perform what activity, which involved greeting their patron in his ātrium in the early morning? Give the Latin term.",
    "answer": "SALŪTĀTIŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which type of ātrium had a roof with two pairs of beams crossing each other at right angles?",
    "answer": "(ĀTRIUM) TUSCĀNICUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who told the herald Venulus that forces from his city of Argyripa would not be able to help Turnus, since he was still plagued by troubles from Venus, whom he had wounded at Troy?",
    "answer": "DIOMEDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Into what type of animal were Diomedes’s companions transformed by the angry goddess?",
    "answer": "BIRDS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Apulian king, who shares his name with Turnus’s father, had welcomed Diomedes to Italy?",
    "answer": "DAUNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After he was defeated in the plains between Callinicum and Carrhae by the Sassanid king Narses, what commander was publicly humiliated by Diocletian, even though this Eastern Caesar and his Augustus saw eye to eye on issues such as the Great Persecution?",
    "answer": "GALERIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What nominal Western Augustus was sent forth by Galerius in 307 A.D. to dislodge the usurper Maxentius, though he was ultimately captured and killed by Maximian?",
    "answer": "(FLAVIUS VALERIUS) SEVERUS (II)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Severus was captured while being besieged in what Northern Italian city, which would become the capital of the Western Empire during the reign of Honorius?",
    "answer": "RAVENNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat “īlicet” vel “prōtinus”?",
    "answer": "STRAIGHTAWAY / IMMEDIATELY / FORTHWITH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat “īlex”?",
    "answer": "(HOLM)OAK (TREE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat “illecebra”?",
    "answer": "ENTICEMENT / CHARM / BAIT / LURE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Though his style was sometimes branded as bombastic, contorted, and reckless with neologisms, what author of Dulorestes and Armōrum Iūdicium was praised by Cicero as the greatest of all Latin tragic poets?",
    "answer": "(M.) PACUVIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which cothurnāta of Pacuvius features the disguised Ulysses returning to Ithaca where he is mortally wounded by his son Telegonus?",
    "answer": "NIPTRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which cothurnāta of Pacuvius includes a contest between Orestes and Pylades to determine which of the two would show greater nobility in the face of death? Advanced — Tiebreakers",
    "answer": "SEMIFINAL ROUND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "26 hymns — 12 on daily events, and 14 on martyrs — as well as the didactic poems Apotheosis, Hamartigenia, and Psychomachia, were written by what author, the greatest Christian lyric poet?",
    "answer": "(AURELIUS) PRUDENTIUS (CLEMENS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Though Prudentius calls him the greatest living orator, what pagan author of 10 books of letters and several Relātiōnēs did he attack in a two-book polemical work?",
    "answer": "(Q. AURELIUS) SYMMACHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What earlier Christian poet gives us the fullest record of Christian chiliastic fantasies within his Carmen Apologēticum, or Carmen dē Duōbus Populīs?",
    "answer": "COMMODIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who threw a footstool at the disguised Odysseus and took Melantho as a lover, then became the second suitor to be killed, dying immediately after Antinous?",
    "answer": "EURYMACHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What suitor from Same tried to throw an ox hoof at Odysseus but missed?",
    "answer": "CTESIPPUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What seer and son of Oenops sought mercy from Odysseus only to be decapitated?",
    "answer": "LEODES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin adjective, which often modifies words like ventus or rēs in the meaning of “favorable” or “propitious,” is derived from the gerundive of a deponent verb and normally serves as an ordinal number?",
    "answer": "SECUNDUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What other adjective, derived from a perfect passive participle, means “unfavorable” and can be used as a preposition?",
    "answer": "ADVERSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Due to differences in Greek and Roman augury, what Latin adjective, a synonym of scaevus in its base meaning, can take on the meaning of either “favorable” or “unfavorable,” though it is the latter meaning that is preserved in its most direct English derivative?",
    "answer": "SINISTER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "First distinguished from perduelliō in a 103 B.C. law by Saturninus, what charge came to rely on the evidence of dēlātōrēs to condemn enemies of the emperor on vague accusations of treason?",
    "answer": "MĀIESTĀS (LAESA / IMMINŪTA / DĒMINŪTA / MINŪTA)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Saturninus used māiestās to try and exile what two men for their recent military defeat? (Q.) SERVILIUS CAEPIO and (CN.) MALLIUS MAXIMUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What cousin of Domitian was executed along with his wife Domitilla on charges of māiestās? Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": "FLAVIUS CLEMENS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author gives us all the following quotations? “Nescit vōx missa revertī.” “Caelum nōn animum mūtant quī trāns mare currunt.” “Quandōque bonus dormītat Homērus.”",
    "answer": "HORACE // (Q.) HORATIUS (FLACCUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin phrase from Vergil means “the utmost limit” or “an unknown region,” and includes the name of the location considered the farthest north in classical thought?",
    "answer": "ULTIMA THŪLĒ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Latin phrase found in Persius means “live mindful of death”?",
    "answer": "VĪVE MEMOR LĒTĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What sister of Sterope and Sthenele may have committed suicide when a bronze statue of her husband was burned by her father Acastus, though the more common account is that she was unable to bear her grief at being separated from his shade after a three-hour reunion?",
    "answer": "LAODAM(E)IA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Laodamia’s husband, Protesilaus, was honored at a shrine in what Thracian city near Sestus, which in historical times was plundered by Artaÿctes?",
    "answer": "ELAEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Description acceptable. What omen demonstrated that Protesilaus still had the power to avenge insults, scaring Artaÿctes into agreeing to give back the riches he had stolen from the temple?",
    "answer": "A FISH LEAPT IN A PAN WHILE BEING COOKED [ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence from Latin into English: “Aliunde aliō trānsfugiunt.”",
    "answer": "THEY FLEE (ACROSS) FROM ONE PLACE TO ANOTHER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into idiomatic English: “Aliud aliī nātūra iter ostendit.”",
    "answer": "NATURE SHOWS DIFFERENT PATHS TO DIFFERENT PEOPLE."
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence from Vergil’s Georgics, understanding that aliās is a temporal adverb, into English: “Nōn aliās caelō cecidērunt plūra serēnō fulgura.”",
    "answer": "AT NO OTHER TIME HAVE MORE LIGHTNING BOLTS FALLEN {DURING / FROM} A CALM SKY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Jurisprudence, military art, agriculture, and oratory are among the six artēs covered in what early imperial author’s encyclopedic handbook, of which only the eight books on medicine survive?",
    "answer": "(A. CORNELIUS) CELSUS’"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What contemporary of Tiberius reported the dietetic and medicinal qualities of the various ingredients contained in his ten-book corpus of cooking recipes?",
    "answer": "(M. GAVIUS) APICIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Augustan Age figure, likely motivated by patriotic purposes, drew a massive map of the known world along with commentariī which may have provided a basis for future geographers?",
    "answer": "(M. VIPSANIUS) AGRIPPA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following forms, if any, can function as more than one part of speech, excluding any substantivation: gregis, relictī, maeror, seram, dōs?",
    "answer": "SERAM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the full dictionary entry, including its meaning, of any two of the words of which seram can be a form, ignoring vowel lengths. Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": "[SEE BELOW]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the full dictionary entry of two more words, of which seram can be a form.",
    "answer": "SERŌ, SERERE, SERUĪ, SERTUM – JOIN / FASTEN / BRAID"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Over half a million of what group of people — across 50 fortresses and 985 villages — were massacred when a governor of Britain, Gaius Julius Severus, was sent by Hadrian to suppress their revolt and banish them from the new colony of Aelia Capitolina?",
    "answer": "JEWS / JUDAEANS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "This genocidal act was the culmination of a long series of offenses against the Jews. What emperor had instructed Publius Petronius to set up a statue of him at the Temple in Jerusalem and tolerated attacks on the Alexandrian Jewish population from Greek mobs?",
    "answer": "CALIGULA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Jewish scholar and philosopher led a delegation to seek redress from Caligula after the prefect Avilius Flaccus encouraged these attacks?",
    "answer": "PHILO (OF ALEXANDRIA)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the best use of the dative case that can be found in the following sentence: “Tetrarchīān Caesar Dēiotārō dēmit.”",
    "answer": "SEPARATION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now identify the case and use of ullī in this line from Ovid: “Barbarus hīc ego sum quī nōn intellegor ullī.”",
    "answer": "DATIVE OF AGENT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Identify the case and use of reditūs in this sentence from Vergil: “Sanguine quaerendī reditūs animāque litandum Argolicā.”",
    "answer": "NOMINATIVE SUBJECT [“RETURNS MUST BE SOUGHT…”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where in Rome might one find the umbilīcus urbis, the milliārium aureum, the Porticus of Gaius and Lucius and the Temple of Castor?",
    "answer": "ROMAN FORUM // FORUM RŌMĀNUM [PROMPT ON “FORUM”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Also in the Forum is a shrine to Venus under what epithet, which connects her to purification and to Rome’s sewer system?",
    "answer": "(VENUS) CLOACINA / CLUACINA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the Latin name for the valley which connects the Forum to the Forum Boārium and contains the Arch of Janus?",
    "answer": "VĒLĀBRUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What island provided a naval force under the command of Eudamus that defeated Hannibal during the Seleucid War, was protected from the Senate’s calls for war by Cato the Elder in 168 B.C., and served as Tiberius’s first location of voluntary exile from 6 B.C. to 2 A.D.?",
    "answer": "RHODES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Rhodian naval commander was defeated by the allied forces of Eumenes II and a Roman admiral at the battle of Cape Corycus? Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": "POLYXENIDAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Who was this Roman admiral, who had led 80 battleships into the Aegean Sea in 191 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(C.) LIVIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The statue of Venus Prōspiciēns on Cyprus serves as a reminder of what woman, who mocked a young man’s love until he hanged himself, causing her to be turned to stone?",
    "answer": "ANAXARETE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Athenian woman in the early books of the Metamorphoses was transformed into a black stone shortly after Minerva summoned Invidia, or Envy, to infect her?",
    "answer": "AGLAURUS / AGRAULUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What women from Amathus were also turned into stone because they lost all shame after becoming the first prostitutes?",
    "answer": "PROPOETIDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What 645-verse work of Latin literature, which imitates Manilius while describing air currents in subterranean channels as the cause for volcanic eruptions, was falsely attributed to Vergil and included in the Appendix Vergiliāna?",
    "answer": "AETNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was the title of Manilius’s work on signs of the zodiac and other astrological phenomena?",
    "answer": "ASTRONOMICA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which other work from the Appendix Vergiliāna shares its title with an idyll by Sueius about varieties of nuts?",
    "answer": "MORĒTUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What usurper was killed when he refused to let his troops sack Moguntiacum — which had supported the revolt of Laelianus — almost 9 years after he killed Saloninus and founded the Gallic Empire?",
    "answer": "POSTUMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What general of Gallienus unsuccessfully attacked Postumus in 265 A.D. before he himself revolted in 268?",
    "answer": "AUREOLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What strategic city along the Rhine River served as the capital of Postumus’s Gallic empire?",
    "answer": "TRIER // AUGUSTA TREVERORUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate into the best classical Latin: “He who kills the king will be made king.” [Brief pause] Note that in this sentence, the tenses should be equivalent to a future more vivid conditional.",
    "answer": "(IS) QUĪ RĒGEM {INTERFICIET / INTERFĒCERIT} RĒX {FĪET / CREĀBITUR}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Without using a conjunction, say in Latin: “Our enemies will not escape if they are defeated first.”",
    "answer": "PRIUS VĪCTĪ NŌN {EFFUGIENT / ĒVĀDENT} {INIMĪCĪ / HOSTĒS} NOSTRĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Without using a conjunction, say in Latin: “He does not seem like he will accuse the emperor.”",
    "answer": "NŌN VIDĒTUR IMPERĀTŌREM {ACCŪSĀTŪRUS / ARGŪTŪRUS}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, who wrote in opposition to Philinus, likely provided a primary source for Books 22-23 of Livy when he described his own trip to the Delphic Oracle in his Greek annalistic narrative, the first prose history of Rome? Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": "(Q.) FABIUS PICTOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which annalist, known for his use of the librī linteī, is best remembered as the father of a neoteric poet who wrote the epyllion Io?",
    "answer": "(C.) LICINIUS MACER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which annalist served at Numantia and eschewed simple annalistic chronicle in favor of giving eyewitness accounts and demonstrating “quō cōnsiliō quāque ratiōne” events occurred?",
    "answer": "(C.) SEMPRONIUS ASELLIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What mythological group is described here? The daughters of Hyacinth were sacrificed on the grave of Geraestus, a member of this group. This group was credited with building the walls of Tiryns and Mycenae. The constellation Sagitta represents the arrow Apollo used to kill this group in order to avenge the death of Asclepius.",
    "answer": "CYCLOP(E)S"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Argonaut Polyphemus was a member of what group, which also included Coronus and Exadius?",
    "answer": "LAPITHS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What fabulous group of one-eyed people constantly warred with the griffins and stole their gold at every opportunity? Moderator should say: “All challenges on toss-ups 1 through 19 must be resolved before toss-up 20 is read. If any players or coaches would like to lodge a challenge, please speak up now.”",
    "answer": "ARIMASPI(ANS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in ultimate derivation between “cover” and “recover,” keeping in mind that the latter word is cognate with “recuperate.” OPERIŌ and CAPIŌ (RESPECTIVELY)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in ultimate derivation between “examination” and “exanimation.” AGŌ and ANIMUS (RESPECTIVELY)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in ultimate derivation between “callow” and “callous.” CALVUS and CALLUM (RESPECTIVELY) Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": "FINAL ROUND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After her grandfather Numitorius and fiancé Icilius unsuccessfully defended her from Marcus Claudius — who claimed she had been his slave — what woman was led away by her father and stabbed in the heart, kicking off the Second Secession of the Plebs?",
    "answer": "VERGINIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Among the laws passed by Valerius Potitus and Horatius Barbatus after this secession was the re-establishment of what right, which was originally secured by Publicola in 509 B.C. against a magistrate’s coercitiō and further strengthened by Valerius Maximus in 300?",
    "answer": "PRŌVOCĀTIŌ [PROMPT FOR THE LATIN IF THEY ANSWER IN ENGLISH]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What later law, which Livy calls “a new beginning” for “the liberty of the Roman plebs,” was so effective at preventing debt servitude that the practice of nexum soon fell into total disuse?",
    "answer": "LĒX POETELIA (PAPIRIA)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What meaning is shared by the Latin words spissus, confertus, and crēber?",
    "answer": "THICK / DENSE / CROWDED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What meaning is shared by the Latin words hāmātus and uncus?",
    "answer": "HOOKED / CROOKED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What meaning is shared by the Latin words subdolus and vafer?",
    "answer": "SLY / CUNNING / CRAFTY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author provided precedent for Augustine’s Confessions in his Ad Dōnātum, promoted forgiving people who renounced their faith during persecutions in his Dē Lāpsīs, and took a firm stand against heresies in his Dē Catholicae Ecclēsiae Ūnitāte?",
    "answer": "(THASCIUS CAECILIUS) CYPRIAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Name both the emperor whose persecutions Cyprian survived and the one whose persecutions saw his death. DECIUS and VALERIAN (RESPECTIVELY)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which priest of Rome opposed Cyprian’s stance on the lāpsī, and had his followers elect him as their own pope?",
    "answer": "NOVATIAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What group, who according to Homer received the daughters of Pandareus as servants from the Harpies, was impersonated by the maids of Polyxo when they hanged Helen and was known to the Romans as the Dirae?",
    "answer": "FURIES / EUMENIDES / ERINYES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Furies were identified at Athens with the Eumenides and what other chthonian deities in a cave on the Areopagus?",
    "answer": "SEMNAI THEAI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What king of Thebes and son of Tisamenus, hounded by the Furies of Laius and Oedipus, left Thebes on the advice of an oracle and left the throne to Damasichthon? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "AUTESION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give an idiomatic translation of this sentence from Book 1 of Livy’s Ab Urbe Conditā: “Ēvēnit facile quod dīs cordī esset.”",
    "answer": "THAT WHICH WAS {PLEASING TO // DESIRED BY} THE GODS TURNED OUT EASILY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate from Livy’s Ab Urbe Conditā: “Utinam prō decore tantum hoc vōbīs et nōn prō salūte esset certāmen.”",
    "answer": "AND NOT FOR YOUR {SURVIVAL / SAFETY}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate from Livy’s Ab Urbe Conditā: “Incolumis ad suōs trānāvit, rem ausus plūs fāmae habitūram quam fideī.”",
    "answer": "THAT WOULD HAVE MORE REPUTE THAN CREDIBILITY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what region of Greece — home to the rivers Cocytus and Acheron — did Heracles sire a child by Phylas’s daughter Astyoche in Ephyra and Odysseus lead an army against the Brygi with queen Callidice?",
    "answer": "THESPROTIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of tree did Heracles take a fancy to in Thesprotia and subsequently introduce to the Peloponnesus?",
    "answer": "(WHITE) POPLAR (TREE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Atreus visited Thesprotia, he mistook what woman for the daughter of king Thesprotus?",
    "answer": "PELOPIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which play of Terence, in which the protagonist unwittingly rapes his own fiancée, gives a sober and sympathetic portrayal of Bacchis the courtesan and Sostrata the titular mother-in-law, which may explain its poor reception and repeated failure?",
    "answer": "HECYRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which play of Terence, partly derived from Diphilus’s Synapothneskontes, compares the different upbringings of Aeschinus and Ctesipho?",
    "answer": "ADELPHOE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What braggart soldier plays an important role in Terence’s Eunuchus, his most comedic play?",
    "answer": "THRASO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A residue called hallec would come from the several-month process of making what substance, which was the result of fermenting salt and fish intestines in the sun?",
    "answer": "GARUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What dish was made by removing the stones of an olive, chopping up the pulp, and seasoning it with various spices before mixing it in a jar with oil and would eventually be eaten with cheese?",
    "answer": "EPITȲRUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the production of wine, the grape juice would be left to ferment in what large, thick-walled jars that were specifically designed for storage? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "DŌLIUM / DŌLIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the scansion, that is, the order of dactyls and spondees, in the first four feet of this line from Vergil: “Insonuēre cavae gemitumque dedēre cavernae.”",
    "answer": "DDDD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now give the scansion of the first four feet of this line from Vergil: “Incedunt pueri, pariterque ante ora parentum.”",
    "answer": "SDDS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now give the scansion of the first four feet of this line from Vergil: “Sit pecori, apibus quanta experientia parcis.”",
    "answer": "DDSD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What tribe joined forces with elements of the Suevi and Alans to break into Roman Gaul on December 31, 406 A.D., though they would be pushed into Spain by Constantine III before finally settling in Africa under the command of King Genseric?",
    "answer": "VANDALS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "While they were still in Spain, the Vandals were forced to endure attacks from what Visigothic king, who had signed a deal with Constantius III to reclaim the Iberian peninsula for Rome?",
    "answer": "WALLIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Genseric succeeded him as leader of the Vandal Kingdom in 477 A.D. and would father the future king Hilderic through his marriage to Valentinian III’s daughter Eudocia?",
    "answer": "HUNERIC"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is grammatically incorrect about the following sentence? “Cōnsilium inībō senātōrum iuxtā aede Castoris interficiendōrum.”",
    "answer": "IUXTĀ TAKES ACCUSATIVE, NOT ABLATIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is grammatically infelicitous about the following sentence? “Opportūnissimē haec imperātōrī nocendī occāsiō ā mē nacta est.”",
    "answer": "NANCISCOR IS DEPONENT, SO IT CANNOT BE PASSIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is grammatically infelicitous about the following sentence? “Minus difficile est rēx fierī quam semper secundum philosophiae praecepta rēgnāre.”",
    "answer": "INFINITIVES ARE ACCUSATIVE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Moliones were killed on their way to what event, which was rededicated to Poseidon by Theseus, and initially founded in honor of a dead child carried to the shore by a dolphin?",
    "answer": "ISTHMIAN GAMES"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What Thessalian immigrant to Elis, along with the Moliones, aided Augeas in his war against Heracles and had famous funeral games in his honor where Nestor won almost every contest?",
    "answer": "AMARYNCEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The tomb of the Moliones can be seen at what city, where Heracles had previously stayed with Molorchus prior to fighting the Nemean Lion? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "CLEONAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man’s controversial testimony against a governor of Macedonia who attacked the Odrysae, as well as a narrow escape from a conspiracy involving Varro Murena, led him to resign the consulship and obtain imperium prōcōnsulāre māius from the Senate?",
    "answer": "AUGUSTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Who was the governor of Macedonia who waged this unauthorized war?",
    "answer": "(M.) PRIMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What specific right was added to Augustus’s proconsular power when it was made māius?",
    "answer": "EXERCISE COMMAND OVER ALL THE LEGIONS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "While reading a new edition of your favorite Latin poem, you notice that a word is different from what you remember, so you look at the apparātus criticus and read, “The MSS disagree on the fourth foot.” What is the Latin and English for the abbreviation in this sentence?",
    "answer": "{MANŪSCRĪPTA // MANŪ SCRĪPTA} – MANUSCRIPTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "You come across the form prōripuit in the same work and have the same thought, so you look down to read “v.l. prōrūpit”. What is the Latin and English for that abbreviation?",
    "answer": "VARIA LĒCTIŌ – VARIOUS / VARIANT / DIFFERENT READING"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "At the top of Lewis and Short entries for verbs, you can often find a list of the various forms attested, which are used to inform principal parts and catalogue irregularities. If you encounter the abbreviation “plqpf.” in such a section, what would the corresponding Latin and English be?",
    "answer": "{PLŪSQUAMPERFECTUM // PLŪS QUAM PERFECTUM} – PLUPERFECT"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Drawing on Junius Cordus, Marius Maximus, and many fictitious sources, what problematic work of history, attributed to Trebellius Pollio, Flavius Vopiscus, and four others, gives unreliable biographies of 2nd- and 3rd-century emperors?",
    "answer": "HADRIĀNŌ USQUE AD NUMERIĀNUM DĪVERSĪS COMPOSITAE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Name any two of the six authors not mentioned in the toss-up.",
    "answer": "VULCACIUS GALLICANUS, AELIUS LAMPRIDIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Because of the unreliability of these biographies, modern historians are forced to rely extensively on 4th-century epitomes such as what man’s Liber dē Caesaribus?",
    "answer": "AURELIUS VICTOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What late-Republican figure, the subject of a praetexta by Curiatius Maternus and a biography by Thrasea Paetus, appears as a Stoic hero in the later books of the Pharsālia, since his stubborn incorruptability and dramatic suicide made him a model for writers nostalgic for the Republic?",
    "answer": "(M. PORCIUS) CATO THE YOUNGER / UTICENSIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Cato’s march through the desert in book 9 of the Pharsālia is interrupted by a long and gruesome digression on what type of animal?",
    "answer": "SNAKE(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What speech of Cicero humorously attacks Cato while defending a client accused of electoral corruption? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "PRŌ MŪRĒNĀ"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What name is shared by a consul who saw one of his armies defect to Sulla in 83 B.C., and a consul who ceded command to Domitius Ahenobarbus prior to the battle of Magnesia due to an illness that was afflicting both him and his brother Scipio Africanus?",
    "answer": "L. (CORNELIUS) SCIPIO (ASIATICUS / ASIAGENES / ASIAGENUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What other consul of 83 B.C. did not fare any better against Sulla?",
    "answer": "(C.) NORBANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After Antiochus III’s defeat at Magnesia, what consul of 189 B.C. was sent to Asia to remove the Scipio brothers from command and impose far harsher terms on the Seleucid monarchy?",
    "answer": "(CN.) MANLIUS VULSO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Identify, in order, the three alliterative Latin words that are at the ultimate roots of three words in the following sentence: “This unreasonable insurrection shows the erosion of society’s morals.”",
    "answer": "REOR, REGŌ, RODŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Identify, in order, the four alliterative Latin words that are the ultimate roots of four different words in the following sentence: “The king decreed an excise tax for the excision of excess fat.”",
    "answer": "CERNŌ, CENSEŌ, CAEDŌ, CĒDŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Let’s have some fun with these words! Please come up with an original English sentence that — without repeating any of the words in the first bonus — contains a derivative of cernō, censeō, caedō, cēdō, and cadō.",
    "answer": "OPPORTUNITY TO SOLVE THE CASE BY COMMITTING SUICIDE”"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What name is shared between a Scythian king who condemned his daughter Idaea to death for her crimes against her stepsons, and a man who married Bateia after immigrating to the Troad from Samothrace, the home of his mother Electra?",
    "answer": "DARDANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The second Dardanus received from Zeus an image of what god, which eventually found its way to Aroe after being given in a chest to a son of Euaemon and Opis?",
    "answer": "DIONYSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Though Idaea is most known for what she did to Phineus’s sons by Cleopatra, she also bore him two sons of her own: Thynus and what man, the eponym of a tribe encountered by the Argonauts whose kings included Dascylus and Lycus?",
    "answer": "MARIANDYNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence from English into completely alliterative Latin: “Let the wealth be given up to the gods of the two temples.”",
    "answer": "DĪVITIAE {DĒDANTUR / DENTUR} DEĪS DUŌRUM DĒLŪBRŌRUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into completely alliterative Latin: “The Thracian touched the burnt incenses with the ankle of a bull.”",
    "answer": "THRĀX TĀLŌ TAURĪ TŪRA TOSTA TETIGIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into completely alliterative Latin, also using three Greek inflections: “A story of the Metamorphoses recalls Memnon being changed at death.” Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "MȲTHOS METAMORPHŌSEŌN MEMNONA MEMORAT MORTE {MŪTĀRĪ / MŪTĀTUM}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb careō, give the perfect active infinitive.",
    "answer": "CARUISSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the same form for cernō.",
    "answer": "CRĒVISSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Change crēvisse to the future tense.",
    "answer": "CRĒTURUS/-A/-UM ESSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Known in Latin as Vallum Aelium, what structure, begun in 122 A.D., served as the northern boundary of the Roman Empire until the construction of a fortification north of it 20 years later?",
    "answer": "HADRIAN’S WALL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What governor of Britannia supervised the construction of Hadrian’s Wall?",
    "answer": "(A.) PLATORIUS NEPOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Immediately north of the wall was the territory of which Scottish tribe?",
    "answer": "PICTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage from Augustus’s Res Gestae, which I will read twice, and answer the questions that follow in English: Annōs undēvīginti nātus exercitum prīvātō consiliō et prīvātā impensā comparāvī, per quem rem pūblicam ā dominātiōne factiōnis oppressam in libertatem vindicāvī … Populus autem eōdem annō mē consulem, cum consulēs uterque bellō cecidisset, et triumvirum reī pūblicae constituendae creāvit. The question: Augustus claims that he freed the republic from the oppression of what? (from: rem pūblicam ā dominātiōne factiōnis oppressam)",
    "answer": "(THE DOMINATION OF) A FACTION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Describe how Augustus mustered an army. (from: exercitum prīvātō consiliō et prīvātā impensā comparāvī)",
    "answer": "WITH PRIVATE PLANS & PRIVATE EXPENSE(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What tragedy led the Roman people to install Augustus as triumvir and consul? (from: cum consulēs uterque bellō cecidisset)",
    "answer": "THE DEATH OF THE TWO CONSULS (IN WAR)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Described by Donatus as tall, dark, and rustic, which Roman author studied under the Epicurean Siro, was nicknamed Parthenias for his social aloofness, and wrote works such as Bucolics and Georgics?",
    "answer": "VIRGIL / (P.) VERGILIUS MARO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the Georgics, Virgil removes mention of what prefect of Egypt, who had fallen out of favor with Augustus?",
    "answer": "CORNELIUS GALLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "In place of a panegyric to Cornelius Gallus, there is an epyllion concerning what mythological beekeeper?",
    "answer": "ARISTAEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What princess, the daughter of Alcinous and Arete, resembled Artemis, according to Odysseus, the man she aided in Book VI of the Odyssey?",
    "answer": "NAUSICAÄ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Thesprotian queen entertained Odysseus and even bore the hero a son during his inland journey after killing the suitors?",
    "answer": "CALLIDICE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other woman in Odysseus’s life was the granddaughter of the god Hermes? ANTICLEIA (prompt on “his mother”)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "“Paraffin” and “infinitesimal” are derived from what Latin noun with what meaning?",
    "answer": "FINIS – END / BOUNDARY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What derivative of finis means “to skillfully handle a situation”?",
    "answer": "FINESSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What derivative of a synonym of finis means “to get rid of completely usually by killing off”?",
    "answer": "ELIMINATE (FROM LĪMEN – END / THRESHOLD)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Livy writes falsus utinam vātēs sim what use of the subjunctive is he employing?",
    "answer": "OPTATIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the subjunctive is expressed by the Ciceronian phrase nihil video quod timeam?",
    "answer": "RELATIVE CLAUSE OF CHARACTERISTIC"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the subjunctive is seen in the Plautine quote etiamne eam salūtem?",
    "answer": "DELIBERATIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Certain caves near the famed silver mines of Thrace were said to be the home of the oracular spirit of what Thracian king whose assassination was caused by a spy named Dolon?",
    "answer": "RHESUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name two Muses given as Rhesus’ mother by the river Strymon.",
    "answer": "EUTERPE / CALLIOPE / CLIO / TERPSICHORE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is interesting about Rhesus’ conception?",
    "answer": "HIS MOTHER WAS IMPREGNATED BY THE RIVER AS SHE WADED IN IT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which rhetorical device, excluding all forms of alliteration can be found in the following lines adapted from Vergil’s Aeneid: versat … lōrīcam ex aere rigentem, sanguineam, ingentem, quālis cum caerula nubes solis inardescit radiīs longēque refulgent. (not a metaphor because quālis means “like” and so this is an explicit comparison)",
    "answer": "SIMILE / ASYNDETON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now do the same for the following lines from Book 1, concerning Neptune quelling the winds: Quōs egō—sed mōtōs praestat componere fluctūs.",
    "answer": "APOSIOPESIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now do the same for the following lines from Book 2 concerning the sack of Troy: est urbe egressīs tumulus templumque vetustum desertae Cereris. CHIASMUS: templumque vetustum desertae Cereris / (The temple, not Ceres herself, is deserted by the Trojans)",
    "answer": "HYPALLAGE / TRANSFERRED EPITHET:"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Publius Servilius Vatia Isauricus, Marcus Aemilius Lepidus, Marcus Antonius, and Marcus Calpurnius Bibulus were the co-consuls of what Roman dictator who was assassinated in the Theatre of Pompey on the Ides of March, 44 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(C.) IULIUS CAESAR / JULIUS CAESAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of those men served as co-consul with Caesar from 48-47 B.C.?",
    "answer": "ISAURICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what year did Caesar serve with Bibulus?",
    "answer": "58 B.C."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Cīvēs veritī sunt nē barbarī tōtam urbem arderent.",
    "answer": "WOULD BURN / BURNED THE ENTIRE CITY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Sunt quī pacem desiderent, sed bellum eīs praeparendum est. (accept literal translation: … BUT WAR MUST BE PREPARED FOR THEM)",
    "answer": "THERE ARE THOSE WHO DESIRE PEACE, BUT THEY MUST PREPARE FOR WAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate: Caesare transiente Rubicōnem, nōn dūbium est quin bellum civile accidat. (accept literal translation: WITH CAESAR CROSSING THE RUBICON)",
    "answer": "THERE IS NO DOUBT THAT CIVIL WAR WILL / MAY HAPPEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When he was unable to fulfill the king’s demand that all inhabitants of Seriphos gift him with horses, who was ordered by king Polydectes to bring the head of the Gorgon Medusa?",
    "answer": "PERSEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two deities provided Perseus with all of the tools that he would need to kill Medusa?",
    "answer": "ATHENA & HERMES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On his way back from killing Medusa, Perseus saved Andromeda from death by a sea monster. Who was the mother of Andromeda, who had boasted that her daughter was prettier than the Nereids?",
    "answer": "CASSIOPEIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What early Roman author wrote a work that declared cabbage to be a very versatile crop?",
    "answer": "CATO THE ELDER / (M. PORCIUS) CATO MAIOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What other Silver Age author wrote letters to his friends, which included the emperor Trajan?",
    "answer": "PLINY THE YOUNGER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Silver Age author wrote a work that included a werewolf interrupting a dinner party?",
    "answer": "PETRONIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate this sentence into Latin: Cicero makes his speeches too long. (do NOT accept habet, this is not a correct use of the idiom, do accept nimium longās or valdē longās, if given)",
    "answer": "CICERŌ (SUĀS) ŌRĀTIŌNĒS LONGIŌRĒS FACIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate this sentence into Latin without using an ablative: I have harmed men greater than you.",
    "answer": "NOCUĪ VIRĪS MAIŌRIBUS QUAM TIBI / VŌBĪS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate this sentence into Latin: I have used and always will use the biggest words of all.",
    "answer": "ŪSUS SUM ET SEMPER ŪTAR MAXIMĪS VERBĪS / DICTĪS OMNIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Edict of Milan and the Nicene Creed are hallmarks of the reign of what Roman emperor, who was the first to convert to Christianity?",
    "answer": "CONSTANTINE I / THE GREAT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name Constantine’s father, whose death led to the demise of the Tetrarchy.",
    "answer": "CONSTANTIUS (I) CHLORUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where in 337 A.D. did Constantine’s relatives meet to discuss partitioning of the empire?",
    "answer": "SIRMIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the meaning of the motto of Brookyln College, nil sine magnō labōre?",
    "answer": "NOTHING WITHOUT GREAT LABOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the meaning of the motto of Dartmouth College, vox clamantis in desertō?",
    "answer": "THE VOICE OF ONE CRYING IN THE WILDERNESS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the meaning of the motto of Wellesley College, nōn ministrārī sed ministrāre?",
    "answer": "NOT TO BE SERVED, BUT TO SERVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Book IV of the Metamorphoses, Alcithoë considers the stories of Daphnis, Celmis, and the Curetes before finally telling the story of what 15-year-old boy, who quite literally became one with the nymph Salmacis?",
    "answer": "HERMAPHRODITUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After Salmacis and Hermaphroditus merged, Salmacis’s pool had what enervating effect on men who bathed in it?",
    "answer": "MADE THEM SOFT AND EFFEMINATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Soon after this story, Alcithoë and her two sisters are transformed into what animals?",
    "answer": "BATS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Arch of Septimius Severus, the Temple of Divine Caesar, and the Regia are all located in which part of the city of Rome?",
    "answer": "ROMAN FORUM / FORUM ROMANUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Horologium Augusti and the Ara Pacis are located in which part of the city of Rome?",
    "answer": "CAMPUS MARTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What temple in the Roman Forum was closed in times of peace and open in times of war?",
    "answer": "TEMPLE OF JANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between the verbs fingō and cingō",
    "answer": "FINGŌ – TO SHAPE / FORM / PRODUCE; CINGŌ – TO BIND / SURROUND / ENCIRCLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between the nouns rāmus and rēmus",
    "answer": "RĀMUS - BRANCH; RĒMUS - OAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between the verbs pandō and pangō.",
    "answer": "PANDŌ - SPREAD OUT; PANGŌ – FASTEN / FIX / COMPOSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which author, the son of a tribunus angusticlavi, worked as an imperial secretary under Hadrian where he had wide access to court documents for writing his De Vita Caesarum?",
    "answer": "(C.) SUETONIUS (TRANQUILLUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Into how many books is Suetonius’s De Vita Caesarum divided?",
    "answer": "12"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other work of Suetonius, of which only the De Grammaticis et Rhetoribus survives, is a collection of biographies subdivided by genres? Language:",
    "answer": "REPLACEMENT TOSSUPS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin motto of Boston.",
    "answer": "AS HE WAS WITH OUR FATHERS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now give the Latin motto of our northern neighbors, Canada.",
    "answer": "Ā MARĪ USQUE AD MARE (FROM SEA TO SEA)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Not only does Canada have a Latin motto, but some of its provinces do. Newfoundland and Labrador has as its motto Quaerite prīmē regnum Deī. Translate that.",
    "answer": "SEEK FIRST THE KINGDOM OF GOD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which of the following verbs, if any, is not syntactically like the others: pudet, ponit, paenitet, piget?",
    "answer": "PONIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What do the other three verbs have in common?",
    "answer": "(THEY ARE) IMPERSONAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What case would the cause of revulsion take in a sentence with pudet? History/Culture:",
    "answer": "GENITIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Seiuges, bigae, and quadrigae were all types of what vehicle found in the circus?",
    "answer": "CHARIOTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The honor ducenarius was given to a horse who won how many races?",
    "answer": "TWO HUNDRED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What term referred to the starting gates for a Roman horse race? Mythology:",
    "answer": "CARCERES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "During the Gigantomachy, missiles of red-hot metal were the deadly weapons of which deity as he defeated his gigantic enemy Mimas?",
    "answer": "HEPHAESTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What enemy of Poseidon was defeated and covered by the island Nisyrus?",
    "answer": "POLYBOTES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two giants were destroyed by the bronze clubs of the Fates?",
    "answer": "AGRIUS & THOAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What character in mythology was poorly regarded in 5th century Athens as a “tricksy sophist” and in Roman times as a prime example of the untrustworthiness of Greeks, far cries from his earlier reputation as a courageous, resourceful, and crafty leader whose actions were crucial for the Greeks’ victory in the Trojan War?",
    "answer": "ODYSSEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "One example of Odysseus’ depiction as a trickster is in Euripides’ Iphigenia in Aulis, in which Odysseus lies to Iphigenia’s mother Clytemnestra by saying that rather than being sacrificed, she will be wed to what man?",
    "answer": "7"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "This conception of Odysseus as an untrustworthy Greek is seen throughout Virgil’s Aeneid, such as in whose rhetorical question “sic notus Ulixes?” as he urges the Trojans to not bring the horse within the city walls? Literature:",
    "answer": "LAOCOÖN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which work of Pacuvius celebrates the victor at Pydna in 168 B.C.?",
    "answer": "PAULLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of work is Paullus?",
    "answer": "FABULA PRAETEXTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Along with which author from Pisaurum is Pacuvius held as a top tragedian?",
    "answer": "ROUND 2"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, born in Arpinum in 106 B.C., rose to fame after defeating his rival Hortensius in trial and soon became the most successful orator of his time?",
    "answer": "(M. TULLIUS) CICERO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "In what series of 14 speeches, modeled after those of the Greek orator Demosthenes, does Cicero vehemently attack Mark Antony?",
    "answer": "THE PHILIPPICS / PHILIPPICAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What last work of Cicero includes a discussion of moral duties in three books?",
    "answer": "DE OFFICIIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Noting that aveo, avēre can mean “to desire,” and “hail” in the imperative, translate into completely alliterative Latin: Hail, grandfather, do you desire birds?",
    "answer": "AVĒ, AVE, AVĒSNE AVĒS?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate into completely alliterative Latin: Why did the fifth oak tree seek peace?",
    "answer": "QUĀRĒ QUĪNTA QUERCUS QUIĒTEM QUAESĪVIT?"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Translate into completely alliterative Latin: “The battle lines and the goose will hear the weapons of the citadel.”",
    "answer": "ACIĒS ATQUE ĀNSER(QUE) ARMA ARCIS AUDIENT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After the incessant demanding of the tribune Terentilius Harsa, what legislation, forming the foundation of Roman law, was formally passed in 449 B.C.? ",
    "answer": "(L.) VALERIUS (POTITUS) & (M.) HORATIUS (BARBATUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What grammatical property is in common among the nouns ravis, vīs, sitis, and febris?",
    "answer": "(THEY ARE) PURE I-STEM(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give a pure i-stem noun which means “rain.”",
    "answer": "IMBER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give two pure i-stem nouns which can mean “ship.”",
    "answer": "PUPPIS & LINTER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who, the son of Hagnias, and the helmsman of the Argo, died while the Argonauts stayed among the Mariandyni?",
    "answer": "TIPHYS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name one of the two Argonauts who was murdered by the Libyan shepherd Caphaurus when they tried to steal his sheep?",
    "answer": "CANTHUS / ERIBOTES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Teleon, almost swam to his death but was saved by Aphrodite and taken to Lilybaeum in Sicily?",
    "answer": "9"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Roman author’s works include a discussion of language and style, a poem about a trip to Spain, and a verse epigram about Terence, although he is perhaps better known for his Commentarii on the Civil and Gallic Wars?",
    "answer": "(C. IULIUS / JULIUS) CAESAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To whom did Caesar dedicate his three-book discussion of language and style, entitled De Analogia?",
    "answer": "(M. TULLIUS) CICERO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name any two works in the so-called Corpus Caesarianum.",
    "answer": "BELLUM AFRICUM, BELLUM HISPANIENSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "“Cute,” “vinegar,” “aglet,” and “acuity” are all derived from what Latin adjective, with what meaning?",
    "answer": "ĀCER - SHARP"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "“Puny,” “naïve,” and “renaissance” are all derived from Latin verb, with what meaning?",
    "answer": "NASCOR – TO BE BORN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "“Proctor,” “sure,” and “curio” are derived from ultimately derived from what Latin noun, with what meaning?",
    "answer": "CŪRA – CARE / CONCERN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Named Cottus, Briareus, and Gyes, what siblings of the Titans later guarded them in Tartarus and are distinguished by their hundreds of limbs?",
    "answer": "HECATONCHIRES / CENTIMANES / HUNDRED-HANDED ONES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other three siblings of the Titans and Hecatonchires were known as Thunder, Lightning, and Bright?",
    "answer": "CYCLOPES / BRONTES, STEROPES, ARGES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Hesiod, what primordial sea deity did Gaia bear on her own alongside Uranus and the hills?",
    "answer": "PONTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which king of Rome who may have reigned from 616-579 B.C., is credited with doubling the membership of the Roman Senate, draining the Roman Forum, and constructing the Cloaca Maxima and Circus Maximus?",
    "answer": "TARQUINIUS PRISCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was Tarquinius Priscus’s Etruscan name?",
    "answer": "LUCOMO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to some traditions, Tanaquil, Tarquinius Priscus’s wife, also changed her name when she came to Rome. What was her new name, which is believed to have been invoked at Roman weddings?",
    "answer": "GAIA (CAECILIA)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Caelum nōn animum mūtant quī trans mare currunt and Eheu fugācēs labuntur annī are both quotations from what Venusian author who advises his readers to carpe diem?",
    "answer": "HORACE / (Q.) HORATIUS (FLACCUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What four worded quotation from Horace denotes the immortality that his book of Odes would bring him?",
    "answer": "10"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the colloquial meaning of the following Horatian quotation: parturient montēs, nascētur rīdiculus mūs.",
    "answer": "ALL THAT WORK AND NOTHING TO SHOW FOR IT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between moror and morior.",
    "answer": "MOROR – TO DELAY; MORIOR – TO DIE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between manus and mānēs.",
    "answer": "MANUS – HAND / TEAM / BAND ; MĀNĒS – SHADES / SPIRITS (OF THE DEAD)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between mōs and mūs.",
    "answer": "MŌS – CUSTOM / HABIT; MŪS – MOUSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What child of Cronus and Rhea is said to have been saved after Rhea gave Cronus a literal horse instead, while sending the child to the care of the Telchines on Rhodes?",
    "answer": "POSEIDON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Zeus, not Poseidon, is the child who was traditionally saved from his father’s ferocity. What tribe was said to bang their shields in order to mask the sounds of the infant Zeus’s cries?",
    "answer": "CURETES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Some traditions say that what other child of Cronus and Rhea was saved by being given to Ophion and Eurynome?",
    "answer": "HERA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, in a poem in Sapphic strophe, compares his love to a flower that is plowed down after his mistress Lesbia’s betrayal?",
    "answer": "(C. VALERIUS) CATULLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The theme of betrayal is especially poignant in Catullus 64, which includes an ecphrasis of the abandonment of what mythological character?",
    "answer": "ARIADNE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Catullus 2 and 3 focus on what pet owned by Lesbia?",
    "answer": "PASSER / SPARROW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On formal documents and inscriptions, what did the letter l denote about a person’s status?",
    "answer": "(HE / SHE WAS A) FREEDMAN / FREEDWOMAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What part of a freedman’s name usually came from his slave name?",
    "answer": "COGNOMEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Under what circumstances would a master give a manumitted slave his praenomen? (e.g. Marcus Tullius Tiro, slave of Marcus Tullius Cicero)",
    "answer": "WHEN THE SLAVE WAS THE MASTER’S FAVORITE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Athenās navigābō ut meum patrem inveniam.",
    "answer": "I WILL SAIL TO ATHENS TO FIND MY FATHER."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Pompeius mīsit legātōs quī pācem cum Caesare peterent.",
    "answer": "POMPEY SENT ENVOYS TO SEEK PEACE WITH CAESAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Dē victōriā Caesaris gaudeamus et desperent!",
    "answer": "LET US REJOICE AND LET THEM DESPAIR OF CAESAR’S VICTORY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "By ignoring a lame man asking for a rope, a floating corpse asking to be taken aboard, and three women asking for help weaving a piece of cloth, who was able to safely enter the Underworld on her mission to fill a box with Proserpina’s beauty ointment?",
    "answer": "PSYCHE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Psyche was able to complete this task with the help of what talking object, who had earlier convinced her not to commit suicide?",
    "answer": "(TALKING) TOWER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What child did Psyche bear by Cupid?",
    "answer": "VOLUPTA(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which Roman author participated in the military campaigns in Germany under Domitius Corbulo and dedicated to the emperor Titus his encyclopedic work entitled Historia Naturalis?",
    "answer": "PLINY THE ELDER / GAIUS PLINIUS SECUNDUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Into how many books is the Historia Naturalis divided?",
    "answer": "37"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Pliny the Elder’s historical work on Germany was used as a source material by what later historian and friend of Pliny the Younger?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS CORNELIUS) TACITUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What battle on the city borders of Rome saw the forces of Sulla defeat the alliance of Marian and Samnite forces in 82 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(BATTLE OF) COLLINE GATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What future member of the First Triumvirate commanded the right flank of Sulla’s army at Colline Gate?",
    "answer": "(M. LICINIUS) CRASSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "From what temple did Sulla give a speech accompanied by the screams of tortured Samnite prisoners in 82 B.C.?",
    "answer": "TEMPLE OF BELLONA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage from Propertius’s Elegies, which I will read twice in prose, and answer the questions that follow in Latin: Quālis et unde genus, quī sint mihi, Tulle, Penātēs, quaeris prō nostra semper amīcitia. sī Perusina tibi patriae sunt nota sepulcra, Italiae dūrīs fūnera tempōribus, cum Romāna suōs ēgit discordia cīvēs. The question: Ad quem Propertius dīcit?",
    "answer": "TULLUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Quālia tempōra in Italiā sunt?",
    "answer": "DŪRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quōs Romāna discordia ēgit?",
    "answer": "SUŌS CĪVĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb aufero, auferre, give the 2nd person plural, pluperfect, passive, subjunctive.",
    "answer": "ABLATĪ/-AE/-A ESSĒTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Change that form to the active voice.",
    "answer": "ABSTULISSĒTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now for the same verb, give the future, passive, infinitive. Language:",
    "answer": "REPLACEMENT TOSSUPS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Instar, gratiā, and tenus all govern what case? ",
    "answer": "CAUSĀ & ERGŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "With what type of verbs are supines ending in -um used?",
    "answer": "VERBS OF MOTION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the ablative is exemplified by supines ending in -ū?",
    "answer": "ABLATIVE OF RESPECT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give two examples of adjectives that used supines ending in - ū to express respect. MIRĀBILIS, FACILIS, DIFFICILIS, DIGNUS, (there are others) History/Culture:",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The family line of Decius Mus was famous for committing what type of act, a sacrifice by charging straight into enemy formation?",
    "answer": "DEVOTIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Name a battle where a Decius Mus committed devotio.",
    "answer": "MT. VESUVIUS (339 B.C.) / SENTINUM (295 B.C.) / ASCULUM (279 B.C.)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "In which of these battles did devotio did not lead to an outright victory? Mythology:",
    "answer": "ASCULUM (279 B.C.)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Phrygian Dares was sent by Apollo to advise Hector not to fight what man, the dear friend of Achilles?",
    "answer": "PATROCLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was the prophecy that Apollo informed Dares of?",
    "answer": "HE HIMSELF WOULD BE SLAIN BY ACHILLES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Who killed Dares when he fled to the Greek camp? Literature:",
    "answer": "ODYSSEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What late Roman author claims that God himself spoke the words Ciceronianus es, non Christanus to him in a dream, sparking his newfound devotion to Christianity and the eventual completion of his magnum opus, a complete Latin translation of the Bible?",
    "answer": "(ST.) JEROME / SOPHRONIUS EUSEBIUS HIERONYMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "At whose behest did Jerome set out to write this translation, the Vulgata?",
    "answer": "POPE DAMASUS(‘S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other work of Jerome consists of 135 biographies from St. Peter to Jerome himself?",
    "answer": "ROUND 3"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Containing a section thanking the Carthaginians for a statue dedicated to him and another section humorously praising a parrot as Second Sophists would, the Florida of what author shows his flexible and brilliant prose?",
    "answer": "(LUCIUS) APULEIUS (MADAURENSIS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the second section of which of Apuleius’ philosophical works does he discuss the position of demons and their function between the world of the gods and the world of men?",
    "answer": "DE DEO SOCRATIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "For chapters 13 and 14 of his De Mundo, Apuleius is said to have drawn on the works of what man who wrote the Attic Nights?",
    "answer": "AULUS GELLIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using two infinitives, say in Latin: Moderator, don’t say that my answer is wrong.",
    "answer": "MODERĀTOR, NŌLĪ DĪCERE MEUM RESPONSUM FALSUM ESSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using cavē, say in Latin: Friends, don’t stop believing me.",
    "answer": "AMĪCĪ, CAVĒ DESINĀS / SISTĀS CREDERE MIHI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using nē, say in Latin: Marcus, don’t listen to that liar.",
    "answer": "MARCE, NĒ AUDĪVERIS ILLUM MENDĀCEM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who recognized the corpse of her son Polydorus in Thrace on her journey back to Greece with Odysseus?",
    "answer": "HECUBA / HECABE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What local king had murdered Polydorus after he had been sent there to stay out of the war?",
    "answer": "POLYM(N)ESTOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two actions did Hecuba’s servants take against Polymestor?",
    "answer": "HIS CHILDREN WERE MURDERED & HE WAS BLINDED WITH THEIR BROOCHES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "“Varsity,” “suzerain,” “prosaic,” “controversial,” and “versatility” are derived from what Latin verb with what meaning?",
    "answer": "VERTŌ – TO TURN (AROUND / ABOUT)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "“Souvenir,” “convent,” “avenue,” “adventitious,” and “supervene” are derived from what Latin verb with what meaning?",
    "answer": "VENIŌ – TO COME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "“Valid,” “avail,” “prevalent,” and “convalescent” are derived from what Latin verb with what meaning?",
    "answer": "VALEŌ – TO BE STRONG / HAVE STRENGTH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Constructed in 138 A.D., what temple in the Forum Romanum was said to have been the largest in all of Rome, dedicated to Venus and the Roma Aeterna?",
    "answer": "TEMPLE OF VENUS AND ROME / TEMPLUM VENERIS ET ROMAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Cassius Dio, the architecture of the Temple of Venus and Rome drew criticism from what prolific royal architect, a favorite of Trajan, leading to his execution?",
    "answer": "APOLLODORUS (OF DAMASCUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name three of his architectural designs created during Trajan’s reign.",
    "answer": "LIBRARY OF TRAJAN, BASILICA ULPIA, ODEON OF DOMITIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Thamyris, the Harpies, and the daughters of king Pierus were all defeated in contests by what group of nine sisters?",
    "answer": "MUSES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whose daughters were threatened by Agamemnon because of their ability to produce endless supplies of food, and were thus transformed into white doves to protect them?",
    "answer": "ANIUS(‘S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whose sisters were so devastated by his death that they were transformed into guinea fowl?",
    "answer": "MELEAGER(‘S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage from one of Cicero’s Catilinarians, which I will read twice, and answer the question that follows in English: Iacet ille nunc prostrātus, Quirītes, et sē perculsum atque abiectum esse sentit et retorquet oculōs profectō saepe ad hanc urbem, quam ē suis faucibus ereptam esse lūget; quae quidem mihi laetārī vidētur, quod tantam pestem evomuerit forāsque proiēcerit. The question: According to Cicero, what does Catiline mourn about? (from: ē suis faucibus ereptam esse lūget)",
    "answer": "THAT THIS CITY WAS SNATCHED FROM HIS JAWS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What has Cicero done to Catiline for which he expects reproach? (from: quae quidem mihi laetārī vidētur, quod tantam pestem evomuerit forāsque proiēcerit",
    "answer": "THAT HE HAS THROWN HIM OUT AND FLUNG HIM OUT OF THE CITY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Cicero, what does Catiline sense? (from: et sē perculsum atque abiectum esse sentit)",
    "answer": "THAT HE IS STRUCK DOWN AND CAST AWAY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid sit futūrum crās, fuge quaerere is a famous quote from Horace’s Ode 1.9, exemplifying what grammatical construction, in which a future active participle is used with a form of sum?",
    "answer": "ACTIVE / FIRST PERIPHRASTIC"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the subjunctive does Horace use in that quote?",
    "answer": "INDIRECT QUESTION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Horace follows that quote with et quem fors diērum cumque dabit, which would appear in prose as et quemcumque fors diērum dabit. What use of the genitive is exemplified there?",
    "answer": "PARTITIVE / OF THE WHOLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Inspired by Propertius’s verse epistle from Arethusa to Lycotas, which of Ovid’s works featured a collection of elegiac love letters written by mostly mythological women?",
    "answer": "HEROIDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Most of Ovid’s Heriodes involve women writing to their male lovers. Name two of the three pairs of lovers who wrote in Ovid’s Heroides.",
    "answer": "PARIS & HELEN / HERO & LEANDER / ACONTIUS & CYDIPPE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In which work of Ovid does he proclaim pride in the originality of the Heroides?",
    "answer": "15"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Which battle saw the deaths of the consuls Aulus Hirtius and Vibius Pansa against the forces of Mark Antony in 43 B.C.?",
    "answer": "MUTINA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what earlier skirmish of 43 B.C. was Vibius Pansa gravely wounded?",
    "answer": "FORUM GALLORUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Two years later, the Perusine War was waged against Octavian by Lucius Antonius and what wife of Mark Antony?",
    "answer": "FULVIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Eos, Phlegon, and Pyrois were all horses of which god, the father of Phaëthon?",
    "answer": "HELIOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was the foster father of Phaëthon who took him and Clymene in?",
    "answer": "MEROPS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is unusual about Phaëthon’s body in the Eridanus river?",
    "answer": "IT STILL BURNS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of Vermont, North Dakota, Missouri, Massachusetts, and Alabama, identify the state whose motto contains a semi-deponent verb.",
    "answer": "ALABAMA (AUDĒMUS IŪRA NOSTRA DEFENDERE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of those same states, identify the state whose Latin motto contains a future imperative.",
    "answer": "MISSOURI (SALUS POPULĪ SUPRĒMA LEX ESTŌ)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of those same states, identify one of the two states whose motto contains a subjunctive as well as the usage of it.",
    "answer": "VERMONT – JUSSIVE / NORTH DAKOTA – PURPOSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "After the disaster at Cannae, what battle of 215 B.C. proved to be a saving grace for the Romans when the forces of Hasdrubal were driven back after attempting to mimic his brother’s tactical maneuvers at Cannae?",
    "answer": "DERTOSA / IBERA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two Roman generals managed to defeat Hasdrubal, but instead of pursuing, continued to consolidate power in Spain?",
    "answer": "LUCIUS & GNAEUS (CORNELIUS) SCIPIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "The Carthaginians won their only land battle without being led by Hannibal in the Second Punic War at what site in Spain circa 211 B.C., at which Publius Cornelius Scipio the Elder and Gnaeus Scipio were killed?",
    "answer": "UPPER BAETIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate this quote from Book IX of Vergil’s Aeneid, whose English translation greets visitors to the Memorial Hall of the 9/11 Museum in New York City: Nulla diēs umquam memorī vōs eximet aevō.",
    "answer": "FROM A REMEMBERING / MINDFUL AGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate this quote from the Romanian philosopher Emil Coiran: Est nulla nātiō in quā habitāmus, sed lingua; cavē errēs, ut prīma lingua vēra nostra patria est.",
    "answer": "MAKE NO MISTAKE, AS OUR FIRST LANGUAGE IS OUR TRUE FATHERLAND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate this quote of the Marquis de Lafayette, translated into Latin, back into English: Rēs novae sacerrimae iūrum et maximē necessāriae officiōrum sunt.",
    "answer": "AND THE MOST INDISPENSABLE / NECESSARY OF DUTIES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Zeus’s seduction of Alcmene, a shipwreck, hidden treasure, a haunted house, and a brave but arrogant soldier are all plot points in the works of which late 3rd-century B.C. Umbrian playwright?",
    "answer": "(TITUS MACCIUS) PLAUTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which play of Plautus premiered at the Plebeian Games in 200 B.C. and is notable for having very little plot or structure?",
    "answer": "STICHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Plautus often combined the plots of multiple extant Greek plays into one play, a process known as what?",
    "answer": "CONTAMINATIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Argive seer and son of Coeranus predicted that his own son would either die of illness at home or die at Troy on the battlefield?",
    "answer": "POLYEIDUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name this son of Polyeidus, who was killed by Paris.",
    "answer": "EUCHENOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Cretan child had Polyeidus earlier brought back to life at the instigation of King Minos?",
    "answer": "GLAUCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Gaius Avidius Nigrinus, Cornelius Palma Frontonianus, Publilius Celsus, and Lusius Quietus were all members of the conspiracy of the Four Consulars that occurred under which emperor in 118 A.D.?",
    "answer": "(P. AELIUS) HADRIAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who, Praetorian Prefect at the time of Trajan’s death, was responsible for the smooth succession of Hadrian when he ordered the execution of the Four Consulars?",
    "answer": "(P. ACILIUS) ATTIANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which friend did Hadrian call upon to suppress an uprising in Mauretania caused by the dismissal of Lusius Quietus, for which he would later be rewarded by becoming Praetorian Prefect in 125 A.D.?",
    "answer": "(Q. MARCIUS) TURBO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Make the phrase caecum fūnus dative singular.",
    "answer": "CAECŌ FŪNERĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Change caecō fūnerī to the accusative plural.",
    "answer": "CAECA FŪNERA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now change caeca fūnera to the genitive.",
    "answer": "CAECŌRUM FŪNERUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who wrote a collection of 30 epigrams, entitled Liber Spectaculorum, to commemorate the opening of the Colosseum under the emperor Titus?",
    "answer": "(M. VALERIUS) MARTIAL(IS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which work of Martial is a book of short inscriptions for accompanying varying presents given on occasions such as Saturnalia?",
    "answer": "XENIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which work of Martial is a book of short inscriptions for accompanying varying presents given to guests at banquets?",
    "answer": "APOPHORETA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give a synonym of the Latin noun gladius. (do not accept pugiō, culter, sīca, or other words for “dagger” or “knife”)",
    "answer": "FERRUM / ENSIS / MŪCRŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give a synonym of the Latin noun praemium.",
    "answer": "DŌNUM / MŪNUS / MANŪBIAE / NĪCĒTĒRIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give a synonym of the Latin adjective mollis. Language:",
    "answer": "REPLACEMENT TOSSUPS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the ablative is often seen following the adjectives sātus, ortus, ēditus, and genitus?",
    "answer": "ORIGIN / SOURCE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What use of ablative naturally follows verbs such as triumphō, exsultō, gaudeō, and ardeō?",
    "answer": "CAUSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The adjectives immūnis, vacuus, and nūdus regularly take what use of ablative?",
    "answer": "SEPARATION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What property is shared by the verb forms that appear in the mottoes of Columbia University, Johns Hopkins University, Idaho, and Missouri?",
    "answer": "ALL IN THE FUTURE TENSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What property is shared by the verb forms that appear in the mottoes of Amherst College, Vermont, Wyoming, and Kentucky?",
    "answer": "ALL IN THE SUBJUNCTIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Again with regards to their verbs, what property is shared by the mottoes of Brooklyn College, Dartmouth College, and the District of Columbia? History/Culture:",
    "answer": "THEY DON’T HAVE VERBS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who set up a council of sixteen prominent senators to advise her young son, Severus Alexander?",
    "answer": "JULIA MAMAEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What praetorian prefect of Septimius Severus was murdered by the Praetorian Guard because he was deemed too strict?",
    "answer": "(DOMITUS) ULPIAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Greek historian would have also been killed had the emperor not sent him to Bithynia? Mythology:",
    "answer": "CASSIUS DIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whose sons overthrew and killed him because he appointed Deiphontes as his successor?",
    "answer": "TEMENUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of Temenus’s sons accidentally killed his sister while fleeing with her?",
    "answer": "PHALCES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whom was this sister that was mishandled and killed? Literature:",
    "answer": "HYRNETHO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author was probably informed by Greek ktisis literature when composing a historical work that celebrated lesser known heroes called the Origines?",
    "answer": "CATO THE ELDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work of Cato the Elder extols virtues such as parsimonia, duritia, and industria, and advises selling slaves when they become too old?",
    "answer": "DE AGRI CULTURA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work of prose by Cato includes such information on social conventions as the fact that poetry was not a respectable art in Rome, and that any man who engaged in it was wanton?",
    "answer": "SEMI-FINAL ROUND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into Latin: He says that you, who have been loved often, will never love him. NUMQUAM EUM / SĒ AMĀTŪRUM / AMATŪRAM ESSE [note sīs not sit]",
    "answer": "DĪCIT TĒ, QUĪ / QUAE SAEPE AMĀTUS / AMĀTA SĪS,"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using two subjunctives, translate this sentence into Latin: Since he cries so much, it is not clear what we should do.",
    "answer": "QUID AGĀMUS / FACIĀMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate this sentence into Latin: So long as he sees her tomorrow, he will be very happy.",
    "answer": "LAETISSIMUS / VALDĒ LAETUS ERIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Proclaimed emperor in Rhaetia, what praetorian prefect from Narbo first began marching against Bahram II and took over Ctesiphon before mysteriously dying in 284 A.D.?",
    "answer": "CARUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where was the predecessor of Carus, Probus, killed in 282 A.D. during a mutiny of his soldiers?",
    "answer": "SIRMIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Carus’s successor, Numerian, was said to have been killed by the praetorian prefect Aper at what city, the future capital of Diocletian’s portion in his tetrarchy?",
    "answer": "NICOMEDIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which late author, who had been banished to Curubis at one point in his life, was able to evade Decius’s persecution but not Valerian’s in 258 A.D.?",
    "answer": "(THASCIUS CAECILIUS) CYPRIAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which work of Cyprian discusses how Christians must treat their brethren who had claimed not to be Christian to avoid the persecutions but came back into the arms of Christians later?",
    "answer": "DE LAPSIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of what African city, his birthplace, was Cyprian bishop?",
    "answer": "CARTHAGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Argive twins yoked a wagon to themselves and carried their mother to a temple as part of a festival to Hera?",
    "answer": "CLEOBIS & BITON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After their mother prayed to Hera that her sons be given the best thing human beings could obtain, what unusual fate befell the twins after the festival was complete?",
    "answer": "THEY DIED / THEY FELL ASLEEP (IN THE TEMPLE) NEVER TO WAKE UP"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Solon, how many miles did the Argives hoist the chariot before arriving at the temple?",
    "answer": "FIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of nurus, socrus, vulgus, manus, and acus, which does not belong because of gender?",
    "answer": "VULGUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of vīrus, pelagus, cētus, pectus, and humus, which does not belong because of gender?",
    "answer": "HUMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of porticus, arctus, mōles, aurīga, and mūla, which does not belong because of gender?",
    "answer": "AURĪGA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English this line from Book III of the Aeneid. parce piās scelerāre manūs.",
    "answer": "MITTE, FUGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "When a secret agreement between Hannibal and Philip V was discovered, which Roman admiral, and praetor of 215 B.C., was sent to foment a war against Philip V and keep him preoccupied?",
    "answer": "(M.) VALERIUS LAEVINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "With which league of Greek city-states did Valerius Laevinus successfully negotiate a treaty in 212 B.C., creating a new enemy for Philip V to contend with?",
    "answer": "AETOLIAN LEAGUE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "With which king of Pergamum did Valerius Laevinus also successfully negotiate a treaty having him fight alongside the Aetolian League against Philip V?",
    "answer": "ATTALUS I"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was purified by members of the Phytalides before he could enter Athens?",
    "answer": "THESEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "At which old woman’s hut did Theseus stay prior to his capturing of the Marathonian Bull?",
    "answer": "HECALE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "With which king of the Abantes did Theseus leave his children prior to his death?",
    "answer": "ELEPHENOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the phrases ad augusta per angusta, consuētudō locī observanda est, ignōtī nulla cupīdo, oleum addere camīno, and ultrā posse nēmo obligātur, which one colloquially means “don’t bite off more than you can chew”?",
    "answer": "ULTRĀ POSSE NĒMŌ OBLIGĀTUR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the phrases in the tossup, which one can colloquially mean “no pain no gain”?",
    "answer": "AD AUGUSTA PER ANGUSTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the phrases in the tossup, which one can colloquially mean “when in Rome, do as the Romans do”?",
    "answer": "CONSUĒTUDŌ LOCĪ OBSERVANDA EST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which famous writer of fabulae palliatae was held as first, ahead of Plautus, on Volcacius Sedigitus’ canon of comic poets?",
    "answer": "CAECILIUS STATIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which Greek author’s Plokion is Caecilius Statius’ Plocium based on?",
    "answer": "MENANDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin term describes the farcical aria that the Menandrian monologues were turned into?",
    "answer": "CANTICUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who would have returned Orestes, Pylades, and Iphigeneia to Thoas as prisoners had his grandfather not revealed to him that he was the half-brother of Orestes and Iphigeneia, since he was the son of Agamemnon by Chryseїs?",
    "answer": "CHRYSES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What object had Orestes, Pylades, and Iphigeneia taken from Thoas when they fled his island?",
    "answer": "A STATUE OF ARTEMIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What island, inhabited by Chryses, did they land on?",
    "answer": "ZMINTHE / CHRYSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Josephus, what corrupt curator of Judea instigated the First Jewish Revolt by exacerbating the relationship between Romans and Jews through his openly discriminatory Jewish policies?",
    "answer": "GESSIUS FLORUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Due to the onset of the First Jewish Revolt caused by Gessius Florus, what legate from Syria was sent to deal with the Jewish rebels, only to be routed at the battle of Beth Horon?",
    "answer": "CESTIUS GALLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Romans did eventually subdue the Jewish rebels after the sack of Jerusalem in 70 B.C. What punitive institution did Vespasian impose on all Jews to fund his lavish projects and restoration of the temple of Jupiter Optimus Maximus in Rome?",
    "answer": "FISCUS JUDAICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the comparative and superlative forms of egēnus.",
    "answer": "DĪTISSIMUS / DĪVENTISSIMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which rhetorical device, excluding all forms of alliteration, can be found in the following lines from Seneca the Younger’s Apocolocyntosis: deformīs hiemps grātōs carpēbat honōrēs dīvitis autumnī, iussōque senescere Bacchō carpēbat rārās serus vindemitor uvās. [personification: hiemps … carpēbat (winter was seizing) / chiasmus: rārās serus vindemitor uvās, / metonymy: Bacchō standing in for wine]",
    "answer": "PERSONIFICATION / CHIASMUS / METONYMY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now do the same for the following lines, concerning the Parcae: mirantur pensa sorōrēs: mutātur vilis pretiōsō lana metallō, aurea formōsō descendunt saecula fīlō. SYNCHESIS [aurea formōsō … saecula fīlō] /",
    "answer": "ASYNDETON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The following lines are from Claudius’s funeral dirge, as sung by a professional mourning choir: “Fundite flētus, edite planctūs, resonet tristī clamōre forum.” Give the dominant foot for this meter, which features two short syllables followed by one long syllable.",
    "answer": "ANAPEST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The Latin phrase nesciō quis meaning “somebody” stemmed originally from an expression of what use of the subjunctive?",
    "answer": "INDIRECT QUESTION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the idiomatic translation of the phrase sānē quam?",
    "answer": "IMMENSELY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence from Livy into idiomatic Enlgish: mīrum quantum prōfuit.",
    "answer": "HE / IT BENEFITTED TREMENDOUSLY / PRODIGIOUSLY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the sentence, “She discovered that she is your first cousin twice removed,” identify all words derived from Latin and specify which Latin word each is derived from.",
    "answer": "REMOVED – FROM MOVEŌ (TO MOVE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Do the same for this sentence: The princess contemplated her advisor’s request.",
    "answer": "REQUEST – FROM QUAERŌ (TO SEEK / ASK FOR)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Do the same for this sentence: The building, which you see now, was owned by the twelfth king.",
    "answer": "NO WORDS ARE DERIVED FROM LATIN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage from Virgil’s Aeneid, which I will read twice in prose, and answer the questions that follow in Latin: Iuppiter, hospitibus nam tē dāre iura loquuntur, hunc laetum Tyriīsque diem Troiāque profectīs esse velīs, nostrōsque huius meminisse minōrēs. Adsit laetitiae Bacchus dator, et bona Iūnō; et vōs, Ō, coetum, Tyriī, celebrāte faventēs. The question: Quōs laetum diem habere decet?",
    "answer": "TYRIŌS (ET PROFECTŌS TROIĀ)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quī in hōc laetō diē adsunt?",
    "answer": "BACCHUS ET IŪNŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quī legēs ā Iove dantur?",
    "answer": "HOSPITĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which satire of Juvenal, the inspiration for a poem by Samuel Johnson, describes how his old friend Umbricius decides to depart from Rome, as the city has become so dangerous and disgusting that it no longer befits honest men to live there?",
    "answer": "RD SATIRE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which satire of Juvenal comically ridicules the emperor Domitian, describing his struggle to decide how to cook an enormous fish, and ultimately serves as an attack on corruption?",
    "answer": "TH SATIRE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What is the subject of Juvenal’s 15th satire?",
    "answer": "CANNIBALISM (IN EGYPT)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Comprised of blocks of lava or other hard stone, what layer of the road was laid with the greatest care as it was the top layer of the road?",
    "answer": "DORSUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the name of the 6-inch bedding of fine concrete made of potsherds and lime which formed the layer underneath the dorsum.",
    "answer": "NUCLEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the name of the curbstones which separated the footpaths from the road?",
    "answer": "UMBO / UMBONES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A horse of Pluto according to Claudian, a horse of Helios according to Ovid, a horse of Hector according to Homer, and a fictional son of Deucalion whom Odysseus impersonates during his first meeting with Penelope all had what name?",
    "answer": "AETHON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Podarge also mothered the horses Phlogaius and Harpagus who served what twin brothers both on earth and on Olympus?",
    "answer": "24"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What horse, despite his mortality, was still able to keep up with his immortal harness-mates Balius and Xanthus, but unfortunately took a spear to the shoulder meant for his master Patroclus? PEDASUS [Iliad XVI.152-4, 467-8] Language:",
    "answer": "REPLACEMENT TOSSUPS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following, if any, is not true about the adjective vetus: it is not i-stem, it has irregular comparison, it is defective, it is a synonym of pristinus.",
    "answer": "IT IS DEFECTIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the comparative and superlative forms of vetus.",
    "answer": "VETUSTIOR, VETERRIMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now give the comparative and superlative forms of dexter.",
    "answer": "DEXTERIOR, DEXTIMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin verb with what meaning is at the root of “strait”?",
    "answer": "STRINGŌ – TO DRAW TIGHT / BIND / TIE TIGHT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin verb with what meaning is at the root of “etiolate.”",
    "answer": "STIPŌ – TO PRESS / PACK TOGETHER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin verb with what meaning is at the root of “etude”? History/Culture:",
    "answer": "STUDEŌ – TO BE EAGER / BE DILIGENT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In 219 B.C., the first man of what occupation arrived in Rome from Greece?",
    "answer": "SURGEON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Julius Caesar forbade auctioneers and undertakers from what occupation?",
    "answer": "PUBLIC OFFICE / POLITICS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What occupation did Cicero respect and hold on par with medicine?",
    "answer": "ARCHITECTURE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After hearing that Chrosroes had deposed the king of Armenia, which Roman emperor from Italica, Spain, quickly set sail in 113 A.D. and captured the Parthian capital two years later?",
    "answer": "TRAJAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was this Parthian capital, one of many, which Trajan sacked?",
    "answer": "CTESIPHON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "By defeating the Parthians, Trajan expanded the Roman Empire to its largest size, by establishing the eastern boundary of the empire to be along which two rivers? Mythology:",
    "answer": "TIGRIS & EUPHRATES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What daughter of Hypseus became a love interest of Apollo when he saw her wrestling a lion?",
    "answer": "CYRENE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What granddaughter of Ares became Apollo’s love interest, though she chose the mortal Idas over him?",
    "answer": "MARPESSA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What youth from Amyclae and love interest of Apollo did the god tragically kill? Literature:",
    "answer": "HYACINTHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which author, born in the Arcadian city of Megalopolis to Lycortas, witnessed the destruction of Carthage with Scipio Aemilianus in his later life and argued for a pragmatic approach to history, demonstrated in his 40-book Histories?",
    "answer": "POLYBIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Polybius attributes the greatness of Rome to her constitution. What does Polybius consider to be the ideal form of government, a view which Cicero continues in his De Re Publica? [Accept as long as playrs say something to this effect]",
    "answer": "MIXED GOVERNMENT (OF DEMOCRACY, OLIGARCHY, AND AUTOCRACY)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Pseudo-Lucian, how did Polybius die?",
    "answer": "HE FELL OFF A HORSE (AT THE AGE OF 82)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which Etruscan author’s satires preach about the deplorability of avarice and the significance of the principle nosce tē ipsum for those ambitious for political success?",
    "answer": "(AULES) PERSIUS (FLACCUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which close friend of Persius was the one to publish his works posthumously?",
    "answer": "CAESIUS BASSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "In which satire does Persius attack those who ask the gods only for money?",
    "answer": "FINAL ROUND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who, along with her brother, was given by her parents to be raised by Creon of Corinth only to be later sold back to her father Alcmeon, unbeknownst to them all?",
    "answer": "TISIPHONE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was Tisiphone’s mother and who was her brother?",
    "answer": "MANTO & AMPHILOCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Why was Tisiphone sold off?",
    "answer": "DECIDED TO SELL HER OFF AS A SLAVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the correct form of the adjective ignōtus to agree with the noun epitomēs.",
    "answer": "IGNŌTAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now give the correct form of the adjective lentus to agree with the noun comētēs.",
    "answer": "LENTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give two alternate forms for the ablative singular of comētēs.",
    "answer": "COMĒTĒ / COMĒTĀ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which late author, who was tortured to death for allegedly conspiring against Theodoric, wrote his most famous work De Consolatione Philosophiae in the form of a Menippean satire?",
    "answer": "(ANICIUS MANLIUS SEVERINUS) BOETHIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What prestigious position did Boethius hold in 522 A.D.?",
    "answer": "MAGISTER OFFICIORUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where does Boethius’s Philosophia argue happiness comes from?",
    "answer": "WITHIN ONE’S SELF"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between paelex and supellex.",
    "answer": "PAELEX – MISTRESS / CONCUBINE; SUPELLEX - UTENSILS / FURNITURE / GOODS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between gracilis and grāculus.",
    "answer": "GRACILIS - SLENDER / GRACEFUL; GRĀCULUS - JACKDAW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate among harundō, hirundō, and hirūdō.",
    "answer": "HARUNDŌ - SHAFT / REED; HIRUNDŌ – SWALLOW; HIRŪDŌ - LEECH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which tribune, an uncle of Cato the Younger, attempted to end the equestrian monopoly on the quaestio de rebus repetundis before he was assassinated in 91 B.C.?",
    "answer": "LIVIUS DRUSUS THE YOUNGER / (M.) LIVIUS DRUSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which governor of Asia, the uncle of Livius Drusus, attempted to stop the extortions of the publicani, and as a result, was wrongly convicted in the extortion court and sentenced into exile at Smyrna in 92 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(P.) RUTILIUS RUFUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which consul of 91 B.C. gathered opposition to Drusus and is thought to have hired the assassins who killed him?",
    "answer": "(L. MARCIUS) PHILIPPUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The Latin phrase accusāre nēmō sē debet, nisi coram deō may be used in court in what circumstance?",
    "answer": "(WHEN) PLEADING THE FIFTH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In ancient Rome, on what type of structure would one find the following words: hōrās nōn nūmerō nisi serēnās?",
    "answer": "SUNDIAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Aside from requiescat in pāce and hic iacet sepultus, what three-word Latin phrase may also be found on a tombstone and is abbreviated as A.A.S.?",
    "answer": "ANNŌ AETĀTIS SUAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What led some Roman forces against the Gauls in 225 B.C., traveled to the Delphic Oracle after the Roman defeat at Cannae in 216 B.C., and was the first Roman historiographer?",
    "answer": "(Q.) FABIUS PICTOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What historian wrote the Historiae Romanae, which covered the period ranging from the end of the Trojan War to the death of Livia?",
    "answer": "(M.) VELLEIUS PATERCULUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What later annalist wrote Histories covering the years 90 to 78 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(L. CORNELIUS) SISENNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What battle of the 4th century A.D., fought against the Alamanni, was an example of a small, but skilled army triumphing over an overwhelming numerical disadvantage and proved the capability of the future emperor Julian when he took over the throne four years later?",
    "answer": "STRASBOURG / ARGENTORATUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Ammianus Marcellinus, what king of the Alamanni, defeated at Strasbourg, was the epitome of brute strength and temerity in combat yet cowardice in defeat?",
    "answer": "CHNODOMAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Julian’s predecessor was said to have instigated the Alamanni to invade Gaul to deal with what usurper to the imperial throne?",
    "answer": "MAGNENTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Euripides, what wife of Erechtheus granted him permission to sacrifice their daughters in order to secure victory against the Eleusinians led by Eumolpus?",
    "answer": "PRAXITHEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What earlier daughter of Cecrops, filled with envy by Athena, was turned into a rock by Hermes?",
    "answer": "AGLAURUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What minor goddess loved Cephalus, causing discord with his wife Procris?",
    "answer": "EOS / AURORA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate into Latin: While these plans were being made, it was fitting for us to address the people.",
    "answer": "DECĒBAT / OPORTĒBAT NŌS APPELLĀRE POPULUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Without using an infinitive, translate into Latin: She asked you what she should do.",
    "answer": "QUAESĪVIT / PETĪVIT Ā TĒ / ROGĀVIT TĒ QUID FACTŪRA ESSET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a relative pronoun, translate into Latin: But if no one else should follow, he said that he would go with the tenth legion alone.",
    "answer": "DIXIT SĒ CUM SŌLĀ DECIMĀ LEGIŌNE ITŪRUM (ESSE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage from Tacitus’ Annales, which I will read twice, and answer the questions that follow in English: nōbīs in artō et inglorius labor; immōta quippe aut modice lacessita pax, maestae urbis res et princeps proferendī imperī incuriōsus erat. nōn tamen sine ūsū fuerit introspicere illa prīmō aspectū levia ex quīs magnārum saepe rērum mōtus oriuntur. The question: How does Tacitus describe how one, at first glance, might view the events he writes about? TRIVIAL / LIGHT (from: introspicere illa prīmō aspectū levia)",
    "answer": "30"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Despite this, Tacitus then argues what about these events? (from: ex quīs magnārum saepe rērum mōtus oriuntur)",
    "answer": "THEY OFTEN SET INTO MOTION GREAT EVENTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name two examples that Tacitus considers examples of apparently insignificant history? (from: lacessita pax, maestae urbis res et princeps proferendī imperī incuriōsus erat)",
    "answer": "AN EMPEROR NEGLIGENT IN EXPANDING THE EMPIRE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Claiming to be an illegitimate son of Caligula, which Praetorian Prefect spread the rumor that Nero had fled to Egypt, causing the Praetorian Guard to switch their allegiance to Galba in 68 A.D.?",
    "answer": "(C. NYMPHIDIUS) SABINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After the death of Nero, who, co-Praetorian Prefect with Sabinus and close confidant of Nero, did Sabinus force to retire early on in 68 A.D., so he could become sole Praetorian Prefect?",
    "answer": "(OFONIUS) TIGELLINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Although Sabinus succeeded in removing Tigellinus as co-Praetorian Prefect, whom did Galba choose to replace Tigellinus, causing Sabinus to regret his support for Galba?",
    "answer": "CORNELIUS LACO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate this sentence into idiomatic English: Sunt quī istam nesciō quam pācem māgnopere laudent. THERE ARE THOSE WHO GREATLY PRAISE PEACE, WHATEVER IT IS [A&G 575b] (accept other equivalent colloquialism to “whatever it is”)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate this sentence into English: Licet gravissimē mihi nocitum sit, tē numquam relinquam.",
    "answer": "I WILL NEVER LEAVE YOU"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate this sentence into idiomatic English: Omnēs, simul vīrus bibēre mortuīque sunt, ut urbs ā nostrīs cōpiīs caperētur fēcimus.",
    "answer": "WE ALL SAW TO IT THAT THE CITY BE SEIZED BY OUR TROOPS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which 1st century A.D. author, who was so poor that he considered moving to Spain, secured a post at Rome with the help of a certain Meliboeus and flattered Nero in his seven eclogues, which are transmitted along with those of Nemesianus?",
    "answer": "(TITUS) CALPURNIUS SICULUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Sharing his name with another author, which playwright under Caligula wrote Phasma and Laureolus and featured special effects such as an onstage crucifixion?",
    "answer": "CATULLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which Roman tragedian was forced to commit suicide in 34 A.D. because of unflattering allusions to Tiberius in his play Atreus?",
    "answer": "31"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Book VII of the Aeneid is a lot of things, including a display of Virgil’s creativity in inventing weapons. Accompanied by warriors with a boot only on their right foot and armed with blue lead pellets, what son of Vulcan brings men from Gabii and his hometown of Praeneste to support Turnus?",
    "answer": "CAECULUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Curiously called Agamemnonius, what man leads troops from Aurunca and Cales armed with leashed javelins, shields, and curved scimitars?",
    "answer": "HALAESUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Virgil further describes the soldiers of what son of Telon and the nymph Sebethis, who use corktree bark helmets and throw their spears “in the Teuton fashion,” although what exactly Virgil meant by that is unclear?",
    "answer": "OEBALUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What late Republican figure served as proconsul of Gallia Comata but was perhaps most famous for suggesting the title Augustus to the Senate?",
    "answer": "(L. MUNATIUS) PLANCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Plancus held what office in 22 B.C., which was abolished until the appointment of Lucius Vitellius in 47 A.D.?",
    "answer": "CENSOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Suetonius’s De Vita Caesarum, who, the ancestor of Nero, forced Plancus to make way for him in the streets, even though he was only an aedile?",
    "answer": "(L.) DOMITIUS AHENOBARBUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The nouns altāria, nōnae, hīberna, and angustiae all belong to what category of words?",
    "answer": "PLŪRĀLIA TANTUM / PLURAL-ONLY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give a singular-only Latin noun meaning “wheat.”",
    "answer": "TRĪTICUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give two different plural-only Latin nouns for types of doors.",
    "answer": "VALVAE / FORĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the sentence, “I requested that the scout’s uncle come to the castle at noon,” identify all words derived from Latin.",
    "answer": "REQUEST, SCOUT, UNCLE, CASTLE, NOON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the sentence, “The count and I disagree on whether it takes a village to raise a child,” identify all words derived from Latin.",
    "answer": "COUNT, DISAGREE, VILLAGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For four of the words you have identified, give the Latin words, and their meanings, from which each is derived.",
    "answer": "32"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Perhaps an Ancient Roman equivalent to SparkNotes, what work of Roman history, later translated into Greek by Paeanius, covers the time of Romulus to the death of Jovian in 364 A.D., and was written at the request of the emperor Valens as an abridgement of the works of Livy and other historians?",
    "answer": "BREVIARIUM AB URBE CONDITA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Who was the author of the Breviarium ab Urbe Condita?",
    "answer": "EUTROPIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other, more well-known abridgements of Livy were written around the 4th century A.D., and survive intact to this day, save for just two sections?",
    "answer": "PERIOCHAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who rejects nomos, or manmade law, in favor of physis, or divine law, when she says, “I did not believe your proclamation had such power to enable one who will someday die to override the gods’ ordinances, unwritten and secure. They are not of today and yesterday; they live forever; none knows when first they were. These are the laws whose penalties I would not incur from the gods, through fear of any man’s temper,” as she disobeys her uncle Creon by burying her brother Polyneices?",
    "answer": "ANTIGONE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Sophocles’ Antigone, Creon’s anger and misogyny can be seen when he declares that “there are other fields for him to plow” in response to whose question of whether Creon would kill his son’s wife to be?",
    "answer": "ISMENE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Creon’s inflexibility and decision to sentence Antigone to death ultimately leave him in a state of living death, as he is forced to cope with the subsequent deaths of what two loved ones? Language:",
    "answer": "REPLACEMENT TOSSUPS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the meaning of the Latin adjective putus?",
    "answer": "PURE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the meaning of the Latin noun putus?",
    "answer": "BOY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The adjective putus gives us the Latin verb putō, which we commonly define as “to think.” What other meaning can putō have?",
    "answer": "TO TRIM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which two of the following six English words are derived from the same Latin root: erudition, rigmarole, corrugate, rouge, route, rowel?",
    "answer": "RIGMAROLE & ROWEL (FROM ROTA – WHEEL)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which two of the following six English words are derived from the same Latin root: ensign, savagery, sergeant, season, seminary, sexton?",
    "answer": "SEASON & SEMINARY (FROM SERŌ – TO JOIN TOGETHER)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which two of the following six English words are derived from the same Latin root: umpire, annex, niece, nonchalance, enervate, announce? History/Culture:",
    "answer": "UMPIRE & NONCHALANCE (FROM NŌN – NOT)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Initially appointed commander of Upper Germany by Galba in 69 A.D., what senator and general, stationed at Novaesium, was indecisive in both swearing allegiances to either Vitellius or Vespasian?",
    "answer": "HORDEONIUS FLACCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the midst of Hordeonius Flaccus’ inaction in the Batavian rebellion, what overzealous general took inconclusive action against Julius Civilis and was later killed by Julius Classicus and Tutor?",
    "answer": "DILLIUS VOCULA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What commander of the Lower Rhine instigated the rebellion of Julius Civilis? Mythology:",
    "answer": "FONTEIUS CAPITO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "On what island did Nauplius falsely signal to the Greek ships, causing them to crash on rocks?",
    "answer": "CAPHAREUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of Nauplius’s informed him of Palamedes’ death?",
    "answer": "OEAX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How did Oeax get the information to Nauplius? Literature:",
    "answer": "AND THREW IT IN THE OCEAN CERTAIN THAT IT WOULD REACH NAUPLIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Medea, Saturnalia, Iliacon, Catachthonion, Silvae, and De Incendio Urbis were all written by which Roman author who managed to be appointed quaestor before the minimum age by law?",
    "answer": "(MARCUS ANNAEUS) LUCAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin term describes the tone with which Lucan asserted his poem against Vergil’s?",
    "answer": "INDIGNATIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What phrase did Quintilian use to describe Lucan?",
    "answer": "34"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The antiquarian Lucius Aelius Stilo and the philosopher Antiochus of Ascalon were both teachers of what prolific Latin author?",
    "answer": "VARRO REATINUS / (M.) TERENTIUS VARRO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To which tragedian is Varro’s De Antiquitate Litterarum dedicated to?",
    "answer": "ACCIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In which work of Varro, does he establish key points about Rome’s origin?",
    "answer": "RES HUMANAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage from Cicero, which I will read twice, and answer the questions that follow in English: Et quoniam L. Torquātus, meus familiāris ac necessārius, iūdicēs, existimāvit, sī nostram in accūsātiōne suā necessitūdinem familiāritātemque violasset, aliquid sē dē auctōritāte meae dēfensiōnis posse dētrahere, cum huius perīculī prōpulsātiōne coniungam dēfensiōnem officī meī. The question: Whom is Cicero addressing here?",
    "answer": "THE JUDGES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What does Cicero consider Lucius Torquatus to be?",
    "answer": "HIS RELATIVE / KIN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What could Torquatus do to Cicero’s authority of his defense?",
    "answer": "DETRACT FROM IT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "As a child, what son of Ctesius was lured by his Phoenician nurse to the ship of merchants and was sold as a slave to Laertes, for whom he then worked as a swineherd?",
    "answer": "EUMAEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What goatherd of Odysseus betrayed his master by bringing weapons to the suitors and was punished by being hung from the rafters?",
    "answer": "MELANTHIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Melanthius and his equally treacherous sister Melantho were the children of what loyal, old servant of Odysseus?",
    "answer": "DOLIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What derivative of a Latin noun meaning “threshold” means “denoting an action or event preceding or done in preparation for something fuller or more important” and describes the round which you are in?",
    "answer": "PRELIMINARY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What derivative of a Latin verb meaning “it is permitted” means “use of free time for enjoyment”?",
    "answer": "LEISURE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What derivative of a Latin verb meaning “to bind” means “a mass meeting of people making a political protest or showing support for a cause”?",
    "answer": "RALLY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quaestor in 237 BC, censor in 230 BC, and consul five times, what man had the notable cognomen Verrucosus, meaning “warty,” but is best known for the attrition warfare with Hannibal for which he received the agnomen Cunctator?",
    "answer": "(QUINTUS) FABIUS MAXIMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Where in 217 BC did Hannibal escape Quintus Fabius Maximus through his ingenious use of oxen?",
    "answer": "(BATTLE OF) AGER FALERNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Catullus 64 focuses not only on the marriage of Peleus and Thetis, but also, though ekphrasis, on the betrayal and abandonment of what maiden by what hero?",
    "answer": "ARIADNE BY THESEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Shorter but similar in form to an epic, what type of poem is Catullus 64?",
    "answer": "EPYLLION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Catullus 64 was one of the longer poems in Catullus’ libellus, which he dedicated to whom?",
    "answer": "CORNELIUS NEPOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What name in mythology is shared by a son of Eos who was carried off by Aphrodite to become warden of her shrine and a son of Helios whose tragic death caused his sisters to turn into poplar trees?",
    "answer": "PHAËTHON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "The latter Phaethon’s sisters supposedly wept what substance upon the death of their brother?",
    "answer": "AMBER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What king of Liguria and friend of Phaethon left his people to mourn among the poplars, being transformed into a swan?",
    "answer": "CYCNUS / CYGNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate idiomatically into English: Cicerō ad patrēs conscriptōs orātiōnem habuit ut causam ageret.",
    "answer": "CICERO DELIVERED A SPEECH TO THE SENATORS TO PLEAD (HIS) CASE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate idiomatically into English: Multā nocte, Caesar mīlitēs hortātus est nē in Germaniam iter facerent.",
    "answer": "NOT TO JOURNEY INTO GERMANY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate idiomatically into English: Apud Marcum, eī, quī rēbus novīs studēbant, consilium cēpērunt.",
    "answer": "CAME UP WITH / HATCHED A PLAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Excluding all forms of alliteration, identify the rhetorical device found in the following phrase from Book 6 of the Aeneid: Illa sōlō fixōs oculōs adversa tenēbat.",
    "answer": "CHIASMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Excluding all forms of alliteration, identify the rhetorical device found in the following phrase from Book 6 of the Aeneid: Mīnōtaurus inest, Veneris monimenta nefandae.",
    "answer": "METONYMY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Excluding all forms of alliteration, identify the rhetorical device found in the following phrase from Book 4 of the Aeneid: Ūritur infēlix Dīdō tōtaque vagātur, urbe furens, quālis coniecta cerva sagitta.",
    "answer": "SIMILE / EXTENDED METAPHOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Who snatched victory from the jaws of defeat at the battle of Margus River in 285 AD, beating Carinus and paving the way for the creation of the Tetrarchy?",
    "answer": "DIOCLETIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which edict, issued by Diocletian in 302 AD, placed a price ceiling on all things from wheat and barley to bed linens and craftsmen’s wages?",
    "answer": "EDICT ON MAXIMUM PRICES"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Against which Persian king did Diocletian and Galerius wage a war, culminating in the capture of Nisibis and the sack of Ctesiphon?",
    "answer": "NARSES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "An event deviating greatly from what is expected is called a “black swan,” a reference to a quotation by what Roman author, who gave this as an example of a rare bird?",
    "answer": "JUVENAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Give the entire quotation from Juvenal’s Satires, which starts with rāra and ends with cȳcno.",
    "answer": "RĀRA AVIS IN TERRĪS NIGRŌQUE SIMILLIMA CȲCNŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The English sentence “John and Judy are rara avises” is technically fine, but using you are Latin students! Give the alternative English plural of rara avis that better maintains its Latin origin.",
    "answer": "RARAE AVES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which Roman author, who was said to have been born in Terni, began his political career under Vespasian, became consul suffectus in 97 A.D., delivered Virginius Rufus’ funeral oration, and wrote a biography of his father-in-law Agricola?",
    "answer": "(PUBLIUS / GAIUS CORNELIUS) TACITUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The description of the punishments suffered by the Christians after the Great Fire of 64 A.D. appears in what historical work of Tacitus?",
    "answer": "ANNALES"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "With his friend’s help, Tacitus prosecuted the ex-governor Marius Priscus for his crimes against Africa. Name this friend, who later became the governor of Bithynia.",
    "answer": "PLINY THE YOUNGER / GAIUS PLINIUS SECUNDUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Phantasos, Icelos, and Morpheus were all sons of what god, the personification of sleep?",
    "answer": "HYPNOS / SOMNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "All three of Hypnos’s children could appear in dreams, each taking a specific form. What form did Morpheus take?",
    "answer": "HUMANS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What forms did Icelos and Phantasos take, respectively?",
    "answer": "ANIMALS; INANIMATE OBJECTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Though lacking a perfect passive participle, what Latin verb has a fourth principal part, when given in dictionary entries, since its future active participle futūrus is used instead?",
    "answer": "SUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What compound of sum means “to be lacking”?",
    "answer": "DĒSUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What compound of sum means “to be in charge of” and takes the dative case?",
    "answer": "PRAESUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "According to the Roman historian Festus, what office in Roman Republic was considered the highest ranked of all priests though he was a figurehead performing minor religious duties assigned to the king during the Monarchy?",
    "answer": "REX SACRORUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What title was fittingly given to the wife of the rex sacrorum?",
    "answer": "REGINA SACRORUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Identify two of the three groups of priests classified under flamines maiores.",
    "answer": "(FLAMEN) DIALIS / MARTIALIS / QUIRINALIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using the adjective incarcerātus, say in Latin: I do not know why the caged bird sings.",
    "answer": "4"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using quaerō, say in Latin: I asked you from where you had received that money.",
    "answer": "Ā TĒ QUAESĪVĪ UNDE ILLAM PECŪNIAM ACCĒPISSĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using rogō, say in Latin: I asked you to buy that for me as quickly as possible.",
    "answer": "TĒ ROGĀVĪ UT ILLUD MIHI QUAM CELERRIMĒ EMERĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What satirist frequently used vocabulary of the body, most often the imagery of the stomach, in his 6 books of satires, and was a good friend of Lucan?",
    "answer": "(AULES) PERSIUS (FLACCUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Where in Etruria was Persius born?",
    "answer": "VOLTERRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Stoic teacher of Persius served as a great influence on his Satires?",
    "answer": "CORNUTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "When translated into Latin, the sentence “Messenger, what news do you have for me?” can contain a genitive. Provide the Latin for that genitive word and identify its usage.",
    "answer": "NOVĪ; PARTITIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "When translated into Latin, the sentence “The messenger walked into the city Athens” can contain a genitive. Provide the Latin for that genitive word and identify its usage.",
    "answer": "ATHĒNĀRUM; APPOSITIONAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "When translated into Latin, the sentence “The messenger has a reputation for boldness” contains a genitive. Provide the Latin for that genitive word and identify its usage.",
    "answer": "AUDĀCIAE; OBJECTIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Called a “beautiful evil” by Hesiod, who was given a human voice by Hephaestus, taught crafts and weaving by Athena, and given charm as well as terrible longing cares by Aphrodite, before being sent by Hermes as a gift to Epimetheus?",
    "answer": "PANDORA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Epimetheus and Pandora had a daughter named Pyrrha who would marry her cousin Deucalion. Who were the Deucalion’s parents?",
    "answer": "PROMETHEUS AND PRONOEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The story of Pandora in Hesiod’s Works and Days precedes his telling of the Ages of Man, during which Hesiod laments being a part of which age?",
    "answer": "IRON AGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Alliteratively translate into Latin the phrase “by means of a very bad apple.”",
    "answer": "PŌMŌ PESSIMŌ / PESSIMA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Alliteratively translate into Latin the phrase “of an ivory sword.”",
    "answer": "ENSIS EBURNEĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Alliteratively translate into Latin the phrase “by means of a small ship.”",
    "answer": "PUPPĪ PARVĀ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man’s experiences at the siege of Numantia led him to observe Rome as an “urbem vēnālem et mātūrē peritūram, sī emptōrem invēnerit,” though he was unable to buy victory when he waged war with the Romans from 112-106 BC?",
    "answer": "JUGURTHA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Jugurtha was survived only by his son Oxyntas, of which hardly anything is known except that he participated in what later war?",
    "answer": "THE SOCIAL / MARSIC WAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name the two half-brothers of Jugurtha with which he quarreled over control of Numidia. Replacement Language:",
    "answer": "HIEMPSAL & ADHERBAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "“Predecessor” and “procedure” are derived from what Latin verb with what meaning?",
    "answer": "CĒDŌ – TO YIELD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "“Caress” and “charity” are derived from what Latin adjective with what meaning?",
    "answer": "CĀRUS – CARING"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "“Ceiling” and “cerulean” are derived from what Latin noun with what meaning?",
    "answer": "CAELUM – SKY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the Latin motto of the Olympic Games?",
    "answer": "CITIUS, ALTIUS, FORTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "As you probably know, the Olympic Games’ motto consists of three comparative adjectives. What state motto consists of one comparative adjective?",
    "answer": "NEW YORK"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin phrase that can mean “being without examination or analysis” also contains a comparative adjective? Replacement Mythology:",
    "answer": "Ā PRIŌRĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What king of Calydon, who killed his son Toxeus for jumping over a ditch, failed to sacrifice the first fruits of the harvest to Artemis and was punished for the insult with a giant boar?",
    "answer": "OENEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Oeneus eventually killed the monster, although he gave the skin to Atalanta?",
    "answer": "MELEAGER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Oeneus’ wife Althaea later killed herself out of guilt for her role in Meleager’s death, causing Oeneus to marry what woman, who bore him Olenias and Tydeus? Replacement History:",
    "answer": "PERIBOEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Bloodless offerings such as flowers, wine, and incense were given to one’s Genius or Iuno on what special day?",
    "answer": "(A PERSON’S) BIRTHDAY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What color were the garments worn during the celebration?",
    "answer": "WHITE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Roman term describes the day on which a child received his/her name? Replacement Literature:",
    "answer": "DIES LUSTRICUS / DIES NŌMINUM / NŌMINĀLIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which author, the first to employ alliteration in dactylic hexameter, was ranked last on Volcacius Sedigitus’ list merely because of his earliness?",
    "answer": "(QUINTUS) ENNIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Because of which author’s earlier work is it believed Ennius must have written on the First Punic War with much concision in his Annales?",
    "answer": "(GNAEUS) NAEVIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To what public records does the title of Ennius’ magnum opus refer to?",
    "answer": "ROUND 2"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, born in 26 AD, was said to have purchased the tomb of Vergil and practically worshipped the poet?",
    "answer": "SILIUS ITALICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Giving credence to the maxim “Quality over quantity,” which of Silius Italicus’ works was the longest yet supposedly worst Latin epic?",
    "answer": "PUNICA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How did Silius Italicus die?",
    "answer": "SUICIDE BY STARVATION TO DEATH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb pōnō, give the future passive infinitive.",
    "answer": "POSITUM ĪRĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What do forms of deus can deum be?",
    "answer": "ACC. SG., GEN. PL."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate between the forms pōnentis and pōnentīs.",
    "answer": "PŌNENTĪS – ACC. PL. PRES. ACT. PART."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Iphiclus left Phylace and his newly-wedded wife Laodameia to go Troy, never to see either again, since he perished as soon as he set foot on Trojan soil?",
    "answer": "PROTESILAUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the Trojans killed Protesilaus as he arrived at Troy?",
    "answer": "HECTOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What brother of Protesilaus assumed control of the Phylacian contingent upon the death of Protesilaus?",
    "answer": "PODARCES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whose death at Lorium ended a remarkable reign, one free of any significant uprisings or military campaigns and shorter only to Augustus’ reign during the Principate?",
    "answer": "ANTONINUS PIUS’"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "During the Principate, which emperor reigned the third longest after Augustus and Antoninus Pius?",
    "answer": "TIBERIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Antoninus Pius was the last emperor born in the 1st century AD. Who was the last emperor born in the 1st century BC?",
    "answer": "CLAUDIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Identify the case and use of senatōribus in the following sentence: Hīs verbīs dictīs, senātōribus persuādendum erit.",
    "answer": "DATIVE WITH SPECIAL VERBS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate that sentence.",
    "answer": "WITH THESE WORDS SPOKEN, THE SENATORS WILL HAVE TO BE PERSUADED."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Explain why persuādeō takes the dative.",
    "answer": "7"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in Latin: Follow me to Sicily, soldiers.",
    "answer": "SEQUIMINI MĒ AD SICILIAM, MĪLITĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in Latin: I thought the men who followed me were Gauls.",
    "answer": "SCIŌ VIRŌS, QUĪ MĒ SECŪTĪ ESSENT, GALLŌS ESSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in Latin: Let us follow the leader most worthy of command!",
    "answer": "DŪCEM DIGNISSIMUM IMPERIŌ SEQUĀMUR!"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What historian, who composed philosophical dialogues in his youth, turned to history at the age of 30 and devoted himself to a massive historical work of 142 books entitled Ab Urbe Condita?",
    "answer": "(TITUS) LIVIUS / LIVY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Although only 35 books remain of Livy’s work, we possess summaries for most of the lost books. What is the term for these summaries?",
    "answer": "PERIOCHAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Livy encouraged the historiographic interests of what emperor?",
    "answer": "CLAUDIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage, which I will read twice, and answer the questions that follow in Latin: Marcus Antōnius ingens bellum cīvīle commōvit cōgente uxōre Cleopātrā dum cupīditāte muliebrī optat etiam in urbe regnāre. Marcus Antōnius victus est ab Augustō in nāvālī pugnā clarā et illustrī apud Actium, quī locus in Ēpīrō est, ex quā in Aegyptum fūgit et, cum omnēs ad Augustum transīrent, ipse sē interfēcit. Cleopātra sibi aspidem admīsit et venēnō eius extincta est. The question: Quāle proelium erat apud Actium?",
    "answer": "NAVĀLE / CLĀRUM / ILLUSTRE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quis coēgit Antōnium ut bellum commoveret?",
    "answer": "CLEOPĀTRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quōmodo Cleopātra extincta est?",
    "answer": "ASPIDE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Originally called Strongyle, which of the Cyclades was the site of Butes’s rape of Coronis, the deaths of Otus and Ephialtes, and the birth of Dionysus, although it is more famous for being the location where Dionysus found the mourning Ariadne?",
    "answer": "NAXOS / DIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name the sister of the Aloadae, who was kidnapped by pirates and taken to Naxos.",
    "answer": "PANCRATIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name the mother of the Aloadae, who was also kidnapped and taken there.",
    "answer": "IMPHIMEDIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to legend, what foreign king was buried under the Busentus River by his soldiers in 410 AD, the same year he sacked Rome?",
    "answer": "ALARIC"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Alaric attempted to siege Rome in 408 and 409 AD, in what city was the emperor Honorius hiding?",
    "answer": "RAVENNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What urban prefect had been declared emperor in place of the missing Honorius?",
    "answer": "PRISCUS ATTALUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following, if any, does not belong due to derivation: empress, severance, imperial, parasol, or parapet? NONE (all are derived from parō)",
    "answer": "8"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following, if any, does not belong due to derivation: reappear, disparage, apparent, apparition, or transparent?",
    "answer": "DISPARAGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following, if any, does not belong due to derivation: parcel, repartee, tripartite participant, or particle? NONE (all are derived from pars)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When one of his bull wandered into the kingdom of Eryx, what hero was forced to wrestle with the Sicilian king Eryx, a match that he handily won?",
    "answer": "HERACLES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Eryx was the son of Aphrodite by the Argonaut Butes or by which god?",
    "answer": "POSEIDON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What descendant of Eryx welcomes Aeneas to Sicily in the Aeneid?",
    "answer": "ACESTES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The claim of being his mistress’ slave, the pursuit of love rather than a military career, the stories of Tarpeia and Vertumnus, and the love affair with Cynthia all appear in the elegies of what Umbrian poet?",
    "answer": "(SEXTUS) PROPERTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The fourth book of Propertius’ elegies, unlike the preceding books, do not discuss Propertius’ relationship with Cynthia. Instead, they recount the origins of Roman myths in a manner similar to the Aitia of which Hellenistic poet?",
    "answer": "CALLIMACHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Propertius also took inspiration from what poet from Cos who wrote the highly acclaimed Demeter?",
    "answer": "PHILITAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Plutarch, what man served as a foil to military commanders by conquering more cities in Greece through eloquence than his advisee, Pyrrhus, did through arms?",
    "answer": "CINEAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "After the Battle of Heraclea, what aged senator prevented another such “conquest” by persuading his colleagues to unanimously reject the tempting peace terms offered by Cineas?",
    "answer": "APPIUS CLAUDIUS CAECUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Given Rome’s past, it is quite ironic that Cineas likened the Roman senators to an assembly of what?",
    "answer": "KINGS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Amantium īrae amoris integratiōst, Senectus ipsast morbus, and Fortis fortūna adiuvat are all phrases attributed to what Roman playwright?",
    "answer": "TERENCE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What phrase of Terence expresses the fact that there is considerable diversity of opinion and thus a difficulty of bringing about agreement?",
    "answer": "QUOT HOMINĒS TOT SENTENTIAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What phrase of Terence indicates that something can be understood without any need for explanation, if the listener has enough wisdom or common sense?",
    "answer": "DICTUM SAPIENTĪ SAT EST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Euboean was nursed by Gaia to enormous size and eventually attempted to rape Leto as she went to Delphi through Panopeus?",
    "answer": "TITYUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What mother of Tityus did Zeus hide in the earth to shield her from the vengeance of Hera?",
    "answer": "ELARES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of animals ate Tityus’ liver as he was stretched over nine acres?",
    "answer": "VULTURES / SNAKES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What does the phrase simul atque mean?",
    "answer": "AS SOON AS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give a synonym of simul atque.",
    "answer": "CUM PRĪMUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What does the correlative cum … tum mean?",
    "answer": "BOTH … AND / NOT ONLY … BUT ALSO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Pompeius Muscosus, Marcus Aurelius Liber, Publius Aelius Gutta Calpurnianus, and Gaius Apuleius Diocles were all memorialized in inscriptions for their great number of victories in what Roman spectacle?",
    "answer": "CHARIOT-RACING"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Described in Book 5 of Virgil’s Aeneid, there were occasionally exhibitions of horsemanship by young men of the nobility in the Circus, when chariot races were not taking place. What were these exhibitions called?",
    "answer": "LUDUS / LUDI TROIAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "More exciting to the spectators, though, were the gory venationes, or hunts. Which of the following animals, if any, were not among those slaughtered at these hunts: panthers, bears, lions, elephants, hippopotamuses, or crocodiles? NONE (all were slaughtered)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Putēs eum hominem bonum esse.",
    "answer": "YOU MIGHT THINK THAT HE IS A GOOD MAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Utinam nē meō cibō vescantur!",
    "answer": "WOULD THAT THEY NOT EAT MY FOOD!"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Quid nōn facerēs?",
    "answer": "WHAT WERE YOU NOT TO DO?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Silver Age author’s attempt to create an inventory of all the knowledge of man resulted in a 37- book encyclopedic work called the Naturalis Historia?",
    "answer": "PLINY THE ELDER / (GAIUS) PLINIUS (SECUNDUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To whom was the Naturalis Historia dedicated?",
    "answer": "TITUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work of Pliny the Elder is a historical work on the German campaigns? Replacement Language:",
    "answer": "BELLA GERMANIAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give all the infinitives for the verb moveō.",
    "answer": "MOVĒRE, MOVĒRĪ, MOVISSE, MŌTUS ESSE, MŌTŪRUS ESSE, MŌTUM ĪRĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Do the same for the verb conor.",
    "answer": "CŌNĀRĪ, CŌNĀTUS ESSE, CŌNĀTŪRUS ESSE, CŌNĀTUM ĪRĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Do the same for the verb supersum.",
    "answer": "10"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat: temerē?",
    "answer": "RASHLY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat: pharētra?",
    "answer": "QUIVER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat: iūdicium? Replacement Mythology:",
    "answer": "TRIAL / JUDGMENT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which priest of Dionysus loved a girl in Calydon and asked for help from Dionysus?",
    "answer": "CORESUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whom was the girl he loved?",
    "answer": "CALLIRRHOË"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was interesting about the fact that Coresus killed himself for Callirrhoë? Replacement History:",
    "answer": "SHE KILLED HERSELF AFTER SEEING HIS DEAD BODY"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "At the Battle of Watling Street, Suetonius Paulinus finally put an end to whose revolt in Britain during the reign of Nero?",
    "answer": "BOUDIC(E)A"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What capital city of the Trinovantes did Boudica and her soldiers raze?",
    "answer": "CAMULODUNUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Boudica’s revolt was inspired particularly by the Romans annexation of her territory, which disrespected the will of her husband. Who was her husband? Replacement Literature:",
    "answer": "PRASUTAGUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which Roman author, born around 82 B.C., was part of the cantores Euphorionis and wrote works including Ephemeris, Chorographia, Bellum Sequanicum, and Argonautae?",
    "answer": "(PUBLIUS TERENTIUS) VARRO ATACINUS / VARRO OF ATAX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the topic of Ephemeris, perhaps a nod to Aratus’ Phaenoemna?",
    "answer": "WEATHER (SIGNS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the name of Varro’s mistress, who is the eponymous title of his collection of erotic poetry?",
    "answer": "ROUND 3"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Romans’ stigma against Oriental women due to memories of Cleopatra forced what daughter of Herod Agrippa I to be abandoned by her lover when he became emperor after his father Vespasian’s death?",
    "answer": "BERENICE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Christian woman was the mistress of Commodus?",
    "answer": "MARCIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After her husband’s death, what Eastern woman sought legitimacy to her rule of Egypt through supposed descent from Cleopatra?",
    "answer": "ZENOBIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following, if any, does not belong due to gender: sanguis, rugītus, procus, praeses, or rūpes?",
    "answer": "RŪPES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which word from the tossup would be described by the sentence: Sī ūnum habēs, salvus sentis?",
    "answer": "PRAESES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which word from the tossup would be described by the sentence: Pēnelopē multōs habet?",
    "answer": "PROCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Melete, Mneme, and Aeode were the original three members of what group who resided on either Mount Helicon or Mount Parnassus?",
    "answer": "MUSES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What nine sisters lost to the Muses in a music contest and were transformed into magpies?",
    "answer": "PIERIDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What bard also lost to the Muses and was a result was blinded?",
    "answer": "THAMYRIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into English: Imperātor, quī sē nōn contineat, exercitum continēre nōn potest.",
    "answer": "IS NOT ABLE TO RESTRAIN THE ARMY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The relative clause of characteristic has its origins in another use of the subjunctive and is the origin of yet another use of the subjunctive. Identify both, respectively.",
    "answer": "POTENTIAL; RESULT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into English: Tālis clamor in cūriā factus est ut populus convenīret.",
    "answer": "THAT THE PEOPLE CAME TOGETHER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Excluding compound verbs, identify two verbs that often used with ablative of price.",
    "answer": "VERTŌ & MUTŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Tantī and magnī can exemplify what analogous use of the genitive?",
    "answer": "INDEFINITE VALUE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now say in Latin: It happened that the king traded his kingdom for a horse.",
    "answer": "12"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Pugil, Epistula, Synaristosae, Epicleros, and Plocium were all written by what Insubrian Gaul, considered the best comedic writer by Volcacius Sedigitus?",
    "answer": "CAECILIUS STATIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Most of Caecilius Statius’s writing is extant through the writings of what later author of the Attic Nights?",
    "answer": "AULUS GELLIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "After what battle of 222 BC was Caecilius Statius brought to Rome?",
    "answer": "CLASTIDIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Driven from Jutland and Schleswig by overpopulation, what two tribes inflicted on Rome a loss of 80,000 men at the Battle of Arausio of 105 BC?",
    "answer": "CIMBRI & TEUTONES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the names of the Roman commanders who were humiliated and defeated by the Cimbri and Teutones at Arausio.",
    "answer": "(CN.) MALLIUS (MAXIMUS) & (Q.) (SERVILIUS) CAEPIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Marius eventually defeated the Teutones and Cimbri in 102 and 101 BC, respectively. Name the corresponding battles.",
    "answer": "AQUAE SEXTIAE; VERCELLAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using crēdō and a synonym of ille say in Latin: Surely we’ve trusted that one sailor?",
    "answer": "NONNE ISTĪ ŪNĪ NAUTAE CRĒDIDIMUS?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now using a semi-deponent synonym of crēdō, say in Latin: These sailors always trusted us.",
    "answer": "HĪ NAUTAE SEMPER NŌBĪS FĪSĪ SUNT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now using a semi-deponent verb in both the protasis and apodosis, say in Latin: If these sailors had trusted us, we would have rejoiced.”",
    "answer": "SĪ HĪ NAUTAE NŌBĪS FĪSĪ ESSENT, GAVĪSĪ ESSĒMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Shakespeare’s A Comedy of Errors was inspired by what play of Plautus, which tells the story of two twins who meet each other for the first time as adults in the city of Epidamnus?",
    "answer": "MENAECHMI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What play of Plautus contains the only extant passages of the Carthaginian language?",
    "answer": "POENULUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What play of Plautus concerns the slave Phronesium, who cheats her three lovers?",
    "answer": "TRUCULENTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Anoerestus and Concolitanus led the Gallic assault against the Romans but were defeated by Gaius Atilius Regulus and Lucius Aemilius Papus at what battle of 225 BC?",
    "answer": "(BATTLE OF) CAPE TELAMON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which tribune of 232 BC’s land redistribution policies alarmed the Gauls into attacking the Romans?",
    "answer": "(C.) FLAMINIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Gaius Flaminius had a habit of supporting populist policies despite becoming a senator. In fact, which tribune of 218 BC’s law prohibiting senators and their sons from performing transactions was Flaminius the only senator to support?",
    "answer": "(Q.) CLAUDIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Giving person, number, tense, voice, and mood, fully parse the verb form portābāre. nd PERS. SG. IMPERF. PASS. INDIC.",
    "answer": "13"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Giving person, number, tense, voice, and mood, fully parse the verb form portāverē. rd PERS. PL. PERF. ACT. INDIC.",
    "answer": "3"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Giving person, number, tense, voice, and mood, fully parse the verb form māvīs. nd PERS. SG. PRES. ACT. INDIC.",
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What mythical thief could change the color and form of stolen objects—an ability he put to good use when he stole a helmet from Amyntor’s armory and carried off the cattle of Eurytus?",
    "answer": "AUTOLYCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, who won Eurytus’ daughter Iole in an archery contest, did Autolycus blame for this theft?",
    "answer": "HERACLES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What daughter of Daedalion was the father of Autolycus by Hermes?",
    "answer": "CHIONE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which Roman author, a Sabine who had a rocky political career, followed in the footsteps of Coelius Antipater in rejecting the annalistic tradition and instead, wrote monographs titled Bellum Iugurthinum and Bellum Catilinae?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) SALLUST(IUS) (CRISPUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the year of Sallust’s birth.",
    "answer": "86 BC"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Sallust’s Historiae, an unfinished treatise covering the years 78 to 67 BC, consists of how many books?",
    "answer": "FIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Based on its derivation, what does the word “sortilege” mean?",
    "answer": "READING / DIVINATION BY LOTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Based on its derivation, what does the word “amanuensis” mean? SECRETARY/SCRIBE (accept any similar job requiring primarily use of one’s hands)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Based on its origins, what is a “Maecenas”?",
    "answer": "PATRON (OF THE ARTS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "The usurper Leucus seized upon what man’s absence during the Trojan War, seducing and killing his wife Meda and driving him from Crete upon his return?",
    "answer": "IDOMENEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What father of Palamedes had instigated this usurpation?",
    "answer": "NAUPLIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What Cretan had been Idomeneus’ second-in-command at Troy and survived the war, although his subsequent fate is unknown?",
    "answer": "MERIONES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author began his career in law, having studied under Arellius Fuscus and Porcius Latro, but later abandoned his legal career to write works like Ibis, Epistulae ex Ponto, Tristia, and Amores?",
    "answer": "(PUBLIUS) OVID(IUS NASO)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of his works, for the most part, contains letters from various heroines to their lovers?",
    "answer": "HEROIDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In letters 16-21, there are 3 pairs of lovers for which both the male and female wrote. Name one such pair.",
    "answer": "14"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following abbreviations, if any, would not be inscribed on a tombstone: D.M., H.J.S., NONE (all belong)",
    "answer": "R.I.P., S.T.T.L.?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give both the Latin and English for the abbreviation D.M.",
    "answer": "DĪS MANIBUS – TO THE SPIRITS OF THE DEAD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give both the Latin and English for the abbreviation S.T.T.L.",
    "answer": "SIT TERRA TIBI LEVIS – MAY THE EARTH REST LIGHTLY ON YOU"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What nurse of Myrrha helped her lay with Cinyras and shares her name with a daughter of Ares who possessed a magical girdle?",
    "answer": "HIPPOLYTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was the mother of Myrrha?",
    "answer": "CENCHREÏS / METHARME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Besides Cinyras with either Myrrha or Metharme, what couple may have been the parents of Adonis?",
    "answer": "PHOENIX & ALPHESIBOEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "According to Vitruvius, what Roman siege weapon, its precursor the Greek oxybeles, resembled large crossbows and would hurl large rocks to destroy enemy walls?",
    "answer": "BALLISTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The onager was a Roman catapulta named for its resemblance to what kind of animal?",
    "answer": "DONKEY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What catapulta was named for its resemblance to an animal the Romans considered a type of fish?",
    "answer": "SCORPIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage from Julius Caesar, which I will read twice, and answer the questions that follow in English: Haec cīvitas longē plūrimum tōtius Galliae equitātū valet magnāsque habet copiās peditum Rhēnumque, ut sūprā dēmonstrāvimus, tangit. In eā cīvitāte duo dē principātū inter sē contendēbant, Indutiomarus et Cingetorix. The question: The state which Caesar describes here borders what geographical feature?",
    "answer": "THE RHINE RIVER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what two military aspects does this state excel?",
    "answer": "INFANTRY & CAVALRY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What were Indutiomarus and Cingetorix fighting for? Replacement Language:",
    "answer": "RULE OVER THE STATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the sentence “Solōne dūce, Athēnae insulā potitae est,” identify both uses of the ablative.",
    "answer": "ABSOLUTE & WITH DEPONENT VERBS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin word meaning “skilled” can take both the ablative and the genitive?",
    "answer": "PERĪTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Verbs like memini often take the genitive. What synonym of memini involves an ablative word?",
    "answer": "MEMORIĀ TENĒRE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give all the principle parts of the Latin deponent verb meaning “to forget.”",
    "answer": "15"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give all the principle parts of the Latin verb meaning either “to complain.”",
    "answer": "QUEROR, QUERĪ, QUESTUS SUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give all the principle parts of the Latin deponent verb meaning “to promise.” Replacement Mythology:",
    "answer": "POLLICEOR, POLLICĒRĪ, POLLICITUS SUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Minos vanished while chasing a mouse and was later found drowned in a vat of honey by the seer Poyleidus, who then resurrected him?",
    "answer": "GLAUCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Minos had earlier learned from an oracle that strange events were afoot in Crete and the man who could find the aptest simile to describe them would find his son. To what did Polyeidus compare a calf which was changing color daily from white to red to black?",
    "answer": "STAGES OF A RIPENING MULBERRY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Some say that it was not Polyeidus, but rather what man who revived Glaucus? Replacement History:",
    "answer": "ASCLEPIUS / AESCULAPIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Gannicus, Castus, Crixus, and Oenamaus were four Gallic gladiators that led a major slave uprising with what Thracian man?",
    "answer": "SPARTACUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Spartacus was trained at the gladiator school of what man?",
    "answer": "LENTULUS BATIATUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of gladiator was Spartacus? Replacement Literature:",
    "answer": "MURMILLO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which author, born in Madura, married his best friend’s widowed mother Pudentilla?",
    "answer": "(LUCIUS) APULEIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was that best friend of his?",
    "answer": "PONTIANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which work of his was considered a reworking of Peri Kosmou and is one of the earlier times writers have tried to incorporate the technical natural sciences into Latin?",
    "answer": "SEMIFINAL ROUND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of Amherst College, Dartmouth College, Hunter College, Indiana University Bloomington, and University of Chicago, which contains a subjunctive within its Latin motto.",
    "answer": "UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of the institutions listed in the toss up, which one contains a participle within its motto?",
    "answer": "DARTMOUTH COLLEGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of the institutions listed in the toss up, which one contains a subjective genitive in its motto?",
    "answer": "HUNTER COLLEGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What battle of the 2nd Punic War proved decisive, for it prevented Hasdrubal from joining forces with Hannibal and it buoyed Roman hopes three years after the winning commander Publius Cornelius Scipio the Elder lost to Hannibal at Ticinus River and just one year after the disaster at Cannae?",
    "answer": "DERTOSA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Both Roman commanders at Dertosa were killed in battle against Hannibal in 211 BC?",
    "answer": "UPPER BAETIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Two years later, Publius Cornelius Scipio the Younger would avenge his father’s death at Upper Baetis by winning what battle?",
    "answer": "CARTHAGO NOVA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was driven from his homeland of Elis because he sided with a stranger against his father in a dispute concerning payment for cleaning some incredibly filthy stables?",
    "answer": "PHYLEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To where did Phyleus go and later become king?",
    "answer": "DULICHIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Because the Spartan king Tyndareus forgot to sacrifice to her once, Aphrodite made three of his daughters be unfaithful to their husbands. Which of these daughters abandoned her husband Echemus and shacked up with Phyleus?",
    "answer": "TIMANDRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which Roman author, part of an avant-garde literary circle that developed in the Late Republic, hailed from Bresica in Cisalpine Gaul, accompanied Catullus on an expedition to Bithynia in 57 BC, and wrote of the incestuous love between Myrrha and Cinryas in Zmyrna?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS HELVIUS) CINNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Catullus, how many years did it take Cinna to compose Zmyrna?",
    "answer": "NINE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To whom, a literary critic and later consul of 40 BC, did Cinna address a Propempticon?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) ASINIUS POLLIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into English: Spectātum veniunt et veniunt ut spectentur.",
    "answer": "THEY COME TO SEE AND TO BE SEEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What part of speech is the first word of that quote, and from what author is that quote taken?",
    "answer": "SUPINE; OVID"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into English: Cum Perseus Medūsam vicisset, monstrum ipsum vīsū horribilem vultum vīdit.",
    "answer": "THE VERY MONSTER SAW A FACE HORRIBLE TO SEE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Pliny the Younger, what woman had a double canine in her right jaw, symbolizing good luck, though it may not have seemed so the moment she told her assassin Anicetus to smite the womb, with which she gave birth to her vile son?",
    "answer": "AGRIPPINA THE YOUNGER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name two ways her son Nero related to his predecessor Claudius.",
    "answer": "GRANDNEPHEW / STEPSON / SON-IN-LAW (OF CLAUDIUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What freedwoman from Asia Minor did Nero take as his mistress, to his mother’s disapproval?",
    "answer": "(CLAUDIA) ACTE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Book 5, line 451 of the Aeneid, what case and use besides the nominative subject are exemplified by the phrase it clamor caelō?",
    "answer": "DATIVE OF DIRECTION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Staying with datives, use a double dative to say in Latin: This bridge will especially be of use to Caesar.",
    "answer": "HĪC PONS ŪSUĪ CAESARĪ MAXIMĒ ERIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate and identify the use of the dative in this sentence: Hostis mīlitī scūtum arripuit.",
    "answer": "THE ENEMY SNATCHED THE SHIELD FROM THE SOLDIER; SEPARATION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What son of Zeus and Aex recommended to the gods that they take the forms of animal to escape Typhon, but is more famous for teaming up with Hermes to steal back the sinews of Zeus from Typhon?",
    "answer": "(AEGI)PAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In a somewhat random turn of events, the form Aegipan took to escape Typhon was half-goat and half what animal?",
    "answer": "FISH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To retrieve the sinews of Zeus, Hermes and Aegipan went to the Corycian Cave in Cilicia, where the sinews were being guarded by what dragon-woman?",
    "answer": "DELPHYNE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, who was prosecuted by Sejanus, gave a voice to the subservient social classes of Rome in stories such as the tale of the Flautist named Princeps and famously established the promythion and epimythion as regular structural elements of the fable?",
    "answer": "PHAEDRUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what meter did Phaedrus write his fables?",
    "answer": "IAMBIC SENARII"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Phaedrus is indebted to what Greek author for much of the material of his fables?",
    "answer": "AESOP"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which two of the following six English words are derived from the same Latin root: tent, contemplation, tentacle, discontent, ostensible, and contemporary?",
    "answer": "TENT & OSTENSIBLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The noun “tense” and the adjective “tense” are derived from two different Latin words, from which two of the words in the tossup are derived. Identify these two English words, respectively.",
    "answer": "CONTEMPORARY; DISCONTENT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The words “temper” and “tempter” are derived from two different Latin words, one of which is the derivation of a word in the tossup. Of these two options, give the Latin word from which no words in the tossup are derived.",
    "answer": "18"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using two irregular verbs, say in Latin: I do not doubt that Caesar wants to go to Rome.",
    "answer": "NŌN DUBITŌ QUĪN CAESAR RŌMAM ĪRE VĒLIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in Latin: I did not doubt that Caesar had wanted to go to Rome.",
    "answer": "NŌN DUBITĀVĪ (-BAM) QUĪN CAESAR RŌMAM ĪRE VOLUISSET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in Latin: Thetis wept when she had discovered that her son, who had killed many Trojans, would not live much longer.",
    "answer": "MULTŌ DIŪTIUS NŌN VICTŪRUM, THETIS LĀCRIMĀVIT (-BAT)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Eos and Astraeus, who was sometimes represented in art with snake tails in place of feet, saved the inhabitants of Megalopolis from a Spartan attack and destroyed the Persians at Salamis?",
    "answer": "BOREAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name all four children of Boreas and Oreithyia.",
    "answer": "ZETES, CALAÏS, CLEOPATRA, CHIONE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which Athenian king was the father of Oreithyia?",
    "answer": "ERECHTHEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What future participant in the Ides of March, in a similar fashion to Duilius at Mylae, defeated the seafaring Veneti in 56 B.C. by fashioning hooks to long poles during Caesar’s Gallic campaigns?",
    "answer": "DECIMUS BRUTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what town was Decimus Brutus almost besieged and defeated by Marc Antony in 43 B.C.?",
    "answer": "MUTINA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "At what village in northern Italy had Marc Antony’s army been attacked by the armies of Hirtius and Pansa, precipitating his failure to capture Mutina?",
    "answer": "FORUM GALLORUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage from Virgil, which I will twice as prose, and answer the questions that follow in Latin: “īte,” ait “ēgregiās animās, quae sanguine nōbīs hanc patriam pepererē suō, decorāte suprēmīs mūneribus, maestamque Evandrī prīmus ad urbem mittātur Pallas, quem nōn virtūtis egentem abstulit atra dies et fūnere mersit acerbō.” The question: Ubī vir nōn virtūtis egens accipiētur?",
    "answer": "IN (MAESTĀ) URBE EVANDRĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quibus eundum est?",
    "answer": "ĒGREGIĪS ANIMĪS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Ā quā Pallas ablātus est?",
    "answer": "ATRĀ DIĒ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which later Roman author, born around 480 A.D and consul in 510 A.D., became magister officiorum in 522 A.D. under Theodoric, but having been charged with treason and imprisoned, wrote De Consolatione Philosophiae?",
    "answer": "(ANICIUS MANLIUS SEVERINUS) BOETHIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The dialogues in the De Consolatione Philosophiae are written in what form, which was inspired by a 3rd century B.C. Cynic writer from Gadara?",
    "answer": "19"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The position of magister officiorum was later filled by Boethius’ kinsman, who was born at Squillace around 490 A.D., and wrote a Chronica from Adam to 519 A.D., a history on the Goths as well as established a monastery at Vivarium. Name this relative.",
    "answer": "(FLAVIUS MAGNUS AURELIUS) CASSIODORUS (SENATOR)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give two synonyms of the Latin deponent verb veneror.",
    "answer": "(AD)ŌRŌ / COLŌ / ADOLEO / VEREOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give two synonyms of the Latin verb exspectō.",
    "answer": "SPĒRŌ / OPPERIOR / PRAESTŌLOR / MANEŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give two synonyms of the Latin verb crīmen.",
    "answer": "FACINUS / SCELUS / DĒDECUS / CULPA / VITIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Hermes and native of Opus was left by Heracles to guard the man-eating mares of Diomedes and was himself eaten?",
    "answer": "ABDERUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Iberian was beloved by Heracles and was said to have been the first to devise a helmet?",
    "answer": "CORYTHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which of the Greek chieftains, described in the Iliad as the second most handsome after Achilles, is also considered to have been a lover of Heracles?",
    "answer": "NIREUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Complete this analogy: polliceor : pollicēmini :: _______ : ēste. (N.B. to moderator: pronounce the long mark on ēste!)",
    "answer": "EDŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give two distinct forms of sum that can be its 1 st person singular imperfect active subjunctive.",
    "answer": "ESSEM & FOREM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The sentence “I hope that we are the winners” can be translated into Latin using a subjunctive rather than an indirect statement. When doing so, what two forms of sum would be present?",
    "answer": "FORE & SIMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What Roman consul, in one of the first battles of the Third Macedonian War, was defeated by Perseus near Larissa in 171 BC?",
    "answer": "(P. LICINIUS) CRASSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What consular successor of Crassus, who shares the name of an ill-fated commander at Numantia 33 years later, similarly failed on the Macedonian front against Perseus?",
    "answer": "(HOSTILIUS) MANCINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What consul, after marching around Mt. Olympus for 11 days, scare Perseus into abandoning his entire frontier line in 169 BC?",
    "answer": "(Q. MARCIUS) PHILIPPUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What which Roman author discusses the analgesic effects of willow bark, the cardinal signs of inflammation, and the surgical removal of cataracts in his eight-book encyclopecia De Medicina?",
    "answer": "(AULUS CORNELIUS) CELSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Celsus’ work originally contained six artes, but only the portion on medicine is extant. Name three of the five other artes Celsus is said to have treated in his encyclopedia.",
    "answer": "AGRICULTURE, MILITARY (ART), PHILOSOPHY, ORATORY, JURISPRUDENCE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Celsus’ encyclopedic approach of the artes takes after the Disciplinarum Libri IX of what earlier Roman author? (Prompt on “Varro”) Replacement Language:",
    "answer": "VARRO OF REATE / (MARCUS TERENTIUS) VARRO REATINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat: harundō?",
    "answer": "REED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat: hirundō?",
    "answer": "SWALLOW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat: hirūdō?",
    "answer": "LEECH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What derivative of a Latin word meaning “mutilated” means “to reduce in extent or quantity or impose a restriction on”?",
    "answer": "CURTAIL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What derivative of the same word is “a woman's gown or outer petticoat”?",
    "answer": "KIRTLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin word with what meaning do we derive “curb”? Replacement Mythology:",
    "answer": "CURVUS – CURVED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Book 5 of Vergil’s Aeneid, what old Sicilian mandefeats Dares to win the boxing match at the funeral games of Anchises?",
    "answer": "ENTELLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Before the fight, Entellus forgoes using the gloves of what man?",
    "answer": "ERYX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "During the archery contest, what brother of Pandarus successfully shot the dove, only to be shown-up by Acestes, whose arrow burst into flames? Replacement History:",
    "answer": "EURYTION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Gaius Cassius Longinus, Asinius Pollio, Valens, Stilicho, and Aetius all had what in common?",
    "answer": "THEY SHARED THE TITLE “LAST OF THE ROMANS”"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name all three “Founders of Rome.”",
    "answer": "ROMULUS, CAMILLUS, MARIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Name all three winners of the spolia opima, and the man whom Augustus refused to award it to. Replacement Literature:",
    "answer": "ROMULUS, COSSUS, MARCELLUS; CRASSUS THE YOUNGER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What epic poem, the most successful of Prudentius’s works, describes duels between Faith and Idolatry, Chastity and Lust, and Patience and Anger?",
    "answer": "PSYCHOMACHIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What other work of Prudentius is a series of hymns that honor Christian martyrs?",
    "answer": "PERISTEPHANON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In his Contra Symmachum, Prudentius takes the side of what man in the dispute over the Altar of Victory?",
    "answer": "FINAL ROUND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Possibly exclaimed during a consular election, translate into Latin: I’m sick and tired of hearing about your wretched letters!",
    "answer": "MĒ AUDIENDĪ DĒ TUĪS MISERĪS EPISTULĪS PIGET TAEDETQUE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a genitive, translate into Latin: Though he was a merciful god, nevertheless he condemned the treacherous nymph to death.",
    "answer": "TAMEN INFIDĒLEM NYMPHĒN CAPITIS DAMNĀVIT (DAMNĀBAT)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a genitive, translate into Latin: The ants marched eight by eight into the river of honey to more easily find food.",
    "answer": "QUŌ FACILIUS CIBUM INVENĪRENT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Claiming to be the son of Caligula, which Praetorian Prefect convinced the Praetorian Guard to betray Nero and later attempted to usurp the throne from Galba?",
    "answer": "NYMPHIDIUS SABINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whom did Nymphidius Sabinus succeed as Praetorian Prefect in 65 AD as a result of his implication in the Pisonian Conspiracy?",
    "answer": "FAENIUS RUFUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After Nero’s death, Sabinus forced the resignation of Tigellinus. Whom did Galba appoint to replace Tigellinus, causing Sabinus unease?",
    "answer": "CORNELIUS LACO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Though the words “illicit,” “solicit,” and “complicit” seem similar, they are derived from three different Latin words. Give the Latin words and their meanings from which each is derived, respectively.",
    "answer": "COMPLICIT, FROM PLECTŌ – TO PLAIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "A word often confused with “illicit” is “elicit,” which is derived from yet another Latin word. Give that Latin noun and its meaning.",
    "answer": "DĒLICIAE – SWEETHEART"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What derivative of dēliciae, would not describe Certamen players, since it means “a person having a superficial interest in an art or a branch of knowledge”?",
    "answer": "DILETTANTE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What son of Minos and Pasiphae was warned by an oracle that one of his children would kill him so he sold two of his children to Nauplius?",
    "answer": "CATREUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which daughter of Catreus was impregnated by Hermes after she slipped and fell on fresh hides while running away from him?",
    "answer": "APEMOSYNE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which brother of Apemosyne, not believing that she had been raped by Hermes, kicked her to death?",
    "answer": "22"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which Roman author studied under the rhetorician Papirius Fabianus, went to Egypt in 26 A.D. in the entourage of his uncle, and discusses the detachment of the sage from worldly concerns in the essays of the Dialogi?",
    "answer": "SENECA THE YOUNGER / LUCIUS ANNAEUS SENECA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To whom, a prefect in charge of the distribution of the food supply and possibly a relative of Seneca’s wife, does Seneca dedicate De Brevitate Vitae?",
    "answer": "PAULINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which seven-book work of Seneca, addressed to Aebutius Liberalis, discusses philanthropy and its maintenance of social harmony?",
    "answer": "DE BENIFICIIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give an antonym of prīdem.",
    "answer": "NŪPER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give an antonym of diū.",
    "answer": "PAULISPER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give an antonym of repentē.",
    "answer": "PAULĀTIM"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Claudius Gothicus, Aurelian, Probus, and Valens are just a few of the many emperors born in what Roman province, heavily populated by troops defending the Danube?",
    "answer": "PANNONIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "From what neighboring region divided into two provinces did the likes of Constantine, Licinius, and Jovian hail?",
    "answer": "MOESIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Until the reign of Trajan, only one emperor was born outside of Italy. Name this emperor.",
    "answer": "CLAUDIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which Greek chieftain at Troy, a son of Peteüs, was second only to Nestor in marshalling chariots and foot soldiers and led 50 ships from Athens?",
    "answer": "MENESTHEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two sons of Ares and Astyoche led 30 ships from Orchomenus to Troy?",
    "answer": "ASCALAPHUS AND IALMENUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Heracles and Astyoche led 9 ships from Rhodes to Troy?",
    "answer": "TLEPOLEMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "In Latin, an object eliciting emotion is normally the object of propter or ob, while the motive influencing the mind of the person acting is found in what case with what use?",
    "answer": "ABLATIVE OF CAUSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate and identify the uses of the ablative found in this sentence: Aliīs āmissīs, spē nītī malumus.",
    "answer": "ABSOLUTE & WITH SPECIAL VERBS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate and identify the uses of the accusative found in this sentence: Laesus crūra et honōre, gladiātor spem sōlam habuit.",
    "answer": "23"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "A native of Gaza in Palestine, what author was considered the first significant Christian poet and wrote a history of the Old Testament and Rome coming down to the destruction of the Roman Empire, the Apocalypse, and the Last Judgment entitled Carmen Apologeticum?",
    "answer": "COMMODIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What lawyer was born at Cirta and wrote a work entitled Octavius, which refuted the attacks on Christianity by Fronto?",
    "answer": "MINUCIUS FELIX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What teacher of rhetoric, born in Sicca Veneria in Africa, was the teacher of Lactantius and wrote a work in 7 books entitled Adversus Nationes whose chief mission was the show the error of Neoplatonism?",
    "answer": "ARNOBIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What aedile published a legal manual of phrases and forms of procedure and posted a calendar in the forum of dies fasti and nefasti in 304 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(GNAEUS) FLAVIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to two contradicting tradition, Flavius either stole the manuscript from or worked together to compose it with what nobleman and ex-censor?",
    "answer": "APPIUS CLAUDIUS CAECUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In another plebeian victory, what law, passed after 293 B.C., extended the legislation of the Lex Publilia of 339 B.C. to elections, requiring the auctoritas partum to precede electoral operations?",
    "answer": "LEX MAENIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage from Propertius, which I will read twice as prose, and answer the questions that follow in English: ō ūtīnam hībernae dūplicentur tempōra brūmae, et sit iners tardīs nāvita Vergiliīs, nec tibi Tyrrhēna solvātur fūnis harēna, nēve inimīca meās ēlevet aura precēs et mē dēfixum vacuā patiātur in orā crūdēlem infestā saepe vōcāre manū! The question: With what does the author supposedly threaten his lover?",
    "answer": "WITH HIS DANGEROUS HANDS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What time of the year does the poet wish were longer?",
    "answer": "WINTER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What does the poet hope will not happen to his prayers?",
    "answer": "THAT THEY BE BLOWN AWAY BY HOSTILE BREEZES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, whom Aelius Verus calls his Vergil, wrote a moving poem about the death of the 6-year old slave girl Erotion and numerous short, witty poems expressing adulation for patrons and the emperor Domitian?",
    "answer": "(MARCUS VALERIUS) MARTIAL(IS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Name an author whom Martial calls one of his auctores.",
    "answer": "LENTULUS GAETULICUS / DOMITIUS MARSUS / ALBINOVANUS PEDO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name another.",
    "answer": "24"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Lycurgus wore only a bearskin and brought only an axe on the voyage of the Argonauts when his grandfather hid his armor, but was still chosen to row beside Heracles due to his youthful strength?",
    "answer": "ANCAEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was this doting grandfather of Ancaeus?",
    "answer": "ALEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "By what animal was this Ancaeus killed?",
    "answer": "BOAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Book 2 of Virgil’s Aeneid, Creusa speaks the following lines: quid tantum insanō iuvat indulgēre dolorī, o dulcis coniunx? non haec sine numine divum ēveniunt; nec te comitem hinc portāre Creusam fas, aut ille sinit superī regnator Olympi. This is the source of the phrase “nil sine numine” found on the seal of what state?",
    "answer": "COLORADO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Oklahoma also draws inspiration from Virgil for its motto, which is found in lines 145-146 of what work and book number of another of Virgil’s works?",
    "answer": "GEORGICS, BOOK 1"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Many other states draw inspiration from Cicero. Which state’s motto is based on a quote by Caecilius Statius in Cicero’s De Senectute?",
    "answer": "NORTH DAKOTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In retaliation for attacks on Cornelius Gallus around the First Cataract of the Nile, what prefect of Egypt led a punitive expedition as far as Nabata against the Queen of Ethiopia circa 25 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) PETRONIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "By what title was the Queen of Ethiopia known to the Romans?",
    "answer": "CANDACE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In 22 B.C., where did Ethiopian envoys meet Augustus to negotiate Rome’s border along the Nile?",
    "answer": "SAMOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "When Ovid wrote the Fasti, he referred to the Fasti Praenestini of what author, who was the tutor of Lucius and Gaius Caesar and the greatest grammarian of the Augustan Age?",
    "answer": "VERRIUS FLACCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was the title of Verrius Flaccus’ work about difficult or obsolete terms?",
    "answer": "DE VERBORUM SIGNIFICATU"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Although the original text of the De Verborum Significatu has been lost, we possess an abridgement produced by what grammarian of the second and third Centuries?",
    "answer": "(SEXTUS POMPEIUS) FESTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the person, number, tense, voice, and mood for the verb form commorās. nd PERSON SG. PLUP. ACT. INDICATIVE",
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Giving person, number, tense, voice, and mood where applicable, what forms of the same verb could monēre be?",
    "answer": "PRES. ACT. INFINITIVE & PRES. PASS. IMPERATIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the 2nd person plural future active imperative of that verb.",
    "answer": "MONĒTŌTE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Euaemon led forty ships to Troy, where he cast his lot to duel Hector but was not chosen, and later received a chest abandoned by Aeneas, which drove him to madness?",
    "answer": "EURYPYLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To cure his madness, the Delphic Oracle directed him to Patrae, then being forced to atone for the actions of what couple, who slept together in a shrine?",
    "answer": "MELANNIPUS & COMAETHO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Eurypylus cured his madness and became king by propitiating the Patraeans with an image of what god, which he had found within his chest?",
    "answer": "DIONYSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Dīcitur comitia trēs hōrās dīlāta esse dum lex ferrī posset.",
    "answer": "UNTIL THE LAW SHOULD BE ABLE TO BE PASSED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Rōmae fuērunt quoad Metellus in prōvinciam prōfectus est.",
    "answer": "THEY WERE AT ROME UNTIL METELLUS SET OUT FOR THE PROVINCE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Haec non rectē identitem fēcī dōnec mē ēmendāvistī. Replacement Language:",
    "answer": "UNTIL YOU CORRECTED ME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin verb takes the accusative when it means to “foresee” and takes the dative when it means “to make provisions for”?",
    "answer": "PRŌVIDEŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin verb takes the accusative when it means to “ask advice of” and takes the dative when it means “to pay attention to”?",
    "answer": "CONSULŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin compound of faciō has two objects, one in the dative and the other in the accusative?",
    "answer": "PRAEFICIŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For a second conjugation verb meaning “to betroth,” give the 3rd person singular pluperfect active subjunctive.",
    "answer": "SPOPONDISSET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For a second conjugation verb meaning “to bite,” give the same form.",
    "answer": "MOMORDISSET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Keeping all else the same, provide turn both spopondisset and momordisset to the passive. Replacement Mythology:",
    "answer": "SPONSUS ESSET; MORSUS ESSET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Also called Dictynna, what Cretan goddess, a daughter of Zeus and Carme, was pursued by Minos and attempted to leap into the sea, but was caught in the net of a fisherman?",
    "answer": "BRITOMARTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What does the name “Dictynna” mean?",
    "answer": "LADY OF THE NETS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Britomartis was worshipped on the island of Aegina under what name? Replacement History:",
    "answer": "APHAEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What barracks emperor was recognized by the senate but defeated in battle by Aemilianus in 253 A.D.?",
    "answer": "TREBONIANUS GALLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where had Aemilianus defeated Trebonianus Gallus to gain the throne?",
    "answer": "INTERAMNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Gallus officially ruled with him as co-Augustus? Replacement Literature:",
    "answer": "26"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which author, chosen bishop in 248 A.D., survived one persecution, but not the other leading to his eventual death September 14th 258 A.D.?",
    "answer": "(THASCIUS CAECILIUS) CYPRIAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of Cyprian's works details his own conversion and the corruption of the Roman government?",
    "answer": "AD DONATUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In which of his works does Cyprian speak of unifying the Catholic Church?",
    "answer": "DE ECCLESIASTE UNITATE CATHOLICA / DE ECCLESIAE CATHOLICAE UNITATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into English: Pȳthia dīxit sē fāta nēscīre sed orācūlis crēdere?",
    "answer": "FATE/DESTINY BUT BELIEVED THE ORACLES."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now try this one: Puella vult scīre num heroa ventūrum esset.",
    "answer": "THE GIRL WANTS TO KNOW WHETHER THE HERO WILL RETURN."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now try this one: Spēramus nōs victurōs esse, sed sōla Pȳthia scit.",
    "answer": "I HOPE THAT WE WILL WIN, BUT ONLY THE PYTHIA/ORACLE KNOWS."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What sisters had many defining features, such as huge boar-like tusks, hands of bronze, gold wings, and heads entwined with snakes?",
    "answer": "THE GORGONS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was given two vials of Gorgon blood by Athena for use in healing?",
    "answer": "ASCLEPIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Athena also gave two drops of Gorgon blood to what Athenian king?",
    "answer": "ERICHTHONIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What novus homo, born in Tusculum in 234 BC, distinguished his political life with his distaste for everything Greek, solidified his literary reputation with historical and agricultural prowess, and immortalized his name with the phrase Ceterum, censeo Carthaginem esse delendam, which is popularly abridged to Carthago delenda est!",
    "answer": "CATO THE ELDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was Cato’s full name?",
    "answer": "MARCUS PORCIUS CATO MAIOR/CENSOR(IUS)/SAPIENS/PRISCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Cato’s De Agri Cultura prominently features what vegetable, which is the modern genus of cabbage, broccoli, cauliflower, choy sum, rutabaga, turnips, mustard, and wild mustard?",
    "answer": "BRASSICA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin noun with what meaning do we derive “jaunty,” “genie,” and, “genteel”?",
    "answer": "GENUS—KIND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin noun with what meaning do we derive “frond”?",
    "answer": "FRONS—LEAF"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin noun with what meaning do we derive “lettuce”?",
    "answer": "LAC—MILK"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What kind of conditional is found in the following sentence: Sī nōn tam temerē ēgisset, vicissēmus.",
    "answer": "PAST CONTRARY TO FACT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate that sentence.",
    "answer": "IF HE HAD NOT ACTED SO RASHLY, WE WOULD HAVE WON."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now, translate this one: Cum improbus puer adsit, talia fiunt.",
    "answer": "SUCH THINGS HAPPEN WHEN A WICKED BOY IS PRESENT."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What province, first invaded by Caesar, was Agricola the governor of from 77 to 85 CE?",
    "answer": "BRITTANIA/BRITAIN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Agricola's first act as governor was to defeat the Ordovices and thereby complete the conquest of Wales. What predecessor of Agricola began the conquest of Wales?",
    "answer": "FRONTINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What emperor recalled Agricola in 85 allegedly because he was jealous of Agricola's successes?",
    "answer": "DOMITIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "We all know our chickpea-faced pal, Cicero. We all know that Cicero’s full 3-word name is Marcus Tullius Cicero. The cognomen, Cicero, is derived from cicer, referring to what type vegetable? CHICKPEA (or GARBANZO BEAN)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Plutarch informs us that he was called this because one of his ancestors had a cleft lip and/or grew chickpeas as a profession. Sadly Cicero, Illinois does not grow chickpeas. However, the town of Cicero does encompass the Corey Steel Company in its jurisdiction. With that in mind, in which specific speech of Cicero, does Cicero ask his opponent Catiline if there was not one Roman youth to whom he “has not handed out steel for audacious crime?”",
    "answer": "IN CATILINAM I"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On what day was this speech given?",
    "answer": "NOVEMBER 8"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who, according to early Roman accounts, consented to marry the Libyan king Iarbas but secretly ordered a funeral pyre to be built and killed herself upon it?",
    "answer": "DIDO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Dido’s first husband was Sychaeus, who was also related to her in what way?",
    "answer": "HE WAS HER UNCLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Vergil’s Aeneid, what action of Iarbas causes Jupiter to have Mercury urge Aeneas to leave Dido?",
    "answer": "HE PRAYS TO (HIS FATHER) JUPITER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In boarding schools, students are often provided for by the school staff due to the students’ distance from home. What Latin phrase describes the legal responsibility bestowed upon these schools to act on behalf of parents?",
    "answer": "IN LOCO PARENTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What similar Latin phrase meaning “parent of the country” describes the power of the state to intervene to protect children, under circumstances of abuse or negligence of the child?",
    "answer": "PARENS PATRIAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin phrase, literally meaning “holding the place” describes one temporarily fulfilling the duties of another, such as a substitute teacher?",
    "answer": "LOCUM TENENS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What emperor was appointed by the Senate in 96 CE, promised to never execute a Senator without a trial, but nevertheless failed to control the army?",
    "answer": "NERVA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whom did Nerva indifferently exile early in his reign for conspiring for the throne?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) CALPURNIUS CRASSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Praetorian Prefect induced the guards to lay siege to Nerva’s palace to execute Petronius Secundus, the lead conspirator against Domitian?",
    "answer": "CASPERIUS AELIANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Complete this analogy: facerēs is to facis as ______ is to vīs.",
    "answer": "VELLĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Complete this analogy: volō is to velle as patior is to ______.",
    "answer": "PATĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Complete this analogy: tollō is to sustulī as afferō is to ______.",
    "answer": "ATTULĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What young relative of Odysseus pretended to have earned the enmity of Odysseus by speaking out against his treacherous murder of Palamedes, and thus won the Trojans’ trust?",
    "answer": "SINON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Aeneas remarks that Sinon’s cunning and false tears had overcome the men who had not been subdued what two much stronger Greek warriors? ACHILLES and DIOMEDES",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Aeneas’ recounts later in his story that whose mighty trunk lay on the shores of Pergamum, a headless corpse without a name?",
    "answer": "PRIAM’S"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What battle of the early Roman Republic was commemorated by a parade of horses and a temple to Castor and Pollux, despite the fact that it was a draw between Rome and the Latin League in 496 BC?",
    "answer": "BATTLE OF LAKE REGILLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "This battle was sparked because Rome signed a treaty with what city in 509 BCE that indicated Rome controlled Latium?",
    "answer": "CARTHAGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What early Plebeian leader negotiated the treaty that followed this battle so skillfully that Rome gained equal status to the Latin League?",
    "answer": "4"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin word can mean “hero,” “husband,” or “man”?",
    "answer": "VIR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What less common definition of the Latin word amīcus is a derivative of the Latin verb discō?",
    "answer": "DISCIPLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What less common definition of the Latin word exuviae is a future active imperative?",
    "answer": "MEMENTO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Identify the correct form of the word “ribbon” if the following English sentence were to be translated into Latin: The girls understood that on Saturnalia, their hair should be fastened with ribbons.",
    "answer": "VITTĪS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Vittae, since they relate to the human body, can often also be found with a passive verb and what type of accusative?",
    "answer": "SYNECHDOCHICAL/RESPECT/SPECIFICATION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin word meaning “thigh” notably takes this accusative in a dramatic scene in Book V of Caesar’s De Bello Gallico?",
    "answer": "FĒMUR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What office was made sacrosanct after the second secession of the Plebeians in 449 BCE?",
    "answer": "TRIBUNE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What did it mean in ancient Roman for a group of people to be sacrosanct?",
    "answer": "ARMS COULD NOT BE USED AGAINST THEM WITHIN THE CITY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Plebeian-favoring consuls of 449 BCE passed the legislation that enacted this?",
    "answer": "VALERIUS POTITUS AND HORATIUS BARBATUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whose physical features—that is, his uncut hairs, fiery eyes, and dirty mantle—complement the ferruginea cumba by which he would convey passengers to the Underworld?",
    "answer": "CHARON’S"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two primordial deities were the parents of Charon?",
    "answer": "EREBUS AND NYX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Across what two rivers did Charon bring his passengers?",
    "answer": "ACHERON AND STYX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Achilles, Aegisthus, Ajax Mastigophorus, Andromeda, Danae, Equus Troianus, Hermiona, and Tereus are all plays written by what author, the father of Latin literature?",
    "answer": "LIVIUS ANDRONICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What two plays from those listed in the toss up share their name with plays written by Gnaeus Naevius?",
    "answer": "DANAE, EQUUS TROIANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What work in Saturnian Meter is Andronicus’s magnum opus?",
    "answer": "5"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage, which I will read twice, and answer in Latin the questions that follow: Eheu, amice! Hesterna gaudia brevī tempōre mē ē negotiō rapuerunt. Hesterna gaudia meam errābundam mentem quae dē morte uxoris Quintiliae lacrimat edūxērunt. Hesterna gaudia meum calamum, perfixum in meīs carminibus, in mensam depulerunt, dum levitāte cerae cum tē ludēbam. The question: Quis in mensam dēpulsus est?",
    "answer": "(MEUS) CALAMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quam diū hesterna gaudia narratorem rapuerunt?",
    "answer": "BREVĪ TEMPŌRE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Qualem mentem hesterna gaudia edūxērunt?",
    "answer": "ERRĀBUNDAM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who am I? I’m popularly considered the father of Church song, I was elected to be bishop of Milan without having been baptized, and I wrote a lot of treatises on virgins, widows, and Christian faith?",
    "answer": "SAINT AMBROSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "My De Officiis Ministrorum draws heavily in style and purpose from the De Officiis of what earlier author?",
    "answer": "CICERO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "While I was the father of Church song, what other author invented the Latin hymn?",
    "answer": "ROUND II"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Pothinus and Achillas were ordered by Ptolemy to kill what man that stumbled on to the shores of Egypt after losing the battle of Pharsalus?",
    "answer": "POMPEY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What general’s second and third lines of defense armed with stabbing spears won the day against Pompey’s larger army at Pharsalus?",
    "answer": "CAESAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What famous two-word Latin phrase did Caesar utter after this battle?",
    "answer": "HOC VOLUERUNT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which two of the six English words are derived from the same Latin root: apprehension, adhesion, malady, movable, ditty?",
    "answer": "MALADY & MOVABLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which two of the six English words are derived from the same Latin root: donate, decision, season, traitor, silhouette, series?",
    "answer": "DONATE & TRAITOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which two of the six English words are derived from the same Latin root: innocent, ennui, otiose, malice, odoriferous, odious?",
    "answer": "ENNUI & ODIOUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was killed either because he was married when he should have been celibate, because he made love before a sanctuary of Apollo, or because he struck a wooden object that was sacred to Neptune?",
    "answer": "LAOCOÖN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Some accounts, like the one by Quintus Smyrnaeus, state that Laocoön met his downfall not because he struck the Trojan Horse, but because he wanted the Trojans to do what with it?",
    "answer": "BURN IT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Aeneas is told by his mother that which deity sent the serpents to kill Laocoön?",
    "answer": "MINERVA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Though originally used for the dative of purpose, the ending -ū became the ablative ending of what verbal abstract of the fourth declension that is commonly introduced by fās, nefās, and opus?",
    "answer": "SUPINE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Opus est is an impersonal verb that introduces what type of subjunctive?",
    "answer": "RESULT CLAUSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Many impersonal verbs often introduce what type of infinitive, such as the one in the sentence “Licetne mihi ad latrīnam īre?”",
    "answer": "SUBJECTIVE INFINITIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author neglected to mention his puella for the first 55 lines of his first poem, even mentioning his patron Messalla before his lover, Delia, in his elegiac tribute to rusticity?",
    "answer": "TIBULLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Tibullus’s mistress was named Delia in his poems. According to Apuleius, what is Delia’s real name?",
    "answer": "PLANIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In his elegies, Tibullus also mentions having relations with a puer delicatus – a term referring to a young boy bought for the sexual satisfaction of his master. The 12-year-old boy toy featured in Tibullus’s work is known by what name?",
    "answer": "MARATHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two Titans did not participate in the Titanomachy, and thus continued their original functions under the rule of Zeus? OCEANUS and HELIUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Oceanus’ wife Tethys and what other Titaness were particularly revered by the Olympians?",
    "answer": "THEMIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Themis was an earth-goddess, as was what other Titaness?",
    "answer": "RHEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage, which I will read twice, and answer the questions that following in Latin: Nulla est enim natio, quam pertimescamus, nullus rex, qui bellum populo Romano facere possit. Omnia sunt externa unius virtute terra marique pacata; domesticum bellum manet, intus insidiae sunt, intus inclusum periculum est, intus est hostis. The question: Quis terram mareque domuit? VIRTUS UNIUS or UNUS (VIR)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quale est periculum?",
    "answer": "(INTUS) INCLUSUM (EST)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quis ab bellis regum nunc liberantur?",
    "answer": "ROMANUS (POPULUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was declared a usurper in 308 AD at the Conference of Carnuntum by Diocletian, Galerius, and his father Maximian?",
    "answer": "MAXENTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who, the Caesar of the West appointed by Diocletian just before his retirement, did Maxentius initially usurp?",
    "answer": "SEVERUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "While Maxentius was trying to one-by-one defeat members of the tetrarchy, what future emperor was training the army of his father Constantius Chlorus in Britain for battle?",
    "answer": "8"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "According to the Lexicon Rēcentis Latinitātis what in modern times would be called an aleātorium?",
    "answer": "CASINO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What famous structure would be called Aedes Alba?",
    "answer": "WHITE HOUSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What event in certain sports would be called retis violatio?",
    "answer": "A GOAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "SpongeBob is often punctuated by insipid, yet eloquent, comments. What author employed a similar style to his prodigious pile of papyrus scrolls, totaling some 12,200 lines of Latin that are deemed collectively as the worst poem of all Latin literature?",
    "answer": "SILIUS ITALICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Other authors are known for writing a lot of rubbish. One of these trash writers, Volusius, is viciously attacked by what eloquent author who deems Volusius’ works as cacata carta?",
    "answer": "CATULLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Some writers wrote intentionally simplistic and trite books. What author was commissioned by the emperor Valens to compose one such simplistic work, the Breviarium Ab Urbe Condita, an abridgement of Livy’s history of Rome?",
    "answer": "EUTROPIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What king of Pontus send his general Archelaus to Greece in 88 BCE to fight Sulla besieging Athens?",
    "answer": "MITHRIDATES VI (THE GREAT)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "At what battle in 86 BCE did scythe chariots not help Archelaus in defeating Sulla?",
    "answer": "CHAERONEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "At what battle in 86 BCE did Sulla build trenches and drive Archelaus’s chariots back into his phalanx?",
    "answer": "ORCHOMENUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin phrase, a precept that must be applied intelligently, advises us to generalize from one example?",
    "answer": "AB ŪNŌ DISCE OMNĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin phrase cautions us that it is easy to fall, but once fallen, difficult to make one’s way back up?",
    "answer": "FACILE DĒSCENSUS AVERNŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin phrase attributed to Suetonius describes the oxymoronic yet necessary balance between caution and action?",
    "answer": "FESTĪNĀ LENTE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who, perhaps in league with the demagogue Menestheus, because he privately feared that the famous king might induce the Scyrians to offer him their country, treacherously murdered Theseus by pushing him off a cliff?",
    "answer": "LYCOMEDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Theseus had gone to Scyrus because he inherited estates there from what grandfather of his?",
    "answer": "SCYRIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to other accounts, Theseus had been carried off by storms and forced to land at Scyrus while sailing to what island ruled by his brother-in-law Deucalion?",
    "answer": "CRETE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What two prominent authors, one a prominent 2nd century tragedian, the other an epic Roman poet, both died in a similar manner: on a voyage to Greece?",
    "answer": "TERENCE AND VERGIL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Under what man did Terence supposedly come as a slave to Rome?",
    "answer": "TERENTIUS LUCANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Terence and Vergil, along with Horace and Lucan, are all prominently featured in the De Poetis chapter of what major work by Suetonius?",
    "answer": "DE VIRIS ILLUSTRIBUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Identify a declinable Latin word that has the same form in only the accusative and ablative cases.",
    "answer": "EGŌ/TŪ/SUI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Identify a declinable Latin word that has the same form in the nominative and ablative singular.",
    "answer": "GENŪ/GELŪ/CORNŪ/VERŪ/PECŪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Identify the Latin monoptote that describes a time of day.",
    "answer": "MANĒ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whose younger brother Promachus and father would meet their deaths in a gruesome fashion, the first through plotted murder, and the second by drinking bull’s blood, all because of the enmity of Pelias?",
    "answer": "JASON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What did Jason’s mother do upon hearing witnessing these injustices?",
    "answer": "SHE KILLED HERSELF WITH A SWORD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Upon hearing what rumor had Pelias dared to murder Jason’s father and younger brother?",
    "answer": "THE SHIP HAD GONE DOWN WITH ALL ITS CREW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Roman general, although more famous for his son Pompey Magnus, is credited with ending the Social War by taking the Italian strongholds at Corfinium and Asculum?",
    "answer": "POMPEIUS STRABO"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What two political enemies of 63 BCE served together under Strabo in the Social War?",
    "answer": "CICERO AND CATILINE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "In what year immediately following the social war did Strabo serve as consul with Sulla?",
    "answer": "10"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into English: Quāre esse amīcī nēquimus?",
    "answer": "WHY CAN’T WE BE FRIENDS?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now try this one: Ūtīnam mea amīca esse vēlit!",
    "answer": "IF ONLY SHE WOULD WISH TO BE MY FRIEND!"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now try this one: Eheu! Sunt quī esse me bonī amicī non cupiant.",
    "answer": "ALAS, THERE ARE THOSE WHO DO NOT WISH TO BE MY GOOD FRIENDS!"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Greek writer serves as the obvious influence for Vergil when he was writing the Aeneid?",
    "answer": "HOMER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Greek writer serves as the obvious influence for Vergil when he was writing the Eclogues?",
    "answer": "THEOCRITUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Greek writer serves as the obvious influence for Vergil when he was writing the Georgics?",
    "answer": "HESIOD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into Latin: The moderators did not know where they were going.",
    "answer": "MODERĀTŌRĒS NĒSCĪVĒRUNT QUŌ ĪRENT."
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into Latin: The moderators whom we choose might also be teachers.",
    "answer": "MODERĀTORĒS, QUŌS LEGIMUS, MAGISTRĪ SINT."
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into Latin: The moderators must be lauded by us for their efforts.",
    "answer": "ROUND III"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Hyginus, who was less faithful at her daughter’s death than anger at Oeax’s advance report that his daughter was bringing home Priam’s daughter Cassandra as a concubine?",
    "answer": "CLYTEMNESTRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "It is for this reason that Hyginus remarks that Oeax thus avenged what unjust action of Agamemnon?",
    "answer": "AGAMEMNON’S CONDEMNATION OF (HIS BROTHER) PALAMEDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Though she bore such great resentment towards him for his role in their daughter’s death, Clytemnestra seemed to have had no such hatred for Agamemnon when he violently killed what man, her first husband?",
    "answer": "TANTALUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Descendant of Messapus and self-proclaimed Homer of Latin, what author glorified lavish eating, introduced an early and rough version of hexameter to Latin literature, and was a follower of Euhemerus, according to Cicero?",
    "answer": "ENNIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Fulvius Nobilior took Ennius with him on his military campaign to Ambracia, what former patron of Ennius was like “oh no you didn’t?”",
    "answer": "CATO THE ELDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work of Ennius technically began the tradition of Roman satire, although official credit for beginning the genre is given to a later author? SOTA (or SATURAE)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence from Latin into English: Cornelius ab amplissimo senātōre portāre aquam usque ad flumen Tiberim iussus est.",
    "answer": "SENATOR TO CARRY WATER ALL THE WAY TO THE TIBER RIVER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence from Latin into English: Non est dubium quin nemo sciat cūr Cornēlius tam pavidus sit.",
    "answer": "KNOWS WHY CORNELIUS IS SO AFRAID."
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence from English into Latin: Cornelius is afraid because he thinks that he will fall into the Tiber River.",
    "answer": "SĒ CASŪRUM ESSE IN FLŪMEN TIBERIM PUTAT."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whose apparent willingness to provide information to his captors may have been due in part to disgruntlement over the fact that his brother Deiphobus had won their quarrel over the right to marry Helen after Paris’ death?",
    "answer": "12"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After the fall of Troy, Helenus traveled with Neoptolemus, and provided him with what useful piece of advice?",
    "answer": "TO RETURN HOME BY LAND (AND NOT SEA)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where did Neoptolemus and Helenus settle upon leaving Troy?",
    "answer": "EPEIRUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Used when describing Aeneas and Rumor in the Aeneid, what third conjugation Latin verb can mean “to hide” or to “sheath one’s sword” though it also has the more common meaning “to found”?",
    "answer": "CONDŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Another such verb with a less common meaning is claudō. Beside “to close,” what else can claudō mean?",
    "answer": "TO LIMP, STUMBLE, FALTER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The adverb multō means “by much” and is a common ablative of degree of difference. What, however, does the verb multō mean? TO PUNISH",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Fans of the HBO series, Game of Thrones, are curious to find out if Danaerys Targaryen and Jon Snow will finally cross paths in the upcoming season. While a potential relationship between the mother of dragons and her nephew should seem weird to most, Roman historians know to think otherwise. What Roman Emperor, imitating the way of the Pharaohs, pursued intimate relationships with his sisters, being especially fond of Drusilla?",
    "answer": "(GNAEUS CORNELIUS) LENTULUS GAETULICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, “the great protégé of Aurunca” drove his steeds of satire to pen 30 poems of satire, thus establishing the genre with which Ennius had flirted?",
    "answer": "LUCILIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two contemporary tragedians were lumped in Lucilius’s laundry list of lampooneries? ACCIUS and PACUVIUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was Lucilius’s mistress?",
    "answer": "COLLYRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the subjunctive is found in the following sentence: Timet nē mox mendax esse ducātur. FEARING",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the subjunctive is found in this sentence: Dīcō eī hominem quī semel mendax esset semper mendācem esse cogitum īrī.",
    "answer": "RELATIVE CLAUSE OF CHARACTERISTIC"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What use of the subjunctive is found in this sentence: Tam stultus est ut verō mea verba non crēdat. RESULT",
    "answer": "13"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Defeats near Cyzicus and Nicaea preceded what Emperor’s final defeat at Issus in 194 AD?",
    "answer": "HIS NECK (IT WAS BLACK)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author in his quotation “possunt quia posse videntur” tells that that the appearance of power bestows power itself?",
    "answer": "VIRGIL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author ominously writes “post equitem sedet atra cūra,” telling us that nobody is free of anxiety?",
    "answer": "HORACE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author calls to attention the irreversible results of time in his quotation “tempus, edax rērum”?",
    "answer": "OVID"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "It was no doubt that the presence of what sexual force enabled Erebus and Nyx, fellow offspring of Chaos, to unite and bring forth the beings Aether and Hemera?",
    "answer": "EROS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Around this time, Ge also singlehandedly produced three offspring. Name them.",
    "answer": "URANUS, PONTUS, OUREA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Later Greek accounts denoted Eros not as an offspring of Chaos but rather as the youthful son of Aphrodite. The poet Olen, however, claimed that what deity was the mother of Eros?",
    "answer": "EILEITHYIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the dative is found in the following sentence: Quamquam non credendum est, gladatōri se grātificarī putant?",
    "answer": "SPECIAL VERBS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What use of the accusative is often used loosely by authors as in this sentence from Horace: Huic errōri simile errōrem insanīre?",
    "answer": "COGNATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What use of the dative, used by poets, is found in the following sentence: Placitōne etiam pugnābis amōrī?",
    "answer": "WITH VERBS OF CONTENDING"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What capable military commander was known as the, “the last of the Romans”, for his victory at the Catalaunian Plains?",
    "answer": "PETRONIUS MAXIMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "His ears beaten with texts of archaic Latin and body beaten by Orbilius, what author hopped onto the literary scene around 41 BC with the Epodes, where he declared that he possessed the spirit of Archilochus?",
    "answer": "HORACE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Hailing from the border between Apulia and Lucania, Horace was born in the same city as the famous 16th century, Italian botanist, Bartolomeo Maranta. What was the name of the Roman city?",
    "answer": "VENUSIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "In what Latin work does Horace write est brevitate opus, ut currat sentential neu se inpediat verbis lassas onerantibus aures, et sermone opus est modo tristi, saepe iocoso, defendente vicem modo rhetoris atque poetae, interdum urbani, parcentis viribus atque extenuantis eas consulto?",
    "answer": "SERMONES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to following passage, which I will read twice, and answer in English the question that follows: Sōllemne est mihi, dōmine, omnia dē quibus dubitō ad tē rēferre. Quis enim potest melius vel cunctātiōnem meam regere vel ignorantium instruere? Cognitiōnibus dē Christianīs interfuī numquam: ideō nesciō quid et quātenus aut punīrī soleat aut quaerī. The question: Why doesn’t the speaker know how to punish Christians?",
    "answer": "HE NEVER ATTENDED TRIALS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To whom is it customary that all questions be addressed?",
    "answer": "THE MASTER/RULER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Why does speaker write to the ruler?",
    "answer": "THE RULER IS MOST CAPABLE OF ADDRESSING ISSUES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Before he saw Pallas’ belt vaunting from Turnus’ waist, Achilles would have granted Turnus’ request to die at the house of what man?",
    "answer": "DAUNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What object, bestowed upon him by Vulcan, did Daunus pass on to Turnus?",
    "answer": "AN UNBREAKABLE SWORD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How were Daunus and Perseus related?",
    "answer": "THEY WERE HALF BROTHERS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What English word derived from the Latin word meaning “to bear” means “slow to act” or “tardy”?",
    "answer": "DILATORY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What English word derived from the Latin word meaning “to measure” means “corresponding in size, extent, amount, or degree”?",
    "answer": "COMMENSURATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What English word derived from a Latin word for a type of vehicle means “exaggeration by means of often ludicrous distortion of parts or characteristics”?",
    "answer": "CARICATURE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Satura Tota Nostra Est declares satire to be of wholly Roman origin – a bold, dubiously patriotic assertion for what author to make in Book 10 of his Institutio Oratoria?",
    "answer": "QUINTILIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quintilian served as what satirist’s tutor?",
    "answer": "PERSIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Harvard Lampoon, founded in 1876, is Harvard’s principal satirical magazine. Their motto, Vanitas, both puns Harvard University’s motto, Veritas, and harkens back to the phrase vanitas vanitatum omnia vanitas found in what work by Jerome?",
    "answer": "VULGATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Triumviri Rei Publicae Constituendae Consulari Potestate were legally recognized by what law of 43 BC?",
    "answer": "CONFERENCE OF TARENTUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the difference in meaning between the Latin correlatives vel…vel and aut…aut?",
    "answer": "AUT…AUT STRESSES ONE OR THE OTHER OF TWO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What does the Latin phrase ne…quidem mean?",
    "answer": "NOT EVEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What does the Latin phrase quin etiam mean?",
    "answer": "SEMIFINALS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin term, deemed a necessity to convict many criminal cases, denotes the knowledge and intent of wrongdoing by a guilty party, and literally means “a guilty mind”?",
    "answer": "MENS REA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin legal term denotes that ignorance of the law is not a viable plea of innocence?",
    "answer": "IGNORANTIA LEGIS NEMINEM EXCUSAT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin legal term describes the subjective state of mind of the guilty party?",
    "answer": "ANIMUS NOCENDI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Books XI and XXIV of the Odyssey, what place is described respectively as the place which clean-heeled Achilles marched away from with great strides, and as “the abode of souls whose work is done”? THE FIELDS OF ASPHODEL (prompt on UNDERWORLD)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What semi-legendary place believed to be in the Atlantic was the residence of those who were reincarnated thrice, and judged to be pure enough to be in Elysium all three times?",
    "answer": "FORTUNATE ISLES / ISLES OF THE BLESSED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to accounts after Homer, Achilles did not stay in the Fields of Asphodel, but instead was sent to the Isles of the Blessed, where he married what woman?",
    "answer": "MEDEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author gives credence to the story that Nero started the fire at Rome and depicts Tiberius as harsh and repulsive in his old age as he covers the period from the death of Augustus?",
    "answer": "TACITUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "This work was, of course, Tacitus’ Annales, and was left unfinished due to his untimely death. Which fourth century AD pagan historian continued this work later on?",
    "answer": "AMMIANUS MARCELLINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which work of Tacitus, which utilized an earlier work by Pliny the Elder, is a short geographic-ethnographic treatise with political roots and motives?",
    "answer": "GERMANIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Claudius described what figure of early Roman history to have been an Etruscan mercenary who worked for Caelius Vibenna?",
    "answer": "17"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin noun commonly used by Cicero as a pejorative prescribed to the Catilinarian Conspirators is also often used by philosophical authors when describing the state of humanity or when trying to denote the difference between men, animal, and deus, which are usages separate from the Latin word vir?",
    "answer": "HOMO/HOMINES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "While homo is in contrast to animal and deus, what two words are vir in contrast to?",
    "answer": "MULIER/FEMINA & LIBERI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Another common Ciceronian word is iste. Besides occasionally having a pejorative connotation, what else can iste denote about something that ille cannot?",
    "answer": "PHYSICAL PROXIMITY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What culture hero from Arcadia brought the Greek pantheon to his new home and instituted the Lupercalia about sixty years before the start of the Trojan War?",
    "answer": "EVANDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Besides introducing the Greek pantheon, Evander also introduced to the Italians what useful invention of Palamedes?",
    "answer": "GREEK ALPHABET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Evander was related to Aeneas through which Titan?",
    "answer": "ATLAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The screams of six thousand Samnite prisoners could be heard as who addressed the Senate at the Temple of Bellona in 82 BC?",
    "answer": "SULLA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What law enabled Sulla to be dictator for life and gave him almost unlimited power?",
    "answer": "LEX VALERIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Sulla’s epitaph, “I have always rewarded my friends with good, my enemies with evil” well summarizes his reign after assuming the dictatorship of Rome. An example of this policy in full effect was when Sulla executed what legate of his for running for the consulship against his orders?",
    "answer": "QUINTUS LUCRETIUS OFELLA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Because of other accounts of the same period, most notably that written by Sallust, which portray the antagonist in a more sympathetic light, even going so far as to excuse him of any involvement at all, it is sometimes believed that what work of Latin Literature was political propaganda designed to solidify Cicero's position in the political sphere rather than a factual account of the events of 63 BC? IN CATILINAM",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where was the first speech delivered? TEMPLE OF JUPITER STATOR",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In which oration did Cicero claim that the city should rejoice because it had been saved from a bloody rebellion and present evidence that all of Catiline's accomplices confessed to their crimes. THIRD",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using two semi-deponent verbs, translate the following sentence into Latin: I was informed that the soldiers, who were accustomed to carry baggage, would arrive a little before dawn.",
    "answer": "SOLERENT, PAULO ANTE PRIMA LUCE PERVENTUROS ESSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into Latin: Who was there that dared to stop them from crossing the narrow river?",
    "answer": "ANGUSTA FLUMEN AUDERET?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a deponent verb, translate this sentence into Latin: If the troops should not arrive in the evening, whom are we to trust?",
    "answer": "SI COPIAE VESPERI NON PERVENIANT, QUO/QUIBUS FIDAMUS?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Seen most commonly with adjectives like magnus and summus and thus mostly confined to expressions of number, what rather infrequent use of the genitive is much less common than its counterpart in the ablative case?",
    "answer": "GENITIVE OF DESCRIPTION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Why would the expression “a king of wit,” when translated into Latin not be considered a genitive of description?",
    "answer": "IT LACKS AN ADJECTIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Unlike the genitive of description, the ablative of description does not necessarily need an adjective. An alternative would be a modifier in what case?",
    "answer": "GENITIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A poem on weather signs in the manner of Aratus, a historical poem on the 58 B.C. campaign against Ariovistus, and a translation of the Argonautica by Apollonius of Rhodes were all written by what author?",
    "answer": "VARRO ATACINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was the title of the work on the campaign against Ariovistus in 58 B.C.?",
    "answer": "BELLUM SEQUANICUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In addition to the works previously mentioned in the tossup. Varro of Atax also wrote erotic poetry to his beloved. What was her name?",
    "answer": "LEUCADIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "A siege by Sulla during the Social War, three battles during the Second Punic War, and the death of Augustus were all events in Roman history that occurred at what city in Campania?",
    "answer": "NOLA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "As referenced earlier, Hannibal failed to take the city of Nola three times during the Second Punic War. What Roman commander repelled all three of these attacks?",
    "answer": "MARCUS CLAUDIUS MARCELLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Around the same time that Marcellus defended the final siege of Nola, what Roman admiral landed at Apollonia with the intention of keeping Philip V in check?",
    "answer": "VALERIUS LAEVINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following poetic passage, which I will read twice in prose, and answer the questions that follow in English: Quae fueram magnis olim patefacta triumphis, ianua Patriciae vota Pudicitiae, cuius inaurati celebrarunt limina currus, captorum lacrimis umida supplicibus, nunc ego, nocturnis potorum saucia rixis, pulsata indignis saepe queror manibus, et mihi non desunt turpes pendere corollae semper et exclusi signa iacere faces. The question: Give two reasons why the door is now complaining. (accept two from list of four):",
    "answer": "HANDS//HAS UGLY GARLANDS ON ITSELF//HAS TORCHES ON ITSELF"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was the door once used for?",
    "answer": "TRIUMPHS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What opposing values has the door experience in its existence?",
    "answer": "CHASTITY AND LUST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Complete this analogy: rosus eras is to rodes as _______ is to vesceris.",
    "answer": "NO FORM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Complete this analogy: habēam is to habitī sint as liquem is to ________.",
    "answer": "LIQUATI SIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Complete this analogy: queri is to questas essetis as quire is to _______.",
    "answer": "QUIVISSETIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who railed at Agamemnon for taking Briseis from Achilles, and advised the soldiery to go home instead of remaining at Troy to make Agamemnon rich?",
    "answer": "THERSITES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who beat Thersites for his insolence?",
    "answer": "ODYSSEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After Thersites insulted Achilles for weeping over the Amazonian queen Penthesileia, Achilles killed him on the spot. This murder led to a dispute among the Greeks, and Achilles had to sacrifice to Apollo, Artemis, and Leto on what island before he could return to battle?",
    "answer": "LESBOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat: reticeo?",
    "answer": "BE SILENT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat: vadimonia?",
    "answer": "BAIL/SECURITY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat: ganeo?",
    "answer": "GLUTTON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, during the persecutions of Diocletian, was forced to abandon his teaching post in Bithynia, but was later chosen by Constantine to tutor his son Crispus in Gaul?",
    "answer": "LACTANTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In which 7 book work of Lactantius, dedicated to Constantine, does he discuss the Christian theology, the final judgement, as well as anti-paganism and philosophy?",
    "answer": "DIVINE INSTITUTIONS/DIVINAE INSTITUTIONES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Lactantius was the pupil of what earlier Christian poet who sought to refuse claims of Christians bringing calamity onto the Roman Empire in his Adversus Nationes?",
    "answer": "ARNOBIUS (OF SICCA)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Achilles was able to wound the Mysian king Telephus because what son of Iphiclus had snatched away Telephus’ shield?",
    "answer": "PROTESILAUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Telephus later begged Achilles to heal him of his wound, which Achilles willingly did in exchange for Telephus’ aid in guiding the Greeks to Troy. Afterwards, the Greeks asked Telephus to join them in fighting against the Trojans, but he refused, citing what reason?",
    "answer": "HE WAS PRIAM’S SON-IN-LAW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Telephus would fight on the Trojan side?",
    "answer": "EURYPYLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following, if any, does not belong due to derivation: conserve, deserve, observe, preserve, reserve?",
    "answer": "DESERVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin verb with what meaning is the English word “lawsuit” derived?",
    "answer": "SEQUOR-FOLLOW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin noun with what meaning is the English word “surly” derived?",
    "answer": "SENEX-OLD MAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What scholar of the Late Republic, a praetor of 58 BC and friend of Cicero, was portrayed in medieval times as a magician, diviner, and occultist, perhaps because of Jerome’s comment that he was a “Pythagoricus et magus”? NIGIDIUS FIGULUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Even in Roman times, his skills as a diviner were well known. Figulus is said to have foretold the greatness of what emperor on the day of his birth? AUGUSTUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Silver Age author would include a portrayal of Figulus uttering dire prophecies, based in part on astrological readings? LUCAN",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into Latin: The women certainly told you what they would have done.",
    "answer": "FEMINAE CERTE TIBI DIXERUNT QUID FACTURAE FUISSENT."
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into Latin: He said that he had asked the man who was present what had happened.",
    "answer": "DIXIT SE AB VIRO QUI ADESSET QUID ACCIDISSET ROGAVISSE."
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a compound of eo, translate the following sentence into Latin: Had the Romans been defeated by the Gauls, we would have been unable to behold a triumph wonderful to see.",
    "answer": "MIRABILEM VISU ASPICERE NEQUIVISSEMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "During the Third Macedonian War, what Illyrian chieftain made the unwise decision to abandon the Roman side and ally himself with Perseus?",
    "answer": "GENTHIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Genthius may have been persuaded to switch sides after what early victory of Perseus in B2. After he finally surrendered to the Romans in 168 BC, Perseus was forced to live out the rest of his life imprisoned in what small country town?",
    "answer": "ALBA FUCENS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Under what circumstances do questions within indirect statements not have their verbs in the subjunctive?",
    "answer": "(WHEN THEY ARE) RHETORICAL QUESTIONS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what case is the subject of the infinitive of a rhetorical question?",
    "answer": "ACCUSATIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of infinitive has its subject in the nominative case?",
    "answer": "22"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between ferveo and foveo.",
    "answer": "TO GLOW & TO CHERISH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between premo and promo.",
    "answer": "TO PRESS & TO BRING OUT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between purgo and pergo.",
    "answer": "TO CLEANSE AND TO PROCEED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What king and seer tried in vain to prevent his sons Adrastus and Amphius from going to the Trojan War?",
    "answer": "MEROPS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other child of Merops also died young after committing suicide shortly after marriage?",
    "answer": "CLEITE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Though he had four children, Merops only had one grandchild. Who was this grandson, to whom he taught the art of prophecy?",
    "answer": "AESACUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A right tentatively used by Claudius and then later more frequently by the Flavians, the ability to appoint any individual to the senate by decree was known as what?",
    "answer": "ADLECTIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After the reign of Domitian, the process of using adlectio reemerged many times throughout the Empire. In order to prevent opposition against the Emperor, what Phrygian freedman used adlectio to pack the Senate with as many followers of Commodus as he could?",
    "answer": "CLEANDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Cleander became infamous for auctioning offices to the highest bidder. How many consulships is Cleander said to have sold in one day?",
    "answer": "TWENTY-FIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which neoteric poet wrote a propemticon to Asinius Pollio in 56 B.C., but was better known for narrating the incestuous love of Myrrha for her father Cinyras?",
    "answer": "CINNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which neoteric poet and follower of the Atticist movement wrote a grief filled epicedion over the untimely death of his wife Quintillia, but is more known for the eponymous epyllion of the heroine who was loved by Jupiter and persecuted by Juno?",
    "answer": "(LICINIUS) CALVUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Which neoteric poet from Cisalpine Gaul wrote on a Cretan myth of the goddess Dictynna and was known among his comrades as the Latin Siren?",
    "answer": "VALERIUS CATO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of Michigan, Kentucky, Idaho, Missouri, and North Carolina, which states do not have an imperative in their Latin mottoes?",
    "answer": "KENTUCKY AND NORTH CAROLINA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of Vermont, Colorado, Virginia, District of Columbia, and Kentucky, which, if any, contain a verb in their Latin mottoes?",
    "answer": "VERMONT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Among Connecticut, Alabama, Michigan, New Mexico, and both of South Carolina’s mottoes, how many verb forms, including participals and infinitives, are there in total?",
    "answer": "TEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who fathered by his wife Enarete several of the most powerful rulers of their time, namely Cretheus, Athamas, Sisyphus, Salmoneus, and Perieres?",
    "answer": "AEOLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What king of Elis is sometimes regarded as a son of Aeolus, though he is more frequently called a son of Zeus?",
    "answer": "AETHLIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What daughter of his did Aeolus kill for committing incest?",
    "answer": "CANACE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After only reigning for a meager eight months, what emperor was found dead in his tent at Dadastana?",
    "answer": "JOVIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Jovian only became emperor after another man refused. What advisor, and Praetorian Prefect of the East, was initially chosen to succeed Julian the Apostate?",
    "answer": "SECUNDUS SALUTIUS / SALLUSTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In an effort to make a hasty peace with the Persians, Jovian gave away a lot of land to what Sassanid king?",
    "answer": "SHAPUR II"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which of the following English words, if any, is derived from the same Latin word as mauve: meager, taupe, marshmallow, mallet, manger?",
    "answer": "MARSHMALLOW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin verb is “manger” derived?",
    "answer": "MANDŌ, MANDERE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What derivative of the Latin verb mandō, mandāre means “to give a compliment”?",
    "answer": "COMMEND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into English: Quamvis scelerati illi fuissent, sunt vere tui parentes.",
    "answer": "THEY ARE INDEED YOUR PARENTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into English: Etsī caret mātūritāte, tamen hic discipulus, alacer multa discere, nōn est malum.",
    "answer": "EAGER TO LEARN MANY THINGS, IS NOT BAD."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into English: Licet omnēs tibi terrōrēs perīculaque impendeant, ne pertimueris!",
    "answer": "24"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "In the face of the unhaulting spread of vice, what author refuses to conform to the rationalistic tradition of satire by adopting the use of indignation to convey the fury of his disgust within his 16 satires?",
    "answer": "JUVENAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Juvenal often makes note of his disgust of the widespread moral corruption around him that in his third Satire, Juvenal tells the story of what friend of his who abandons Rome, for life there has become too dangerous for honest men?",
    "answer": "UMBRICIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "There was no doubt that Juvenal’s works may have offended many, but the final straw came for him when he offended the emperor’s favorite and was sent to spend his final place in what land?",
    "answer": "EGYPT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "That she was called, at her shrine at Athens, the eldest of the Fates, and that she taught the workings of the planets to Hermes are traces in the Greek tradition of what deity’s Asiatic role as an all-knowing queen of heaven?",
    "answer": "APHRODITE’S"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What minor goddess has no myth beyond being called one of the Fates or a daughter of Zeus?",
    "answer": "TYCHE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What female death spirits, who personified only the inevitability of death, and unlike the Erinyes had no retributive duties, are occasionally identified with the Fates as the bringers of death?",
    "answer": "KERES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which play of Plautus includes Sosicles reuniting with his brother after being separated and raised in different households?",
    "answer": "MENAECHMI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "In which play by Plautus does the eponymous character swindle Periphanes so that his master Strippocles can purchase the two girls he loves?",
    "answer": "EPIDICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to stock character names in Atellan Farce, what does Plautus’ nomen connote about his appearance?",
    "answer": "FLAT FOOTED/BIG EARED (MACCUS IS HIS NOMEN)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The Latin motto of Harvard is, of course, veritas, the third declension noun that means “truth.” Give the definition of the other Latin word that has also has a form “veritas.”",
    "answer": "TO FEAR/RESPECT/REVERE (VEREOR)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What two meanings can the Latin word flet have?",
    "answer": "IT WEEPS, LET IT BLOW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What three meanings can the Latin word nemus have?",
    "answer": "GROVE, LET US SWIM, & WE WEAVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following poetic passage, which I will read twice in prose, and answer the question that follows in English: Abstineas, Mors atra, precor: non hic mihi mater Quae legat in maestos ossa perusta sinus, Non soror, Assyrios cineri quae dedat odores Et fleat effusis ante sepulcra comis, Delia non usquam; quae me cum mitteret urbe, Dicitur ante omnes consuluisse deos. Illa sacras pueri sortes ter sustulit: illi Rettulit e trinis omina certa puer. The question: In order to convince death to keep his hands away, the poet begs for mercy by pointing out the absence of what three people?",
    "answer": "HIS MOTHER, HIS SISTER, DELIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two actions are described as happening thrice in this passage?",
    "answer": "AND THE BOY ASCRIBING GOOD OMENS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Where was the poet when Delia consulted the gods?",
    "answer": "OUTSIDE OF THE CITY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "At age twenty-two, I was a consul of Rome in 348 BC. I was an ardent supporter of the Lex Ogulnia of 300 BC. During my hundred-year lifespan, I held the consulship an astounding six times. Probably my most famous act, I earned my cognomen after a raven helped me defeat a giant Gaul in single combat. Who am I? ",
    "answer": "FLYING IN FRONT OF GAUL’S FACE/EYES / OBSTRUCTING HIS VIEW)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What emperor later erected a statue of Corvus in his Forum?",
    "answer": "AUGUSTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Shortly after the Greeks first disembarked from their ships, Achilles battled against and killed what king of Colonae, who had been granted invulnerability to weapons by his father Poseidon?",
    "answer": "CYCNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How did Achilles successfully kill Cycnus?",
    "answer": "HE STRANGLED HIM WITH THE THRONGS OF HIS HELMET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Another Cycnus, although aided by his father Ares, lost in battle to what Greek hero?",
    "answer": "HERACLES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man was metaphorically addressed by the patria through the literary device of prosopopoeia, used in the first of four speeches against him delivered in 63 B.C. by Cicero?",
    "answer": "CATILINE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, against whom only one of the many speeches Cicero wrote was actually delivered, was defended by one of Cicero’s greatest rivals, Hortensius Hortalus?",
    "answer": "VERRES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man was viciously attacked in Cicero’s Prō Rosciō Amerīnō for his rise from the slave markets at Delos to a life of ill-begotten luxury?",
    "answer": "CHRYSOGONUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A barber revealed the secret of what king, who had disagreed with Tmolus in judging Apollo’s musicianship and was cursed even after he had just washed away his golden touch?",
    "answer": "MIDAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "In what river did Midas wash away his golden touch?",
    "answer": "PACTOLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Tmolus was sometimes portrayed not as a mountain-god, but as a human married to what daughter of Iardanes?",
    "answer": "OMPHALE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence: “Cum modo coeperīmus, timidī tamen sumus.” Keep in mind that modo means “just now.”",
    "answer": "ALTHOUGH WE’VE JUST (NOW) BEGUN, WE’RE NONETHELESS SCARED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate: “Cum omnēs cōnsēnserimus, moderātōrī respōnsum ultimum dabimus.”",
    "answer": "MODERATOR A FINAL ANSWER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate, taking superbombiō to mean “hyperbuzz”: “In animō habeō iterum iterumque superbombīre, dōnec tandem rectē respondeam.”",
    "answer": "I INTEND TO HYPERBUZZ AGAIN AND AGAIN UNTIL I FINALLY ANSWER CORRECTLY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "As was humiliatingly commemorated in an Iranian relief, whose role changed from emperor to lowly footstool after he was defeated near Edessa by the Persian Shapur I in 260 A.D.? Advanced — Preliminary Round One",
    "answer": "VALERIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What progenitor of Shapur founded the Sassanid dynasty?",
    "answer": "ARDASHIR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What praetorian prefect of Gordian III did well to hold the Persians at bay?",
    "answer": "TIMESITHEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What sort of people popularized the song “gaudeāmus igitur,” become known by a Latin word that literally means “nourished,” and can receive so-called “Latin honors” such as summā cum laude?",
    "answer": "(UNDERGRADUATE) STUDENT(S) // GRADUATE(S) // ALUMNI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "University students are often attached to their school’s Latin mottoes. What is the Latin motto of Dartmouth College?",
    "answer": "VŌX CLĀMANTIS IN DĒSERTŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What West Coast school has the Latin motto “palmam quī meruit ferat”?",
    "answer": "UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA // USC"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whose actions gave the road on which they occurred its name when, having already murdered her husband Arruns, she drove over the corpse of her deceased father Servius Tullius?",
    "answer": "TULLIA (MINOR)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What was the Latin name — which started with vīcus, not via — for the road on which Tullia’s actions took place?",
    "answer": "VĪCUS SCELERĀTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What hill of Rome was Tullia reportedly headed towards when she ran over her father, conveniently the same hill on which Tullius lived?",
    "answer": "ESQUILINE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A recent edition of The New York Times included letters to the editor under the title “Should Schools Curb Grade Inflation?” From what Latin verb, with what meaning, do we derive “inflation”?",
    "answer": "FLŌ – TO BREATHE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin adjective, with what meaning, do we derive “curb”?",
    "answer": "CURVUS – CURVED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "One of the letters, advocating against artificial grade deflation, contains the sentence “Grades are not a limited resource.” Give the Latin words at the ultimate root of “limited” and “resource.” LĪMES – BORDER / LIMIT and REGŌ – RULE / DIRECT",
    "answer": "[PROMPT ON SURGŌ WITH “CAN YOU GIVE THE ULTIMATE ROOT FOR SURGŌ?”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "The only extant fābulae cothurnātae were written by what Silver Age author, more known for addressing Helvia with a Dē Cōnsōlātiōne and Lucillius with Stoic “moral epistles”?",
    "answer": "SENECA THE YOUNGER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Of Livius Andronicus, Ennius, Pacuvius, and Accius, how many have fully extant fābulae praetextae?",
    "answer": "NONE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of those same individuals, how many are known to have written fābulae palliātae? Advanced — Preliminary Round One",
    "answer": "TWO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What meaning is shared by the nouns dēlūbrum, fānum, and aedis, which often see people in the act of precārī and contain an āra, and are also synonymous with templum?",
    "answer": "TEMPLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What does aedis mean in the plural?",
    "answer": "HOUSE / HOME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of building are māgālia, which appear in Book 1 of the Aeneid in the lines “Mīrātur mōlem Aenēās, māgālia quondam, / mīrātur portās strepitumque et strāta viārum”?",
    "answer": "HUTS / TENTS / SHABBY DWELLINGS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who claimed to be a Cretan son of Deucalion named Aethon while disguised as a beggar, during which time he boxed Irus, faced Antinous’s mockery, and revealed himself to Eumaeus?",
    "answer": "ODYSSEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Another of Odysseus’s lies involved him being a Cretan wanderer who settled in Egypt, which may be connected to the historical Battle of the Delta between Ramses III and the mysterious Sea Peoples. Similarly, what people, led by Tarchon and Mezentius in the Aeneid, may be connected with a subgroup of the Sea Peoples called the Teresh?",
    "answer": "TYRRHENIANS / ETRUSCANS / TYRSENIANS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What mythological group’s legend may reflect historical evidence of a Dorian invasion of the Peloponnesus, which some have also connected with the Sea Peoples?",
    "answer": "HERACLIDS // DESCENDANTS OF HERACLES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Often seen following adverbs of place such as ubi, what use of the genitive also frequently follows superlatives or appears in phrases such as quis vestrum, nēmō eōrum, and pars mīlitum?",
    "answer": "PARTITIVE GENITIVE // GENITIVE OF THE WHOLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate: “Nēscīmus ubinam gentium hostis sit.”",
    "answer": "PEOPLES”; PROMPT IF THE TRANSLATION IS TOO STILTED TO MAKE ENGLISH SENSE]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence using a partitive genitive: “One of the consuls is good, the other is bad.”",
    "answer": "ALTER CŌNSULUM EST BONUS, ALTER EST MALUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What general cardinal direction would one travel to get from Trapezus to Byzantium, from Utica to Gades, or from Byzantium to Tarentum?",
    "answer": "WEST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What general cardinal direction would one travel from what the Romans called Philadelphia to Hierosolyma?",
    "answer": "WEST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What general cardinal direction would one travel from Glevum to Augusta Treverorum?",
    "answer": "EAST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Triple-faced statues depicted what goddess, who was also known as Brimo, was accompanied by hellhounds, represented crossroads, and was the patron of sorceresses like Medea? Advanced — Preliminary Round One",
    "answer": "HECATE [PROMPT BEFORE BRIMO ON “ARTEMIS” OR “SELENE”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Hecate was also worshiped as the goddess of what object, alongside two other female deities?",
    "answer": "MOON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Under what name did the people of Thalamae worship the moon goddess? This name is more commonly associated with a sister of Circe.",
    "answer": "PASIPHAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What location saw two battles, one where Attius Varius defeated Scribonius Curio in 49 B.C., another where the Spartan mercenary Xanthippus captured Atilius Regulus in 255?",
    "answer": "BAGRADAS VALLEY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two monarchs were defeated 20 years apart at Pydna, one a legitimate Macedonian king, the other a pretender who claimed to be his son? PERSEUS and ANDRISCUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What lake saw two Roman victories during the Republic, one by Publius Cornelius Dollabella against the Boii, and the other by Fabius Rullianus against the Etruscan League?",
    "answer": "(LAKE) VADIMO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, writing primarily in Asclepiadic, Alcaic, and Sapphic meters, addresses his patron Maecenas and encourages readers to “love golden moderation” and “seize the day”?",
    "answer": "HORACE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Iambī was the Latin name for what other work of Horace, which borrows more from Archilochus than Alcaeus and contains an inverted propempticon wishing ill on Maevius?",
    "answer": "EPODES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "In another major Horatian work, he cites what author as his inspiration, saying that he “rubbed the city down with much salt” despite his disordered compositional style?",
    "answer": "LUCILIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "An attempt to rape the Hyperborean maiden Opis, an ill-fated game of quoits with Artemis, or a boast that he would kill all animals are all stories that explain the demise of what giant hunter?",
    "answer": "ORION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Orion’s most known myth is being blinded by what king of Chios, whose daughter Merope he had attempted to rape?",
    "answer": "OENOPION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was Orion’s first wife, sent down to Hades for claiming to be more beautiful than Hera?",
    "answer": "SIDE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Before his death at the Lūdī Apollinārēs in 169 B.C., what “semigraecus” author published Hedyphaegetica and Ambracia, which retold events also recounted in his hexameter Annālēs?",
    "answer": "ENNIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "In his Annālēs, Ennius declares himself the reincarnation of which Greek author because he had appeared to Ennius in a dream?",
    "answer": "HOMER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What work of Ennius is a translation which conveyed the idea that gods originated from stories about heroes of mankind? Advanced — Preliminary Round One",
    "answer": "EUHĒMERUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a participle of loquor, say in Latin: “After saying this, they left.” You will need a nominative plural perfect participle. Β1: Using a participle of loquor and a different word for “to leave,” say in Latin: “I left her as she was saying such things.”",
    "answer": "EAM TĀLIA LOQUENTEM RELĪQUĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Sometimes deponent perfect participles can be translated as present participles. Translate the following sentence: “Caesar, veritus nē hostēs castra cēpissent, explōrātōrēs mīsit.”",
    "answer": "CAMP, SENT SCOUTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What political position was used to sell 25 consulships in a day by one man — Cleander — and to accuse rivals of treason during Tiberius’ island retirement by another — Sejanus?",
    "answer": "PRAETORIAN PREFECT // PRAEFECTUS PRAETŌRIŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Cleander was chamberlain and praetorian prefect under what emperor, though he was later replaced by Eclectus in the former position and Laetus in the latter?",
    "answer": "COMMODUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Cleander was ultimately sacrificed to the mob to appease their anger over what sort of event?",
    "answer": "FAMINE // GRAIN SHORTAGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The noun suffixes -ciō, -xilla, and -ulus all signify what sort of noun, often used to denote affection or small size?",
    "answer": "DIMINUTIVES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the diminutive form of mūnus which means “a small gift.”",
    "answer": "MŪNUSCULUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now give the diminutive of liber, a word used by Catullus in the first line of his first poem to describe his work. Advanced — Preliminary Round One Advanced — Preliminary Round Two",
    "answer": "LIBELLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What event, in which Faenius Rufus played an integral role and which caused the deaths of Thrasea Paetus and Lucan, was a plot that took place in 65 A.D. to assassinate Nero?",
    "answer": "PISONIAN CONSPIRACY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Faenius Rufus was the colleague of what other praetorian prefect of Nero, who replaced Afranius Burrus as a “darker” influence on Nero?",
    "answer": "(OFONIUS) TIGELLINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other praetorian prefect replaced Faenius Rufus, later claiming descent from Caligula and trying to usurp the throne during the reign of Galba?",
    "answer": "NYMPHIDIUS SABINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: “Nūper, trēdecim puerī duodēvigintī arbōrēs ūnō diē ascendērunt.”",
    "answer": "THIRTEEN BOYS RECENTLY CLIMBED EIGHTEEN TREES IN ONE DAY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate: “Dum nōnnullae puellae in silvā lūdunt, octōgintā aliae librīs fruēbantur.”",
    "answer": "ENJOYING BOOKS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate, using efficiō: “With nineteen guards sleeping, the twentieth brought it about that the camp was saved.”",
    "answer": "UT CASTRA SERVĀRENTUR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "In a Greek tragedy, who criticizes “the one who considers a friend more important than their own country” when he bans the burial of Polynices and condemns Antigone to death?",
    "answer": "CREON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Creon and fiance of Antigone tries to convince his father to spare her, fails, and commits suicide in front of his father in protest?",
    "answer": "HAEMON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "In Sophocles’s Antigone, after Teiresias tells Creon that the gods are not accepting sacrifices because of the death of Antigone, what group reminds Creon that Teiresias has never been wrong and he needs to heed the warning?",
    "answer": "CHORUS / THEBAN ELDERS [ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Six poems to Neaera and five to Cerinthus from Sulpicia are included in the corpus of what elegiac poet, who is most known for his poems to Marathus and Delia?",
    "answer": "TIBULLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was the patron of Tibullus that Tibullus accompanied on several military expeditions such as the expedition to Aquitania?",
    "answer": "MESSALA (CORVINUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Horace, Tibullus also had an unhappy love for what woman, who is not mentioned by name in his poetry? Advanced — Preliminary Round Two",
    "answer": "GLYCERA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Complete the following analogy, which contains extra clues if necessary: vetō is to [blank] as edō is to ēsset OR volō is to vellet OR dūcō is to dūceret.",
    "answer": "VETĀRET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Vetō is to [blank] as amō is to amātus eram.",
    "answer": "VETITUS ERAM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Vetō is to [blank] as dō is to duint.",
    "answer": "VETENT [GIVE 20 BROWNIE POINTS FOR THE ARCHAIC FORM VOTENT]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between the verbs luceō and lugeō. TO SHINE and TO MOURN (RESPECTIVELY)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now differentiate in meaning between the nouns mōlēs and prōlēs. MASS and OFFSPRING (RESPECTIVELY)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now differentiate in meaning between the nouns lutum and lētum. MUD / CLAY and DEATH (RESPECTIVELY)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What important book, which one author read upon hearing the chant tolle, lege, ultimately inspired the ideology of authors like Tertullian and Lactantius and was translated into Latin by Saint Jerome?",
    "answer": "(HOLY) BIBLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "The author inspired to read the Bible by the words tolle, lege was Augustine. What work of Cicero was another book that changed Augustine’s life?",
    "answer": "HORTENSIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Before he wrote his Christian works, Lactantius was professor of rhetoric in what city?",
    "answer": "NICOMEDIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which praenōmen of Sabine origin was brought to Rome by a man of the gēns Claudia and is abbreviated App.?",
    "answer": "APPIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which praenomen was only used by the gēns Aemilia and is abbreviated Mam.?",
    "answer": "MAMERCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which praenomen was only used by the gēns Iūlia, fell out of use after the early Republic, and is sometimes abbreviated Vop.?",
    "answer": "VOPISCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What deity, for whom four horses were thrown annually into the sea by Rhodians, exposed Ares and Aphrodite’s affair and spurned Clytie, who turned into a sunflower?",
    "answer": "HELIOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What possible son of Helios was the only person to offer Heracles financial compensation for one of his labors, though he reneged on his offer?",
    "answer": "AUGEAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Heracles led the Rhodian contingent at Troy, where he was killed by Sarpedon? Advanced — Preliminary Round Two",
    "answer": "TLEPOLEMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who used a lēx Valeria to become dictātor reī pūblicae cōnstituendae after defeating forces raised by Carbo, Cinna, and Marius the Younger at battles including Colline Gate in 82 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(L. CORNELIUS) SULLA (FELIX)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What nearby Italian city, now called Palestrina, was Marius the Younger attempting to defend when his life was cut short by Sulla?",
    "answer": "PRAENESTE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was the co-consul of Scipio Asiaticus in 83 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(C.) NORBANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Events of what sort were ended by the exchange of a scarlet belt and sword and the breaking of a helmet thong in books 7 and 3 of the Iliad, ending hopes of cutting the war short?",
    "answer": "DUEL(S) // SINGLE COMBAT(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After the duel in book 7 of the Iliad, what Trojan elder advocates for returning Helen?",
    "answer": "ANTENOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Before the duel in book 3 of the Iliad, Helen identifies what Cretan, a frequent guest of hers?",
    "answer": "IDOMENEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What meaning is shared between the Latin verb from which we derive “scout” and the Latin verb from which we derive “obedient” — auscultō and audiō?",
    "answer": "TO HEAR / LISTEN TO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What meaning is shared between the Latin verbs from which we derive “arraign” and “excise” in the context of “excise tax”?",
    "answer": "TO THINK / JUDGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What meaning is shared between the Latin nouns from which we derive “scourge” and “surplice”?",
    "answer": "SKIN / HIDE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whose fondness for Alpine cheese caused his death at Lorium, leaving behind a temple for his wife Faustina, an empire that had been at peace from 138 to 161 A.D., and a second wall in Scotland?",
    "answer": "(TITUS AURELIUS) ANTONINUS PIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Antoninus also established a charity in memory of Faustina, which expanded what program established by Trajan as a welfare system for freeborn children?",
    "answer": "ALIMENTA // ALIMENTARY SYSTEM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Antoninus was not Hadrian’s first choice as successor. Whose death in 138 A.D. caused Hadrian to select Antoninus instead?",
    "answer": "(LUCIUS) AELIUS CAESAR // (LUCIUS) CEIONIUS COMMODUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Excluding sound effects, identify a literary device that can be found in the 4th line of the Aeneid — “Vī superum saevae memorem Iūnōnis ob īram” — a line which contains ABAB word order.",
    "answer": "SYNCHYSIS / TRANSFERRED EPITHET / HYPALLAGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which literary device, excluding all forms of alliteration, can be found in the following sentence adapted from the Aeneid? “Tum Cererem corruptam undīs expediunt fessī rērum.” Advanced — Preliminary Round Two",
    "answer": "METONYMY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which literary device can be found in the following line from Ovid’s Metamorphoses? “‘invide,’ dīcēbant, ‘pariēs, quid amantibus obstās?’”",
    "answer": "PERSONIFICATION / APOSTROPHE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author received a threat starting “dabunt malum” from the aristocratic family of the Metelli in the same Saturnian meter he used for his seven-book epic, Bellum Pūnicum?",
    "answer": "(GNAEUS) NAEVIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Naevius had provoked the Metelli by saying that they “become consuls by [blank].” What word fills in the blank?",
    "answer": "FATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Naevius’s epitaph, what did the Romans forget how to do after his death?",
    "answer": "SPEAK LATIN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a purpose clause, say in Latin: “I am going to the forum to buy food.”",
    "answer": "AD FORUM EŌ UT CIBUM EMAM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a genitive gerundive, say in Latin: “I am going to the forum to buy food.”",
    "answer": "AD FORUM EŌ CIBĪ EMENDĪ {CAUSĀ / GRĀTIĀ}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a participle in the appropriate tense, say in Latin: “I am going to the forum to buy food.”",
    "answer": "AD FORUM EŌ CIBUM {ĒMPTŪRUS / ĒMPTŪRA}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The compass, the potter’s wheel, and the saw were all invented by what ingenious boy, who was flung off the Acropolis and turned into a partridge by his uncle Daedalus in a jealous rage?",
    "answer": "PERDIX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Belus invented the first 2-prowed ship to aid in his escape from his twin brother?",
    "answer": "DANAUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what region, later ruled by Nyctimus, did a culture-hero named Pelasgus invent sheepskin coats and huts and teach men to eat acorns?",
    "answer": "ARCADIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Keenly interested in “cultural relativism,” what Roman author compared Greek, Carthaginian, and Roman statesmen in his Dē Virīs Illūstribus and was the dedicatee of Catullus’s poems?",
    "answer": "CORNELIUS NEPOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Nepos also wrote a biography of what early author, who would have rejected “cultural relativism” in the steadfast pursuit of Rōmānitās that he displays in his seven-book history?",
    "answer": "CATO THE ELDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What later Roman author also wrote a Chronicon and a Dē Virīs Illūstribus based on Eusebius’ Chronicle and Historia Ecclēsiastica, respectively?",
    "answer": "JEROME"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What king, kept at bay by the admiral Valerius Laevinus when he allied with Hannibal after Cannae, was ousted when an Aetolian appeal led Flamininus to defeat him at Cynoscephalae? Advanced — Preliminary Round Two",
    "answer": "PHILIP V"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What kingdom joined forces with Valerius Laevinus under its king Attalus I, and later provided Rome with significant assistance under Eumenes II?",
    "answer": "PERGAMUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "After the Second Illyrian War, what man, who had betrayed first Teuta, then Rome, fled to Philip V for protection?",
    "answer": "DEMETRIUS OF PHAROS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What neuter Latin noun, which is irreparābile according to a line from the Georgics, is said by Ovid to be edāx rērum and by Vergil to “fugit … fugit,” never to be reclaimed?",
    "answer": "TEMPUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What verb, in two different forms, fills in the blanks in the following Latin quote that refers to the impermanence of life: “tempora [blank] et nōs [blank] in illīs”?",
    "answer": "MŪTŌ / MŪTĀRE / MŪTANTUR / MŪTĀMUR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What four-word quotation from Horace’s Odes expresses a similar sentiment to tempus fugit and is often translated “alas, the fleeting years glide by”? Advanced — Preliminary Round Two Advanced — Preliminary Round Three",
    "answer": "ĒHEU, FUGĀCĒS LĀBUNTUR ANNĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "The focus of a local myth from Brasiae and an Orphic tradition where he was the resurrection of Zagreus, what god was nursed by Ino and later drove her and Agave to kill Pentheus?",
    "answer": "DIONYSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Another weird tradition about Dionysus claims he was killed in what city? Other versions say that he faced Proëtus there, presumably before Acrisius took over the kingship.",
    "answer": "ARGOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In a tradition associated with Orphism, Cronus and Rhea deposed not Uranus, but what most ancient goddess, who fell into the Ocean alongside her consort, Ophion?",
    "answer": "EURYNOME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who got the lēx Rubria passed, which would have given North African land to veterans to found a colony dedicated to Juno, before an SCU allowed Opimius to murder him in 121 B.C.?",
    "answer": "GAIUS (SEMPRONIUS) GRACCHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Gaius Gracchus also passed a law excluding senators from the quaestiō dē rēbus repetundīs, a permanent court meant to try cases of what crime?",
    "answer": "EXTORTION // PROVINCIAL MALADMINISTRATION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Italian town’s rebellion against Rome was crushed by Lucius Opimius a few years before Gracchus’s tribunate?",
    "answer": "FREGELLAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work, possibly inspired by Propertius 4.3, consists of 21 short poems on the theme of the “lament of the abandoned woman” in which Penelope, Dido and others are given voice by Ovid?",
    "answer": "HĒRŌIDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Another important inspiration for the Hērōides was the ekphrasis on Theseus and Ariadne in the middle of which poem of Catullus, which focuses on the marriage of Peleus and Thetis?",
    "answer": "(CATULLUS) 64"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In discussing poems like Catullus 64, what distinguishes the specific term ekphrasis from a term like “digression” or “embedded narrative”?",
    "answer": "(WITHIN A POEM)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Parse the archaic form of edō in the following line adapted from Naevius: Caepam edundōd oculus alter profluit. This would be rendered as edundō or edendō in classical Latin.",
    "answer": "ABLATIVE GERUND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the case and number of the first word of Lucretius’s Dē Rērum Nātūrā: “Aeneadum genetrīx, hominum dīvumque voluptās.”",
    "answer": "GENITIVE PLURAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Fill in the following Lucretian line with an archaic present passive infinitive of cēlō: “Nōn possent ūllum tempus [blank] ignēs” Advanced — Preliminary Round Three",
    "answer": "CĒLĀRIER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What body of water, which a Roman would have to pass through to get from the Propontis to the Pontus Euxīnus, was a strait located east of Byzantium named after Io’s journey?",
    "answer": "BOSPHORUS / BOSPORUS (STRAIT)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What would a Roman call the strait northwest of Troy that they would sail through from the Mare Aegaeum to the Propontis?",
    "answer": "HELLESPONT / HELLESPONTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the modern name for the Hellespont?",
    "answer": "DARDANELLES (STRAIT) / (STRAIT OF) GALLIPOLI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The two extant works of what man are a speech thanking the emperor for appointing him consul suffectus in 100 A.D. and a 10-book collection of letters that describes Mt. Vesuvius?",
    "answer": "PLINY THE YOUNGER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was the name of Pliny’s speech thanking the emperor Trajan?",
    "answer": "PANEGYRICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following positions did Pliny the Younger not achieve in his political career: aedile, praetor, tribune of the plebs, quaestor?",
    "answer": "AEDILE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What experience, symbolized by the artistic inscription “et in Arcadiā ego,” prompts the abbreviation d.s.p. — dēcessit sine prōle — and has its causes examined in a postmortem?",
    "answer": "DEATH / DYING [ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What two-word Latin phrase, an artistic trope that symbolizes the inevitability of death, is often translated “remember that you must die”?",
    "answer": "MEMENTŌ MORĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin word fills in the phrase “[blank] Acheruntis,” meaning “food for the gallows”?",
    "answer": "PĀBULUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Worshiped as meteorites at Orchomenus, what deities may have been tasked with dispensing beauty to young girls in their function as personal attendants to Aphrodite?",
    "answer": "GRACES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "By what collective name were the Graces known to the Greeks?",
    "answer": "CHARITES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which Grace was identified by Hesiod as the wife of Hephaestus?",
    "answer": "AGLAEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What city, near which Gallienus was assassinated, was the home of the western Augustus during the Tetrarchy and the origin of a namesake edict of religious toleration in 313 A.D.?",
    "answer": "MEDIOLANUM / MILAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The edict of Milan was agreed upon between what two Augusti? CONSTANTINE (I // THE GREAT) and LICINIUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What general had Gallienus besieged at Mediolanum prior to his assassination? Advanced — Preliminary Round Three",
    "answer": "(MANIUS ACILIUS) AUREOLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the subjunctive can be found in the sentences “Doleam necne doleam nihil interest,” “Cōnsuluit, possetne id fierī,” and “Mīrābar quid reī esset”?",
    "answer": "INDIRECT QUESTION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the subjunctive is found in this line from Cicero: “Neque enim tū is es quī nesciās”?",
    "answer": "RELATIVE CLAUSE OF CHARACTERISTIC"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Finally, what use of the subjunctive is found in the phrases dī faxint and quod dī omen averterint?",
    "answer": "OPTATIVE / WISH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Domitius Ahenobarbus’ beard was turned bronze with the touch of what figures, who aided Aulus Postumius Albus by appearing on shining horses at the Battle of Lake Regillus? THE DIOSCURI // CASTOR and POLLUX",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name the son-in-law of Tarquinius Superbus, a man from Tusculum who was killed during this battle while leading the Latin forces against Rome.",
    "answer": "OCTAVIUS MAMILIUS // MAMILIUS OCTAVIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name the Roman who killed Octavius Mamilius, who was one of Horatius Cocles’ allies at the Pons Sublicius.",
    "answer": "TITUS HERMINIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Ehōdum, prō, mehercle, babae, ēia, and euge are all words of what kind, not to be strictly classified as a part of speech, since they are simply expressions of strong emotion?",
    "answer": "INTERJECTIONS / EXCLAMATIONS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following could best be used to express the joy of winning a hard-fought contest: heus, ēn, vae, iō, ēheu?",
    "answer": "IŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the words in the preceding question can rarely take the accusative, especially with personal pronouns, but more routinely takes the dative?",
    "answer": "VAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "It is imperative that one distinguish among the various forms of indirect discourse. Translate into Latin: “Grumio asked that Rufus be absent tomorrow.” This will use an indirect command.",
    "answer": "GRUMIŌ PETĪVIT/QUAESĪVIT UT RŪFUS CRĀS ABESSET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate: “Grumio knew, however, that both Rufus and Marcus would be present.”",
    "answer": "GRUMIŌ AUTEM SCIĒBAT ET RŪFUM ET MARCUM ADFUTŪRŌS ESSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate into the best Latin: “I do not doubt that Grumio has a plan.”",
    "answer": "NŌN DUBITŌ QUĪN GRUMIŌ CŌNSILIUM HABEAT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who is the addressee of letters attributed to Sallust, whom he put in charge of Africa; the subject of the first of 12 gossipy biographies by Suetonius; and the author of Dē Bellō Gallicō?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS JULIUS) CAESAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who wrote the eighth book of Dē Bellō Gallicō?",
    "answer": "(AULUS) HIRTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Suetonius’s biography of Caesar begins abruptly and is likely missing its opening, which would have included a dedication to what man? Advanced — Preliminary Round Three",
    "answer": "SEPTICIUS CLARUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "By sending a son of Mygdalion with 49 clay ships to Troy, what king of Cyprus had time to engage in an unwitting incestuous relationship with his daughter Myrrha?",
    "answer": "CINYRAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Cinyras promised to send 50 real ships when he was visited by Menelaus, Odysseus, and what Greek herald, often paired with Eurybates?",
    "answer": "TALTHYBIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Apollodorus claims that Adonis was in fact simply the son of Cinyras and his wife, the daughter of Pygmalion. Name her.",
    "answer": "METHARME [DO NOT ACCEPT “CENCHREIS”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What two Latin words are found at the root of the name for a wedge-shaped writing style used in ancient Mesopotamia — cuneiform? CUNEUS (WEDGE) and FORMA (SHAPE)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What two Latin words are found at the root of the name for a type of stiff fabric used to stiffen clothing — crinoline? CRĪNIS (HAIR) and LĪNUM (FLAX / THREAD)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Finally, what two Latin words are found at the root of the word for a type of decorative bedspread — coverlet? OPERIŌ (TO COVER) and LECTUS (BED)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What island had a king who tried to take one of Heracles’s bulls in a boxing match and a later king named Acestes, who hosted Aeneas for the funeral games of Anchises?",
    "answer": "SICILY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Like Heracles, that king — Eryx — could also claim divine descent, as what deity was his mother?",
    "answer": "APHRODITE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "During the funeral games of Anchises, what figure was said to have learned boxing from Eryx, a skill that helped him win against his Trojan opponent?",
    "answer": "ENTELLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What emperor forced Aemilius Lepidus — who later rebelled with Gaetulicus — to marry his sister Drusilla, though he may have engaged in incest with her after his illness in 37 A.D.?",
    "answer": "CALIGULA // GAIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What sister of Drusilla married her own uncle after said uncle changed the laws to make this legal?",
    "answer": "AGRIPPINA THE YOUNGER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What position did Lepidus’s triumviral ancestor pass on to Augustus upon his death in 12 B.C.?",
    "answer": "PONTIFEX MAXIMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate any of these sentences, which mean the same thing. “Mihi librīs dē linguā Latīnā opus est,” or “Egeō librīs dē linguā Latīnā,” or “Necesse est habeam librōs dē linguā Latīnā.” Advanced — Preliminary Round Three",
    "answer": "[ALSO ACCEPT “I LACK” OR “IT IS NECESSARY THAT I HAVE”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate the following sentence: “Librī Cicerōnis prōsunt ad linguam discendam.”",
    "answer": "THE BOOKS OF CICERO ARE BENEFICIAL FOR LEARNING THE LANGUAGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now idiomatically translate the following sentence: “Quid prōdest linguae Latīnae studēre, sī Aenēida numquam lēctūrus es?”",
    "answer": "WHAT IS THE POINT OF STUDYING LATIN, IF YOU’RE NEVER GOING TO READ THE AENEID?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author discusses a dinner given by Virro, the protests of Naevolus, and cannibalism in Egypt, all in a tone of angry indignātiō at the vices of the people he satirizes?",
    "answer": "(D. JUNIUS) JUVENAL(IS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which of Juvenal’s satires discusses an episode of cannibalism reported to have occurred in Egypt?",
    "answer": "FIFTEEN(TH SATIRE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What man angrily leaves Rome in Juvenal’s third satire, hopefully not reflecting the emotion you will feel upon leaving Yale Certamen prelims? Advanced — Preliminary Round Three Advanced — Semifinals",
    "answer": "UMBRICIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who executed Cornificia and Plautilla, conducted a massacre at Alexandria, and murdered his brother in his mother’s arms before his assassination by Julius Martialis in 217 A.D.?",
    "answer": "CARACALLA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to some sources, Caracalla treacherously attempted to assassinate what Parthian king after proposing marriage with his daughter?",
    "answer": "ARTABANUS (IV / V)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What peculiar change did Caracalla make to the imperial palace on the Palatine early in his reign?",
    "answer": "DIVIDED IT IN TWO (TO AVOID LIVING WITH GETA)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Relying on his experience designing the Basilica of Fano and serving as an officer in Caesar’s engineering corps, what author set out to write a comprehensive treatise on architecture?",
    "answer": "(MARCUS) VITRUVIUS (POLLIO)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How many books comprise Vitruvius’ Dē Architectūrā?",
    "answer": "10"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To whom is the Dē Architectūrā dedicated?",
    "answer": "AUGUSTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage, which is Sophonisba’s speech after she is captured by Massinissa, then answer the questions that follow in English: “Omnia quidem ut possīs in mē, dī dedērunt virtūsque tua. Sed sī captīvae ōrāre licet, precor nē mē in Rōmānōrum arbitrium venīre sinās. Multum Carthāginiēnsī timendum est, plūs etiam Hasdrubālis fīliae.” The question: What two aspects of Sophonisba’s identity make her especially frightened of coming into the Romans’ power?",
    "answer": "BEING A CARTHAGINIAN AND DAUGHTER OF HASDRUBAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What did the gods grant Massinissa?",
    "answer": "THE POWER TO DO ANYTHING TO SOPHONISBA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The passage continues, describing Massinissa’s reaction to the speech: Itaque cum propius blanditiās iam ōrātiō esset quam precēs, in amōrem prōlāpsus est victōr. The question: How does the author characterize Sophonisba’s speech?",
    "answer": "CLOSER TO FLATTERY THAN {BEGGING / PRAYER}"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What woman, after a battle at Marathon, either gouged out the eyes of a severed head brought to her by Hyllus or personally ordered Eurystheus’s death, avenging his persecution of her son?",
    "answer": "ALCMENE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In some versions, who saw two stars above his chariot as he pursued Eurystheus, giving him the power to carry on?",
    "answer": "IOLAUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Hyllus is said to have pursued Eurystheus as far as what geographical formation, named after a local Megarian warlord? Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": "{SCIRONIAN / SCEIRONIAN} ROCKS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the forms vesperāscit, ningit, scīscit, and grandinat, which does not belong because it cannot be used impersonally to refer to a change of heavenly phenomena?",
    "answer": "SCĪSCIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Such words as scīscō and vesperāscit are categorized as what sort of verbs, which denote the beginning of an action?",
    "answer": "INCHOATIVES / INCEPTIVES"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What type of verb is exemplified by verbs meaning “to jest” and “to warble”?",
    "answer": "DIMINUTIVES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For this question, take cīvitās as “state” and sententia as “motto.” Quae cīvitās, cūius sententia iussit pācem bellō praeferre, nōn iam sententiam Latīnam habet, sed habēbat “Cēdant arma togae?”",
    "answer": "WYOMING"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quae cīvitās in sententiā suā dīcit pācem vērē līberam bellō petendam esse?",
    "answer": "MASSACHUSETTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quae cīvitās in sententiā suā eōs laudat quī aliquid incipiunt cūius frūctus nōn nisi post mortem percipiētur?",
    "answer": "NORTH DAKOTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On an island in the Black Sea, what Oceanid was startled by Rhea’s arrival during her affair with Cronus, after which she fled and gave birth to the centaur Chiron?",
    "answer": "PHILYRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Into what did Zeus transform Philyra?",
    "answer": "LINDEN / LIME TREE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In lost tragedies, what granddaughter of Chiron was forced to expose her sons Aeolus and Boeotus, who were adopted by Theano and Metapontus?",
    "answer": "MELANIPPE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What battle, whose aftermath saw Quintus Pedius become consul, was preceded by a skirmish at Forum Gallorum and involved Decimus Brutus being freed by Hirtius and Pansa?",
    "answer": "(BATTLE OF) MUTINA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "The 43 B.C. battle of Mutina was actually not the first time a man named Brutus had been besieged at Mutina — the same thing happened in 77 B.C to an ally of what rebellious consul of 78, who had tried to rescind Sulla’s legislation?",
    "answer": "(M. AEMILIUS) LEPIDUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "At what battle near Rome was Lepidus defeated by the proconsul Lutatius Catulus?",
    "answer": "(BATTLE OF THE) MILVIAN BRIDGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Perhaps inspired by Sisenna’s translations of Aristides in following the tradition of Milesian Fables, what author from Madaura wrote an 11-book novel called Asinus Aureus?",
    "answer": "APULEIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What bella fabella, encompassing books 5 and 6, serves as the model old wives’ tale for Apuleius’ masterpiece? Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": "CUPID & PSYCHE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Asinus Aureus centers around Lucius’s quest for what sort of plant, which could restore him to human form?",
    "answer": "ROSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a supine, say in Latin: “Children often say things amazing to hear.”",
    "answer": "{PUERĪ / LĪBERĪ} SAEPE DĪCUNT MĪRABILIA AUDITŪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence: “Marius mīlitēs turrim mūnītam obsessum mīsit.”",
    "answer": "MARIUS SENT SOLDIERS TO BESIEGE THE FORTIFIED TOWER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence: “Pars nostrum in hōc certāmine perficiendō nimium sērō cubitum īvit.”",
    "answer": "SOME OF US, IN FINISHING THIS TOURNAMENT, WENT TO BED TOO LATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What three Latin verbs can all be at the root of the two-letter English suffix “-fy” — exemplified by the words “vilify,” “crucify,” and “defy” — and mean “to make,” “to attach,” and “to trust”?",
    "answer": "FACIŌ, FĪGŌ, FĪDŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What four Latin words can all be at the root of the four-letter English suffix “-gree” in the words “pedigree,” “filigree,” “agree,” and “degree”?",
    "answer": "GRŪS, GRĀNUM, GRĀTUS, {GRADUS / GRADIOR}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What two Latin nouns can be at the root of “round” in the words “around” and “surround”? ROTA and UNDA",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Through victories at Vetera and Augusta Treverorum, what future governor of Britain drove Julius Classicus and Julius Civilis back to their territory and ended the Batavian revolt?",
    "answer": "(QUINTUS PETILLIUS) CERIALIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What city, whose modern-day name is Mainz, fell back into Cerialis’ hands with no resistance, allowing him the position to take back Augusta Treverorum?",
    "answer": "MOGUNTIACUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Cerialis had previously served in Britain under Suetonius Paulinus, leading a legion against Boudicca from what ancient city, now known as Lincoln?",
    "answer": "LINDUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What city, the birthplace of Cicero’s commentator Asconius, was the subject of a famous reproach by Asinius Pollio that criticized the “provincial” style of its most famous native, Livy?",
    "answer": "PADUA / PATAVIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Northern Italy was a common birthplace for Roman authors. What northern Italian playwright, a native of Mediolanum, did Cicero accuse of being a “malus auctor Latīnitātis”?",
    "answer": "CAECILIUS STATIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Silver Age author may have been born in Patavium, given that his full name begins Tiberius Catius Asconius and within his poem he highlights a soldier named Pedianus?",
    "answer": "(TI. CATIUS ASCONIUS) SILIUS ITALICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which cult was an offshoot of Zoroastrianism, as it promoted the worship of a Persian god, exclusively admitted men, namely soldiers, and constructed temples akin to caves? Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": "THE CULT OF MITHRAS / MITHRAISM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Archaeology has yielded around 700 depictions of Mithras killing what sort of animal?",
    "answer": "BULL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "During the principate, emperor worship was highly controversial. As a result, which goddess became associated with the deified emperors in the west?",
    "answer": "ROMA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Objects of what type include one that Iris offered to Eileithyia and one made by Hephaestus, used at Iphis’s suggestion to bribe Eriphyle after it was given to Harmonia along with a robe?",
    "answer": "NECKLACE(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Euripides, tokens like a golden necklace helped what woman realize that an infant raised at Delphi, whom she had tried to kill, was actually her own son by Apollo?",
    "answer": "CREUSA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What woman receives a necklace from Peisander and earrings from Eurydamas, among a whole suite of other gifts that Homer does not recount in full?",
    "answer": "PENELOPE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "In Varro’s Logistorici, what author speaks on chronology, reflecting the expertise displayed in his Liber Annālis, though he is most known for his 16 books of letters with Cicero?",
    "answer": "ATTICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In imitation of what work of Varro did Atticus publish an album of great Romans in which each portrait was accompanied by an epigram of 4 or 5 verses?",
    "answer": "HEBDOMADĒS / DĒ IMĀGINIBUS / IMĀGINĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "In what city did Atticus remain for 20 years after leaving Rome at the time of the Sullan proscriptions for reasons of safety?",
    "answer": "ATHENS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the forms baseōs, hērōis, tigrī, and lampados, which does not exemplify a valid genitive singular for a 3rd-declension Greek borrowing?",
    "answer": "TIGRĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following, if any, is not a valid form of the accusative singular: Salamīna, Dīdō, Parin, hērōum?",
    "answer": "HĒRŌUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following, if any, is not a valid genitive form, in the singular or plural: Thūcȳdidī, Georgicōn, crambēs, Dīdūs?",
    "answer": "ALL ARE VALID"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A statue of what deity looked up to heaven in horror when her Trojan sanctuary was violated, after which she took a thunderbolt and struck Oileus’s son Ajax dead for his rape of Cassandra?",
    "answer": "ATHENA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Two suitors of Cassandra joined the Trojan side in the famous war in hopes of winning her hand. For 5 points, name either one. Advanced — Semis",
    "answer": "COROEBUS / OTHRYONEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Cassandra bore Agamemnon two children who were eventually killed by Aegisthus and Clytemnestra. For 5 points, name either one.",
    "answer": "TELEDAMUS / PELOPS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Note: there will be an extra clue. Translate this sentence: “Nisī quis respondēre vult, pergāmus.” Note that pergāmus is a hortatory subjunctive rather than a future less vivid conditional.",
    "answer": "MIXED CONDITIONAL]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate idiomatically the following sentence, which contains an impersonal verb: “Nisī rectē responsum esset, hanc quaestiōnem nōn audīrēmus.”",
    "answer": "[DO NOT ACCEPT “WE WOULD NOT HAVE HEARD”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate this sentence, in which “prōvocāre” means “to challenge”: “Discipulī sciunt sibi prōvocandum fore, nisi dīcant quod in pāginā sit.”",
    "answer": "THEY SAY WHAT IS ON THE PAGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What praenōmen is shared by a man put to death after his plot was exposed by Minucius Augurinus and a man put to death for similar reasons despite negotiating the 493 B.C. foedus Cassiānum?",
    "answer": "SPURIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was the man that killed Spurius Maelius for distributing grain at low prices, acting as either a private citizen or the magister equitum of Cincinnatus?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) SERVILIUS AHALA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was, much later in the Republic, granted a commission to relieve Rome of another grain shortage in 57 B.C., shortly before the Sibylline Books forbade him from gathering an army to restore a king of Egypt? Advanced — Semis Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "POMPEY (“THE GREAT”) // (GNAEUS) POMPEIUS (MAGNUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What island housed a magical garden in which fruit never died, ships that guided themselves without oarsmen, and gold and silver watch-dogs that guarded the palace of Alcinous?",
    "answer": "(ACCEPT DREPANE / CORCYRA / CORFU)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Scheria also housed Medea’s cave, which had originally been home to what woman?",
    "answer": "MACRIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What goddess, who was indirectly referenced by the island’s original name “Drepane”, brought wealth to the island out of fondness for Macris?",
    "answer": "DEMETER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which of the following words, if any, is not derived from the same Latin root as the others: “suzerain,” “overture,” “vertebrate,” “prose,” “varsity”?",
    "answer": "OVERTURE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which of the following words, if any, is not derived from the same Latin noun as the others: “plush,” “pillage,” “pellet,” “peel”?",
    "answer": "PELLET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other derivative of pila describes a small group of soldiers usually commanded by a lieutenant?",
    "answer": "PLATOON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What emperor, who called religious councils at Seleucia and Ariminum, made Constantius Gallus Caesar to defend the East as he headed west to defeat the usurper Magnentius?",
    "answer": "CONSTANTIUS II"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What wife of Constantius II opined on behalf of Julian after his brother Gallus was executed?",
    "answer": "EUSEBIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What brother of Constantius II had Magentius executed to seize the imperial purple?",
    "answer": "CONSTANS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "A collection of maxims in iambic trimeter was compiled from the works of what author, who composed Putātōrēs and Myrmidōn and vied with Decimus Laberius in the genre of mimes?",
    "answer": "PUBLILIUS SYRUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Roman mime tradition took its origins from what festival, held near the end of April?",
    "answer": "LŪDĪ FLŌRĀLĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin name was given to mime actors because they did not wear the raised shoes common to Roman theater?",
    "answer": "PLĀNIPEDĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A sententia of Publilius Syrus reads: “improbē Neptūnum accūsat, quī iterum naufragium facit.” What is the meaning of the noun naufragium, which is derived from navis and frangō?",
    "answer": "SHIPWRECK"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A saying falsely attributed to Publilius reads, “quī aliī maledīcit, sibi convīcium facit.” What is the meaning of convīcium? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "OUTCRY / LOUD NOISE / INSULT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Explain the message of the proverb in the toss-up: “improbē Neptūnum accūsat, quī iterum naufragium facit.” You can do this either by translating it idiomatically or summarizing its meaning.",
    "answer": "CONVEY A CLEAR MEANING]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What region of Greece, from which 150,000 prisoners were taken in 167 B.C., was home to an uncle of Alexander the Great summoned by Tarentum, as well as to their later ally Pyrrhus?",
    "answer": "EPIRUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In 168 B.C., a whirlwind expedition to Illyria had captured what king?",
    "answer": "GENTHIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In 167 or 166 B.C., what island was made a customs-free port and given to Athens in order to reduce the income Rhodes received as a commercial center?",
    "answer": "DELOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What discipline, studied by Serenus Sammonicus, was the subject of the only extant work, in eight books, by an encyclopedist and so-called mediocrī vir ingeniō, Celsus?",
    "answer": "MEDICINE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Celsus was called a mediocrī vir ingeniō by what other author?",
    "answer": "QUINTILIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author from the time of Claudius composed a book of medicinal prescriptions intended for practical use?",
    "answer": "SCRIBONIUS LARGUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen to this passage, describing Laelius’s arrival shortly after the events of the semis passage, and answer the question that follows in Latin: Nūptiīs habitīs supervēnit Laelius, et adeō nōn dissimulāvit sē hoc factum improbāre, ut eam tractāre ut captīvam cōnātus sit. Victus est autem precibus Masinissae, ōrantis ut Scīpiō dēcerneret utrīus rēgis fortūnam Sophonisba habēret. The question: Quid ā Laeliō improbātum est, cum huic reī supervēnisset?",
    "answer": "[PROMPT ON “HOC FACTUM” WITH “PROMPT: QUID FACTUM ERAT?”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Answer in English: in what manner did Laelius present his negative reaction to the marriage?",
    "answer": "OPENLY // WITHOUT HIDING IT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What agreement did Laelius and Massinissa come to in the end? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "FORTUNE} SOPHONISBA WOULD HAVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What name in mythology is shared among a king set adrift in a chest that landed at Oenoe, a son of Andraemon who led 40 ships to Troy, and a king who tried to kill Orestes at Tauria?",
    "answer": "THOAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What descendant of the Aetolian king Thoas later took over the throne of Elis from Dius and invited Agorius to share power with him?",
    "answer": "OXYLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son did Odysseus bear to an unnamed daughter of Thoas son of Andraemon?",
    "answer": "LEONTOPHONUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Place the following provinces in order from west to east: Galatia, Armenia, Dalmatia, and Belgica.",
    "answer": "BELGICA, DALMATIA, GALATIA, ARMENIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Place the following provinces in order from east to west: Noricum, Moesia, Cappadocia, and Raetia.",
    "answer": "CAPPADOCIA, MOESIA, NORICUM, RAETIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Place the following provinces in order from north to south: Thracia, Baetica, Cyrenaica, and Germania Inferior.",
    "answer": "GERMANIA INFERIOR, THRACIA, BAETICA, CYRENAICA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What, if anything, is grammatically infelicitous about the following sentence? “Necāvērunt tribūnum īnsontem omnium crīminum in mediō forī.”",
    "answer": "IT SHOULD BE “IN MEDIŌ FORŌ”"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What, if anything, is grammatically infelicitous about the following sentence: “Deus Sōlis est invictior et cārior imperātōrī Aurēliānō quam ūllī alterī hominī.”",
    "answer": "INVICTUS LACKS A COMPARATIVE FORM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What, if anything, is grammatically infelicitous about the following sentence: “Dux vulnerātum mīlitem ex perīculō ēripuit quō longius vīveret.”",
    "answer": "NOTHING"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A holder of what position has subordinates “ā latere,” is called “servus servōrum,” can speak “urbī et orbī” or “ex cathedrā,” and is reminded “sīc trānsit glōria mundī” when he is crowned?",
    "answer": "(CATHOLIC) POPE // BISHOP OF ROME // PONTIFEX MAXIMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What two-word Latin phrase, containing the name of an animal, refers to Christ as proclaimed by John the Baptist or a medallion blessed by the pope and stamped with that animal’s image?",
    "answer": "AGNUS DEĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give either the two-word Latin phrase that refers to the private meeting to elect a pope or the two-word Latin phrase that refers to the pope’s designation of a cardinal without a public announcement. IĀNUĪS CLAUSĪS or IN PECTORE",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "A so-called forte epos and a didactic Dē Morte were penned by what author, who rejected calls to fill in tibicinēs or make edits when he worked with Plotius Tucca to publish the Aeneid?",
    "answer": "VARIUS RUFUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Varius Rufus also wrote a tragedy with what title? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "THYESTES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Horace’s description of Varius Rufus’s work as a forte epos contrasts with his mockery of what poet as “stuffed with rich tripe” in poems set in Ethiopia and Gaul?",
    "answer": "(M.) FURIUS BIBACULUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Attacks by robbers under Lydius the Isaurian and the revolt of Bonosus occurred during the reign of what emperor, who defeated Florianus to take the throne after Tacitus’s death?",
    "answer": "(MARCUS AURELIUS) PROBUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What position did Probus hold in the army of Aurelian as leader of the Cataphractāriī, one which Aurelian himself held in Gallienus’ army?",
    "answer": "MAGISTER EQUITUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "With what king of Persia, who was overthrown by Narses during Diocletian’s reign, did Probus reach a truce?",
    "answer": "BAHRAM II"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Alxion had one child who pretended to be a woman to reach Daphne and a daughter who murdered her bastard son Chrysippus, both of whom eclipse his deeds as king of Pisa?",
    "answer": "OENOMAUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Identify one figure who is commonly named as Oenomaus’ mother. HARPINA or (A)STEROPE",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Pelops was not the first to compete for Hippodameia’s hand, and Pausanias conveniently gives us all the names of her previous suitors, who all lost the chariot race. Name one of them.",
    "answer": "PELAGON / AEOLIUS / CRONIUS / ERYTHRAS / EIONEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate: “Caesar īnfectō negōtiō, postquam nox aderat, in castra revertitur.” That’s “Caesar īnfectō negōtiō, postquam nox aderat, in castra revertitur.” Here, īnfectus is the negation of factus.",
    "answer": "WITH THE BUSINESS {UNDONE // UNFINISHED}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is unusual about the syntax of this sentence from Sallust: “Haec Maurus sēcum diū volvēns, tandem prōmīsit.”",
    "answer": "PRESENT PARTICIPLE USED FOR AN ACTION THAT IS COMPLETED BEFORE THE MAIN VERB"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence adapted from Sallust: “Nam posteā quid ille fēcerit, incertus sum utrum magis pudeat an pigeat disserere.”",
    "answer": "DISGUSTED TO DESCRIBE WHAT HE DID AFTERWARDS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, the likely ancestor of Tasciovanus, held a stronghold at Wheathampstead captured in 54 B.C. by Caesar during his campaign in Britain, where he was the principal opponent?",
    "answer": "CASSIVELLAUNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What grandson of Tasciovanus, dubbed the champion of Druidism, was defeated by Aulus Plautius and Claudius in battles before being handed over to Rome by the Brigantian queen Cartimandua? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "CARATACUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name the other son of Cunobelinus, who succeeded his father with Caratacus and fought in the two day battle of Medway, dying after it due to his wounds.",
    "answer": "TOGIDUBNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "No flute player could enter the sanctuary of what man, who was accused of making advances on his stepmother Philonome and sent by his father Cycnus to an island near Troy that soon took his name?",
    "answer": "TENES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was the sister of Tenes that, for some reason, was also shipped along with him?",
    "answer": "HEMITHEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Who was the flute player that bore false witness to Philonome’s accusations, and was stoned to death by Cycnus?",
    "answer": "EUMOLPUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who wrote lines where each word gets one syllable longer — a style called “rhopalic” — a Commemorātiō on professors from his hometown of Bordeaux, and most famously the Mosella?",
    "answer": "(DECIMUS MAGNUS) AUSONIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work of Ausonius is a poem composed entirely of rearranged verses from Vergil?",
    "answer": "CENTŌ NŪPTIĀLIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Agamemnon, Achilles, and Ulysses all feature in what work of Ausonius, a set of fictitious tomb inscriptions?",
    "answer": "EPITAPHIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of what case appears in the most common phrase for “to sound a retreat,” in the indeclinable antonym of nēquam — frūgī — and in the phrase auxiliō venīre, followed by a dative of reference?",
    "answer": "DATIVE OF PURPOSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What third-declension neuter word, which lacks an attested genitive plural, is used in an idiomatic double dative construction meaning “is pleasing to”?",
    "answer": "CŌR / CORDĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence adapted from Apuleius, which contains two datives of purpose: “Ad balneum eum dūcō et quod ūnctuī, quod tersuī, ipse praebeō.” Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "FOR OILING AND {CLEANING / RUBBING} OFF"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What word is shared between the fanbase of BTS — the popular K-pop group — and the organization they will have to join for a period of time to serve their mandatory conscription?",
    "answer": "ARMY"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "How many members are in BTS? This is the same number as the number of consulships Marius had.",
    "answer": "7 / SEVEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What group, who often says they’re in your area, are currently touring the US? Moderator should say: “Subsequent questions will count for points. Good luck and have fun!”",
    "answer": "BLACKPINK"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence from Latin to English with the knowledge that colocyntha is a first declension word meaning ‘pumpkin’: Mense Octōbrī sunt quī colocyntham magnam exspectent.",
    "answer": "WHO WAIT FOR THE GREAT PUMPKIN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate: Forsan hōc annō colocyntha magna ā puerīs videātur.",
    "answer": "PERHAPS THIS YEAR THE GREAT PUMPKIN {WILL / MIGHT} BE SEEN BY THE BOYS."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Finally translate: Ūnus calvus ex hīs puerīs exclāmat ‘Ō dolōrem bonum! Nūlla est colocyntha magna!’",
    "answer": "PUMPKIN!’"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Despite a victory at Locus Castorum, what emperor committed suicide to avoid further civil war after he advanced toward Cremona and was defeated by Valens and Caecina, Vitellius’s generals?",
    "answer": "(PUBLIUS SALVIUS) OTHO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Otho’s defeat took place between Cremona and what other city, which he had been using as a base?",
    "answer": "BEDRIACUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After Otho’s death, his troops tried to proclaim what man emperor, who had previously refused the throne after defeating Vindex?",
    "answer": "(LUCIUS) VERGINIUS RUFUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who describes Labrax being shipwrecked, Euclio jealously guarding his wealth, and Pyrgopolynices bragging of his military exploits in Rudēns, Aululāria, and Mīles Glōriōsus, respectively?",
    "answer": "(TITUS MACCIUS) PLAUTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which Plautine character, whose name literally means “weevil,” is the title character of Plautus’s shortest play and steals a ring from another braggart soldier? Advanced — Round 1",
    "answer": "CURCULIO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which Plautine play features Tranio deceiving the merchant Theopropides?",
    "answer": "MOSTELLĀRIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the meaning of the Latin noun laetātiō, which is derived from the deponent verb laetor — formed in turn from laetus?",
    "answer": "JOY / REJOICING"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the meaning of the noun luctātiō, which is derived from the deponent verb luctor?",
    "answer": "WRESTLING / STRUGGLING / CONTEST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the meaning of the noun mētātiō, which is derived from the deponent verb mētor and ultimately from the noun mēta?",
    "answer": "A {MEASURING OUT // SETTING OF A BOUNDARY}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "At the valley of Gargaphia, whose dogs wonder where their master is, even though they had torn him to pieces after he was transformed into a stag?",
    "answer": "ACTAEON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Ovid’s Metamorphoses, the valley was sacred to what goddess, who transformed Actaeon for noticing her bathing?",
    "answer": "DIANA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On what Theban mountain had Actaeon been hunting? This is the same mountain where Oedipus would later be exposed.",
    "answer": "(MOUNT) CITHAERON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Forms of what Latin noun appear at the end of Emory University’s motto, as well as in the mottos of UMich and UChicago — artēs, [blank], vēritās and crēscat [blank], vīta excōlātur?",
    "answer": "SCIENTIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Forms of what Latin noun are contained in the mottos of the Royal Air Force and Kansas?",
    "answer": "ASTRUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Forms of what Latin noun are contained in the mottos of London and the University of Oxford?",
    "answer": "DŌMINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What conflict was indirectly caused by Thurii requesting Roman aid, involved the Roman ambassador Fabricius and the Greek Cineas, and saw battles at Maleventum, Heraclea, and Asculum?",
    "answer": "PYRRHIC WAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Who won the battle of Maleventum and renamed the city to Beneventum?",
    "answer": "(M’.) CURIUS DENTATUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Curius Dentatus also helped end what war, which involved battles at Camerinum and Aquilonia?",
    "answer": "THIRD SAMNITE WAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What group, who came from neighboring islands like Dulichium and Same, comprised 108 men and followed the lead of Eurymachus and Antinous in trying to become the new king of Ithaca?",
    "answer": "SUITORS OF PENELOPE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Just as Odysseus would kill Antinous, what father of his killed Antinous’s father Eupeithes? Advanced — Round 1",
    "answer": "LAERTES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "During his time in Odysseus’s palace, Eurymachus became close with what servant, a sister of one of Odysseus’s herdsmen?",
    "answer": "MELANTHO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Consider the following English sentence: As soon as that was announced to Caesar, he ordered his soldiers to march across the Alps. Translate the phrase “as soon as” into Latin.",
    "answer": "SIMUL {AC / ATQUE} // CUM PRĪMUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "While considering that same sentence – “As soon as that was announced to Caesar, he ordered his soldiers to march across the Alps.” Assuming that the verb for “order” is imperō, translate the verb ‘march’ using an idiomatic phrase.",
    "answer": "ITER FACERENT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate the entire sentence using imperō and the parts you answered already.",
    "answer": "EST, IMPERĀVIT MĪLITIBUS UT TRĀNS ALPĒS ITER FACERENT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author demonstrated how a professional librarian is important for historical research by using the imperial archives under Hadrian to write the Dē Virīs Illustribus and Dē Vītā Caesarum?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) SUETONIUS (TRANQUILLUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name the first and last people who receive a biography in the Dē Vītā Caesarum. JULIUS CAESAR and DOMITIAN, RESPECTIVELY",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What autobiography by Augustus, inscribed on monuments at Ankara and across the empire, was one of the few imperial biographies that predated Suetonius’ Dē Vītā Caesarum?",
    "answer": "RĒS GESTAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin verb with what meaning do we derive “curfew” and “handkerchief,” the latter of which is an object that covers the head?",
    "answer": "OPERIŌ – COVER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Based on its etymology, a curfew signals the time that one would cover what object?",
    "answer": "FOCUS / HEARTH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What derivative of cūra can mean “to clean or brighten the surface of something by rubbing it hard, typically with an abrasive or detergent”?",
    "answer": "SCOUR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following cities was furthest south: Pompeii, Rome, Ostia, Ravenna?",
    "answer": "POMPEII"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following cities was furthest north: Antium, Beneventum, Misenum, or Mediolanum?",
    "answer": "MEDIOLANUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following cities was furthest east: Brundisium, Tarentum, Cumae, or Misenum?",
    "answer": "BRUNDISIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What man, whose grandfather Hostius fought against a Sabine in single combat, himself conducted wars against the Sabines and Alba Longa, razing the latter after the betrayal of its dictator Mettius Fufetius? Advanced — Round 1",
    "answer": "TULLUS HOSTILIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which Sabine, who gave his name to the lake he drowned in, did Tullus Hostilius’ grandfather fight?",
    "answer": "METTIUS CURTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Romulus built a temple to what god with what epithet after that battle?",
    "answer": "JUPITER STATOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What poem, whose ending narrative comes from Thucydides, applies the “honey of the Muses” to the theory of clināmen and expounds Epicurean philosophy in six books by Lucretius?",
    "answer": "DĒ RĒRUM NĀTŪRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What historical event did Lucretius describe in the ending narrative, with Thucydides as his source?",
    "answer": "PLAGUE OF ATHENS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "The opening section of Lucretius’s work uses the death of what mythological woman to support his claim that “religion has been able to advise so many evils”?",
    "answer": "IPHIGEN(E)IA / IPHIANASSA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who married twice in the hopes of fathering a child, eventually doing so in Troezen when he “loosened the wineskin” with Aethra and fathered Theseus?",
    "answer": "AEGEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What half-brother of Aegeus lost his city of Megara because Minos wanted to attack Athens?",
    "answer": "NISUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After the betrayal of his daughter, Nisus was turned into what sort of bird to pursue her?",
    "answer": "OSPREY // SEA EAGLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb secō, secāre, give the second person plural, perfect active subjunctive, given that its 3rd principal part is secuī.",
    "answer": "SECUERĪTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Change that form to the imperfect passive indicative.",
    "answer": "SECĀBĀMINĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Not including compounds, give two other 1st conjugation verbs with -uī in their 3rd principal part.",
    "answer": "VETŌ, MICŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What object, which was originally placed down between 2 quarreling snakes that would entwine it, was furnished with small wings at the tip, and was used to guide the dead by Hermes?",
    "answer": "CADUCEUS / KERYKEION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other object, owned by Hades, did Hermes use to kill the giant Hippolytus?",
    "answer": "{HELM / CAP} OF DARKNESS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Description acceptable. What “objects” did Hermes and Aegipan recover from a cave after Typhon had separated them from their owner?",
    "answer": "SINEWS OF ZEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen to the following passage adapted from Seneca the Younger, which I will read twice, then answer in English the question that follows: Nihil tam damnōsum bonīs mōribus est quam in spectāculō Advanced — Round 1 sedēre; tunc enim per voluptātem facilius vitia ingrediuntur. Quid mē existimās dīcere? Avārior redeō, ambitiōsior, luxuriōsior? Immō vērō crūdēlior et inhūmānior, quia inter hominēs fuī. The question: What is the most dangerous thing for good morals?",
    "answer": "TO SIT {IN / AT} A SPECTACLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give all the bad qualities that Seneca does not become because of spectacles.",
    "answer": "GREEDY, AMBITIOUS, {LUXURIOUS / DECADENT}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the direct cause of the negative qualities that spectacles do instill?",
    "answer": "BEING AMONG PEOPLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work had to be divided into pentads and decades and compressed into Periochae to make sense of its massive bulk, since it covered history up to Augustus in 142 books written by Livy?",
    "answer": "AB URBE CONDITĀ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Asinius Pollio criticized the Ab Urbe Conditā for its provincial stylings, since Livy was born in what town in Cisalpine Gaul?",
    "answer": "PATAVIUM / PADUA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What 4th-century author, at the request of the emperor Valens, wrote a 10-book summary of Roman history that uses Livy for the first six books?",
    "answer": "EUTROPIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When her husband died, her daughters were raped, and she was flogged, who dealt the Romans crippling defeats at Verulamium, Camulodunum, and other British cities until she was brought down in 61 A.D.?",
    "answer": "BOUDICCA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What governor of Britain defeated Boudicca, probably along a road later called Watling Street?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) SUETONIUS PAULINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What woman had earlier rebelled against Rome until she was betrayed by Demetrius of Pharos? Advanced — Round 1 Advanced — Preliminary Round 2",
    "answer": "TEUTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who blamed Attianus for a purge at the beginning of his reign — which saw the death of a star Moorish general, Lusius Quietus — after Pompeia Plotina secured his adoption and his predecessor Trajan died?",
    "answer": "HADRIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Bithynian youth, who died during Hadrian’s tour in Egypt, was Hadrian fond of?",
    "answer": "ANTINOUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Hadrian replaced Lusius Quietus with what man, who quelled a revolt in Mauretania?",
    "answer": "(QUINTUS) MARCIUS TURBO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into English: Malum est discipulīs studendī causā somnum perdere.",
    "answer": "IT IS BAD FOR STUDENTS TO LOSE SLEEP TO STUDY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate this sentence into English: Rogāvī num cēterī discipulī octō hōrās dormīvissent.",
    "answer": "I ASKED IF THE OTHER STUDENTS HAD SLEPT EIGHT HOURS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate this sentence into English: Bene dormiāmus quō quaestiōnibus respondeāmus difficiliōribus.",
    "answer": "LET’S SLEEP WELL SO WE CAN ANSWER HARDER QUESTIONS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What set of twins, one a skilled herdsman, the other a master lyrist, murdered Dirce for harming their mother Antiope and later built the walls of Thebes? AMPHION and ZETHUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Amphion and Zethus had overthrown what regent of Thebes, who ruled while Laius was still a boy?",
    "answer": "LYCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Amphion might have died when he tried to take vengeance on what god, who killed all his sons?",
    "answer": "APOLLO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What subject, whose self-proclaimed praeceptor later described its “remedia,” needed two books for men and one for women to expound its ars in the form of a humorous didactic poem by Ovid?",
    "answer": "LOVE // FALLING IN LOVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other poem by Ovid takes inspiration from Callimachus’s Aetia and describes the origins of Roman festivals over the course of its six books?",
    "answer": "FASTĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What poem by Ovid, named after a type of bird, also takes inspiration from Callimachus for a vicious attack against an unnamed enemy?",
    "answer": "IBIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "In the name “Marcus Livius Augustae L Ismarus” the “L” stands for what Latin word, which describes a person who has donned the conical pilleus after being manumitted?",
    "answer": "LĪBERTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What part of the name was strictly inherited from a freedman’s former master and what part of the name was their own? NŌMEN INHERITED and {COGNŌMEN / AGNŌMEN} THEIR OWN",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the term for the property of an enslaved person that they could use to buy their freedom? Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": "PECŪLIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Though he was accused of adultery with Milo’s wife and governed Africa Nova corruptly, what author from Amiternum took a moralizing tone in his historical monographs, including Bellum Catilīnae?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) SALLUST(IUS CRISPUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What political figure put Sallust in charge of Africa Nova?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) JULIUS CAESAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin term is generally used for Sallust’s technique of asymmetrical and non-parallel clauses?",
    "answer": "INCONCINNITĀS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin noun with what meaning is at the root of “surly,” “sir,” and “senile”?",
    "answer": "SENEX – OLD MAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin noun with what meaning is at the root of “sewer”?",
    "answer": "AQUA – WATER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin verb with what meaning is at the root of “spawn”?",
    "answer": "PANDŌ – SPREAD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What foreign king, who finished his life in luxurious exile at Alba Fucens, defeated the Romans near Larissa at Callinicus in 171 B.C. before being subdued entirely by Aemilius Paullus at Pydna?",
    "answer": "PERSEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Perseus had first come to odds with the Romans when he murdered and supplanted what brother of his, who had been an ally of Rome?",
    "answer": "DEMETRIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Lucius Aemilius Paullus first made his mark in 181 B.C. by defeating the Ingauni in what region of Northern Italy, a favorite ground for ambitious Roman generals in the early 2nd century B.C.?",
    "answer": "LIGURIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a gerundive, translate the following sentence into Latin: What should you avoid?",
    "answer": "QUID TIBI / VŌBĪS (Ē)VĪTANDUM (EST)?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Again using a gerundive, and taking the adjective Harvardiēnsis, Harvardiēnse for “Harvard,” translate: I think that you ought to avoid the Harvard Certamen. CERTĀMEN HARVARDIĒNSE (Ē)VĪTANDUM ESSE {CĒNSEŌ / PUTŌ / CŌGITŌ} vel sim.",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Again using a gerundive, translate: You should learn not for my sake, but for yours!",
    "answer": "[ACCEPT MEĪ / TUĪ, BUT INFORM PLAYERS THAT THE ADJECTIVE IS MORE IDIOMATIC]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What occupation was shared by a man who gave 12 jugs of wine to Odysseus, a man whose daughter Chryseis was kidnapped, and a man who flung a spear at the Trojan Horse?",
    "answer": "PRIEST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was that priest of Apollo that gave Odysseus 12 jugs of wine?",
    "answer": "MARON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to different accounts, Laocoon, the man who flung a spear at the Trojan Horse, was possibly the priest of which two gods? APOLLO and {NEPTUNE / POSEIDON} Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what sort of setting might you hear the phrases particeps crīminis, in flagrante dēlictō, nōlō contendere, and habeās corpus?",
    "answer": "COURT(ROOM) // LEGAL (SETTING) // TRIAL // CASE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the Latin term for a sort of person who volunteers or is invited by the court to give advice on a pending matter?",
    "answer": "AMĪCUS CŪRIAE [PROMPT ON “AMĪCUS”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the Latin term for the order a higher court might give to direct a lower court to perform a legal duty?",
    "answer": "MANDĀMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Supposedly called to invade by Honoria, what man was defeated by Theoderic’s Visigoths and a Roman army at the Mauriac Plains in 451 A.D., showing the excellent generalship of Aetius against the Huns?",
    "answer": "ATILLA (THE HUN)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Honoria is not the only Roman to call a foreign king to invade. According to some scholars, what Vandal king was called in by Boniface to overrun Africa in 429 A.D.?",
    "answer": "GAISERIC / GENSERIC"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Aetius had actually allied with the Huns earlier, when they helped him force what woman — the mother of Valentinian III — to give him a high military position?",
    "answer": "(GALLA) PLACIDIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Though he was the dedicatee of the Dē Clēmentiā and was flattered in the Pharsālia, what emperor forced Lucan and Seneca to commit suicide when they were implicated in the Pisonian Conspiracy?",
    "answer": "NERO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What mediocre poet, whose lengthy Pūnica acts as a fan sequel to the Aeneid, survived Nero’s reign but later distanced himself from his unscrupulous political career?",
    "answer": "(TIBERIUS CATIUS ASCONIUS) SILIUS ITALICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What handsome mythological character, whom Nero seems to have identified closely with, was the hero of a poem that Nero wrote and may have recited during the fire of Rome?",
    "answer": "PARIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What deity punished 5 nymphs for not sacrificing to him, fathered the Sirens, and lost a horn while in the form of a bull during a fight with Hercules?",
    "answer": "ACHELOUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "For whose hand in marriage was Achelous fighting Hercules?",
    "answer": "DEIAN(E)IRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What nymph, whom Achelous fell in love with and seduced, was almost killed by her father until Achelous prayed for her to be transformed into an island?",
    "answer": "PERIMELE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Alvus, sapphirus, quercus, and Aegyptus are second declension nouns that are of what gender?",
    "answer": "FEMININE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Taking the Latin word valē as a noun, say in Latin “a happy goodbye.”",
    "answer": "LAETUM VALĒ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What grammatical term is used for the nouns vās, Mulciber, and iūgerum? Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": "HETEROCLITE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Using adjectives like expolītus and lepidus to describe his libellus, what author mourns his brother’s death in the Troad, writes “ōdī et amō,” and praises the sparrow of his beloved Lesbia?",
    "answer": "CATULLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Lesbia’s real name was Clodia. In which speech of Cicero does he imply that Clodia had incestuous relations with her brother and tried to poison Cicero’s client?",
    "answer": "PRŌ CAELIŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Catullus 65, he uses his brother’s death as an excuse for not sending a fully original poem to what man, a prominent orator in the Asiatic style and rival of Cicero?",
    "answer": "(QUINTUS) HORTENSIUS (HORTALUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After being taken to the camp of the Third Legion ‘Gallica’ by Gannys, what 14-year old Syrian boy was proclaimed emperor by his grandmother Julia Maesa in opposition to Macrinus in 218 A.D.?",
    "answer": "ELAGABALUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name Elagabalus’s mother, who aided him in his ascension to the purple.",
    "answer": "JULIA SOAEMIAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Elagabalus was recognized as emperor throughout the entire empire when troops loyal to him ultimately defeated Macrinus outside what Syrian city on June 8th of that same year?",
    "answer": "ANTIOCH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the genitive can be found when Apuleius writes semper annōrum right after ubique gentium, though more common examples are aliquid nummōrum and satis eloquentiae?",
    "answer": "PARTITIVE / OF THE WHOLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What use of the genitive is found in this Latin phrase from Cicero’s Prō Flaccō? Hermobius, cuius frāter item pecūniae pūblicae est condemnātus.",
    "answer": "CHARGE / PENALTY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the genitive is replaced by an adjective in Sallust’s phrase “metus hostīlis in bonīs artibus cīvitātem retinēbat,” describing Rome’s state before the fall of Carthage?",
    "answer": "OBJECTIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Known as the “hounds of Zeus,” what group did Iris save from the pursuit of Calais and Zetes, explaining that they polluted and snatched the food of Phineus as a punishment?",
    "answer": "HARPIES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How were Iris and the Harpies related?",
    "answer": "SISTERS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Zetes and Calais were perhaps willing to help Phineus because he had married what sister of theirs?",
    "answer": "CLEOPATRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between fundus and profundus — the former being found in the word latifundia and the latter being an adjective. FUNDUS = BOTTOM / FARM / ESTATE and PROFUNDUS = DEEP / PROFOUND",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now provide the meaning of the word funda, which would be used with lapidēs and tormenta. Advanced — Round 2",
    "answer": "SLING(SHOT)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between the adverbs funditus and dīvīnitus. FUNDITUS – FROM THE BOTTOM and DĪVĪNITUS – FROM HEAVEN / BY DIVINE Advanced — Round 2 Advanced — Preliminary Round 3",
    "answer": "PROVIDENCE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Our source for Sallust’s birth year and Lucretius’s love potion is the Chronicon of what Christian author, a native of Stridon who went to Bethlehem and learned Hebrew to translate the Bible?",
    "answer": "CHRONICON” AND PROMPT ON “CHRONICON” BEFORE THE TITLE IS READ]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In a dream, Jerome was reproached by God with the phrase “[blank] es, nōn Christiānus.” Fill in the blank with the Latin or English.",
    "answer": "CICERŌNIĀNUS / CICERONIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Jerome served for a time as secretary for what pope?",
    "answer": "(POPE) DAMASUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the verb “build” from the following sentence into Latin: There is nobody who can stop us from building our city. Note that one option involves a subjunctive verb in the present tense.",
    "answer": "MŪNIĀMUS / MŪNĪRE / MŪNIENDŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the first clause of the following sentence into Latin using only two words: After the walls had been built, the enemy decided to dig under our moat instead.",
    "answer": "MŪRĪS MŪNĪTĪS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the verb “build” from this sentence into Latin: If we had built the walls deep underground, the enemy would not have been able to so easily sack the city.",
    "answer": "MUNĪ(VI)SSĒMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "An eagle signaled the birth of what man, who stood a head taller than all other Greeks at Troy, where his massive shield served to protect his half-brother Teucer and a man from Locris who shared his name?",
    "answer": "AJAX THE GREAT(ER) // {GARGANTUAN / BIG / LARGE / HUGE} AJAX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Book 7 of the Iliad, Hector gives Ajax what object, which would appear in his story later?",
    "answer": "(SILVER-STUDDED) SWORD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The duel only came to a halt due to the calls of what two heralds, one Greek and one Trojan?",
    "answer": "TALTHYBIUS & IDAEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "“Moriāmur, et in media arma ruāmus,” meaning “Let us die, and charge into the thick of the fight,” is a famous example of what literary device whose name means “following preceding”?",
    "answer": "HYSTERON PROTERON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What literary device, excluding sound effects, can be found in the line “miserō quod omnīs ēripit sēnsūs mihi,” given that the normal word order of miserō and mihi in the sentence is distorted?",
    "answer": "HYPERBATON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What literary device, excluding sound effects, can be found in this sentence drawn from Quintilian, “emit morte immortālitātem,” seeing that multiple words derived from the same root have been used in close proximity?",
    "answer": "FIGURA ETYMOLOGICA // POLYPTOTON"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Though he had earlier dropped the fold of his toga that symbolized war, what man feuded with Minucius Rufus, his magister equitum, in 217 B.C. when he repeatedly delayed battle against Hannibal? Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": "(QUINTUS) FABIUS MAXIMUS (CUNCTATOR)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two consuls of 216 B.C. did Fabius Maximus try in vain to persuade to continue his strategy? (C. TERENTIUS) VARRO and (L. AEMILIUS) PAULLUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "When sealed off between a mountain pass, Hannibal evaded capture by Fabius Maximus by creating a dummy army using what animals?",
    "answer": "OXEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Sometimes called “dubitative,” what independent use of the subjunctive can be found in the sentences “etiamne eam salūtem” and “cur tibi loquar”?",
    "answer": "DELIBERATIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the sentence “quō mē verterem?,” which contains a deliberative subjunctive.",
    "answer": "WHERE {SHOULD I HAVE TURNED // WAS I TO TURN} (MYSELF)?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the subjunctive is found in the sentence “Biennium perīculum erat nē nihil reī pūblicae superesset”?",
    "answer": "FEARING"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Consolidated into new barracks under Tiberius, disbanded by Constantine, and led by men like Laetus and Tigellinus, what group killed Pertinax, Caligula, and other emperors they were supposed to protect?",
    "answer": "PRAETORIAN GUARD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Praetorian Guard consisted exclusively of Italians until what emperor replaced them with troops drawn from the legions, ensuring its loyalty before he fought his rivals at Issus and Lugdunum?",
    "answer": "(LUCIUS) SEPTIMIUS SEVERUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The immediate impetus for Septimius Severus’s decision may have been the auction for the throne that the Praetorian Guard had held between Didius Julianus and what man?",
    "answer": "(TITUS FLAVIUS CLAUDIUS) SULPICIANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work’s so-called tibicinēs, or half-lines of hexameter, help explain why Plotius Tucca and Varius Rufus were charged with burning its 12 books of epic poetry on the order of its author, Vergil?",
    "answer": "AENEID"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Vergil’s first major example of epic narration is an inset epyllion in the 4th book of the Georgics about what mythological figure, which in turn contains the inset tale of Orpheus and Eurydice?",
    "answer": "ARISTAEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Some later sources say, though scholars doubt this, that the Aristaeus tale was added to replace praises of what disgraced elegiac poet?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) CORNELIUS GALLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following Latin sentence into English: Nec deōs nec hominēs crēdō tibi nocēre posse.",
    "answer": "I {THINK / BELIEVE} NEITHER GODS NOR MEN CAN HARM YOU"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following Latin sentence into English: Crēderēs nēminem esse ā quō comminus vulnerārī possēs.",
    "answer": "YOU COULD BE WOUNDED {IN CLOSE COMBAT // HAND-TO-HAND}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Identify both the independent and dependent uses of the subjunctive found in that sentence. POTENTIAL and RELATIVE CLAUSE {OF CHARACTERISTIC / IN INDIRECT STATEMENT} Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What king falsely announced his intention to vie for the hand of Hippodameia, requiring horses for his bride gift from all the citizens of Seriphos, including the new resident Perseus?",
    "answer": "POLYDECTES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name both the brother of Polydectes and the woman whom he was truly intent on marrying.",
    "answer": "DICTYS & DANAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was Perseus’ original name, under which he was raised in Dictys’ home?",
    "answer": "EURYMEDON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What barbarian, although admitted to the equester ordo for his service in the Roman army, sprung a trap between the Weser and Ems rivers in 9 A.D. that ensnared 3 legions under Quinctilius Varus?",
    "answer": "ARMINIUS / HERMAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Germanic tribe did Arminius hail from?",
    "answer": "CHERUSCI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Another revolt around this time involved two Pannonian chieftains who shared what name?",
    "answer": "BATO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What broad geographical feature is signified by all of the following terms: stagnum, fretum, aequor, amnis?",
    "answer": "(BODIES OF) WATER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What article of clothing do all of the following words denote specific variations of: mitra, apex, causia, petasus?",
    "answer": "HAT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whereabouts can the following objects be found: mentum, māxilla, cilium, gingīva?",
    "answer": "SOMEONE’S HEAD [PROMPT ON “BODY”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the Aeneid, who was forced to hide in the Aventine Hill due to a bull’s cry, after he had covered the tracks of the cattle of Geryon which he had stolen from Hercules?",
    "answer": "CACUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "This story was mentioned to Aeneas by what man who was sacrificing to Hercules right before graciously welcoming Aeneas?",
    "answer": "EVANDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Evander also mentions how Tarchon had sent a crown and scepter to him to succeed what cruel man as king of Etrurian Argylla?",
    "answer": "MEZENTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin word form fills in the blanks of the names of the ancient counterparts of Aix-en-Provence and Bath — [blank] Sextiae and [blank] Sulis?",
    "answer": "AQUAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Forms of what emperor’s name fill in the blanks of the names of the ancient cities [blank] Taurīnōrum and [blank] Trēverōrum?",
    "answer": "AUGUSTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What modern city once named after the Roman imperial family did the Romans call Colōnia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium? Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": "COLOGNE / KÖLN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, whose suffect consulship in 100 A.D. saw him deliver a Panēgyricus, asked Trajan how to treat Christians in one of his Epistulae, which also describe a volcanic eruption?",
    "answer": "PLINY THE YOUNGER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Pliny’s letter about the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius describes the death of Pliny the Elder. What was their familial relationship?",
    "answer": "UNCLE / NEPHEW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "One of Pliny’s letters mentions how Tacitus delivered the funeral oration for what man, whom he replaced as consul in 97 A.D.?",
    "answer": "(LUCIUS) VERGINIUS RUFUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What law, which took effect after Acilius Glabrio’s temporary command in the East, was defended by Cicero and completed Lucullus’s replacement with Pompey in the Third Mithridatic War?",
    "answer": "LĒX MĀNĪLIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "One of Lucullus’s major victories took place in 69 B.C. at what city, whose king remarked that Lucullus’s forces were “too few for an army, too many for an embassy”?",
    "answer": "TIGRANOCERTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Lucullus was undermined by what brother-in-law of his, who deliberately chose a plebeian spelling of his nōmen?",
    "answer": "(PUBLIUS) CLODIUS PULCHER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What part of speech encompasses the ultimate Latin roots of all of the following English words: “estranged,” “souffle,” “entrails,” and “ulterior”?",
    "answer": "PREPOSITION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What part of speech encompasses the Latin roots of “umpire” and “maxim”?",
    "answer": "ADVERB // ADJECTIVE // ADVERB AND ADJECTIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What particular grammatical characteristic is shared by the Latin nouns at the roots of “ferial” and “delicious”?",
    "answer": "PLŪRĀLIA TANTUM // ONLY APPEAR IN THE PLURAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Eupalamus was tried for murdering a boy that rivaled his skill — Perdix — and ended up on Crete where he made a wooden cow for Pasiphae as well as the Labyrinth?",
    "answer": "DAEDALUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Daedalus took refuge on Sicily with Cocalus, where he was able to thread a shell using what animal, who traversed the tortuous windings of the shell?",
    "answer": "ANT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Daedalus notably built a temple to Apollo in what city, near Lake Avernus?",
    "answer": "CUMAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two third declension nouns are used in a pair of similar Vergilian phrases in which each one is said to “conquer all”? AMOR and LABOR Advanced — Round 3",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Vergilian line that features “omnia vincit amor” goes on to say “et nōs cēdāmus amōrī.” Please translate that continuation into English.",
    "answer": "LET US TOO YIELD TO LOVE // AND LET US YIELD TO {IT / LOVE}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the Eclogues, Vergil writes “magnus ab integrō saeclōrum nāscitur ōrdō” about the coming of a second Golden Age. Where does the three-word adaptation of this quote appear in the US?",
    "answer": "ON THE (GREAT) SEAL // ON THE {DOLLAR / 1$} BILL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "The line “I never poetize unless I have the gout” is attributed to what “three-hearted” author, whose Hedyphagetica and 18-book historical epic Annālēs introduced dactylic hexameter to Rome?",
    "answer": "(QUINTUS) ENNIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was the meaning of Ennius’s claim that he had three hearts?",
    "answer": "HE COULD SPEAK THREE LANGUAGES (GREEK, LATIN, OSCAN)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Ennius’s love of alliteration can be seen in a line addressed to what figure in his Annālēs, telling him “tūte tibi tanta, tyranne, tulistī”? Advanced — Round 3 Advanced — Semifinals",
    "answer": "TITUS TATIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "A poem on the phoenix is ascribed to what Christian author, who studied under Arnobius, tutored Crispus, and attempted to systematize Christian doctrine in the Divine Institutions?",
    "answer": "(LUCIUS CAELIUS FIRMIANUS) LACTANTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where did Diocletian appoint Lactantius to teach rhetoric until the Great Persecution?",
    "answer": "NICOMEDIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the title of Arnobius’s pro-Christian treatise, which makes up in vehemence for what it lacks in accurate knowledge of Christianity?",
    "answer": "ADVERSUS NĀTIŌNĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What woman, raped by Jupiter and granted immortal life, transformed into Camers to reignite the battle between the Latins and Trojans and into Metiscus to help her brother flee Aeneas?",
    "answer": "JUTURNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In book 10 of the Aeneid, Juno helped Turnus flee Aeneas and brought him to what city of his?",
    "answer": "ARDEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Juturna reigniting the fight indirectly caused what seer to cast his spear and kill a son of Gylippus?",
    "answer": "TOLUMNIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Identify the use of the accusative in the following sentence: Nōnne ipsum caput et supercilia olēre malitiam et clāmitāre calliditātem videntur? Keep in mind that clāmitāre is normally intransitive.",
    "answer": "COGNATE / INTERNAL / KINDRED SIGNIFICATION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Identify the only use of the accusative in these lines from Vergil’s Aeneid: omnia Mercuriō similis, vōcemque colōremque / et crīnīs flāvōs et membra decōra iuventā.",
    "answer": "SYNECDOCHICAL / GREEK ACCUSATIVE / RESPECT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Identify the use of the genitive in the phrase id temporis.",
    "answer": "PARTITIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What two regions did Rome seize in the aftermath of the Truceless War and combine into their second province after Sicily, entirely robbing the Carthaginians of their island possessions near Italy? SARDINIA and CORSICA",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following provinces was NOT added during the reign of Claudius: Britannia, Thrace, Pannonia, Mauretania?",
    "answer": "PANNONIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What emperor split up many of the provinces, increasing the total number from around 40 to around 105, and then grouped them into larger units supervised by vicāriī?",
    "answer": "DIOCLETIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin noun is the “p” in the abbreviations s.l.p. and s.m.p., in which the middle words are “legitimā” and “masculā,” and in the abbreviation d.s.p.?",
    "answer": "PROLĒS / PROLĒ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin and English equivalent of the phrase coch. parv.",
    "answer": "COCHLEĀR(E) PARVUM – A TEASPOONFUL / SMALL SPOON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin and English for the symbol represented by the letter C with a line above it (c̅). Advanced — Semifinals",
    "answer": "CUM – WITH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man rode with Baton, his charioteer, away from the pursuing Theban Periclymenus until Zeus struck the ground to swallow them up, fulfilling his prophecy of his own death?",
    "answer": "AMPHIARAUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other member of the Seven Against Thebes might have received divine aid, had he not desecrated Melanippus’s body at Amphiaraus’s instigation?",
    "answer": "TYDEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Argive son of Alector helped Polynices get Amphiaraus to join his expedition?",
    "answer": "IPHIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen to the following passage, which I will read twice, adapted from Claudius’s arrival to heaven in the Apocolocyntōsis, where he is met by Hercules. Answer in English the question that follows: Cum novī generis faciem vīdisset, Herculēs perturbātus est, et putāvit sibi tertium decimum labōrem vēnisse. Tamen accessit et ait: “Quis es, aut unde venīs?” Claudius Homēricō versū respondit. Tum Herculēs “Dā mihi vērum,” inquit, “nē tibi fatuitātem excutiam.” The question: What did Hercules think had come to him when he saw Claudius?",
    "answer": "HIS THIRTEENTH LABOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Why did Hercules think Claudius was being a fool?",
    "answer": "CLAUDIUS REPLIED TO HIM {IN GREEK // IN A HOMERIC VERSE}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What did Hercules threaten to do if Claudius didn’t tell him the truth about his origin?",
    "answer": "{SHAKE / KNOCK} OUT HIS FOOLISHNESS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author depicts a man condemned to indigestion, proclaims that he brings forth his poetry ex praecordiīs, and describes a journey to Sicily, inspiring Horace and Juvenal with his Satires?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) LUCILIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What mistress of Lucilius is the focus of the 16th book of his Satires?",
    "answer": "COLLYRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the name of the man condemned to indigestion in the Concilium Deōrum?",
    "answer": "(LUCIUS CORNELIUS) LENTULUS LUPUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Take the phrase quaedam nais fōrmōsa and give its plural accusative form.",
    "answer": "QUĀSDAM NAIDAS FŌRMŌSĀS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the genitive singular of the phrase nūllus gurges ātrōx.",
    "answer": "NŪLLĪUS GURGITIS ATRŌCIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the accusative singular of the noun Salamīs.",
    "answer": "SALAMĪNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "The decisive victor at a battle near Tauromenium, what Republican admiral turned pirate captain was not placated by a conference at Misenum and soon lost to Agrippa in 36 B.C. at Naulochus?",
    "answer": "SEXTUS POMPEY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where did the triumvirs meet in 40 B.C. to re-cement their alliance? Advanced — Semifinals",
    "answer": "BRUNDISIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "During this campaign, Agrippa constructed the Portus Iulius to enable him to train naval crews in what lake?",
    "answer": "(LAKE) AVERNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in derivation between “contempt” and “attempt.” CONTEMPT - TEMNŌ (DESPISE) and ATTEMPT - {TEMPTŌ (TRY) / TENDŌ (STRETCH)}",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in etymology between “peel” and “appeal.” The first is related to the shape that peelings make. PEEL - PILUS (HAIR) and APPEAL - PELLŌ (PUSH / DRIVE) / APPELLŌ (NAME / ADDRESS)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in etymology between “decoy” and “coy.” DECOY - CAVEA (CAGE) and COY - QUIĒS (REST)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What ancient river, along whose shores a Roman traveler would find Nemausus, Arausio, and other cities of southern Gaul, is now called the Rhone?",
    "answer": "RHŌDANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Along the shores of what river would a Roman traveler find the cities Carnuntum, Vindabona, and Aquincum?",
    "answer": "DANUBE / DANUVIUS / ISTER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Along the shores of what river would a Roman traveler find the city Perusia?",
    "answer": "TIBER / TIBERIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What emperor could not stop the mutilation of Parthenius and the execution of Petronius Secundus after the praetorians besieged the palace and demanded the death of his predecessor’s assassins in 97 A.D.?",
    "answer": "NERVA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What commander of the Praetorian Guard led the hunt for the conspirators, imprisoning Nerva in the imperial palace until they had their way?",
    "answer": "CASPERIUS AELIANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Although it was hard for Nerva to find favor with the praetorians, he was heavily supported by the senate and received what title upon his ascension, which Augustus had previously received in 2 B.C.?",
    "answer": "PATER PATRIAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What man, sent to unknowingly kill his father in a cell at Mycenae, had to watch his mother Pelopia commit suicide before he returned to kill Atreus and finally avenge his father Thyestes?",
    "answer": "AEGISTHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Why did Pelopia commit suicide?",
    "answer": "SHE FOUND OUT SHE HAD A SON (AEGISTHUS) BY HER OWN FATHER (THYESTES)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Aegisthus caused his own death by ignoring the warnings of what god not to seduce Clytemnestra?",
    "answer": "HERMES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Forced to earn his sportula as a client, cultivate a tiny farm at Nomentum, and ask Pliny the Younger to pay for his trip home, who tried to “spare the persons, addressing their vices” in 15 books of epigrams? Advanced — Semifinals",
    "answer": "(MARCUS VALERIUS) MARTIAL(IS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Flavian epic poet, who sang of fraternae aciēs, was similarly forced to earn extra money by composing a libretto to a pantomime entitled Agāvē?",
    "answer": "(PUBLIUS PAPINIUS) STATIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Martial jokes that his farm at Nomentum was so small it could fit under the wing of what animal?",
    "answer": "CRICKET / CICADA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What event saw the rejection of the term heteroousios, the setting of a fixed date for Easter Sunday, and the burning of Arius’s writings in 325 A.D. after Constantine called together the empire’s bishops?",
    "answer": "COUNCIL OF NICAEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what Roman province in Asia Minor was Nicaea located?",
    "answer": "BITHYNIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In 451 A.D., at what other city in Asia Minor did Marcian, Pulcheria, and Pope Leo I call together the Fourth Ecumenical Council in an attempt to resolve the issue of Christ’s nature?",
    "answer": "CHALCEDON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into Latin using a subjunctive: “The soldier will hide the spears from the general lest he expect his death.”",
    "answer": "PRAEVIDEAT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate into Latin using a clause of proviso: “So long as I am king, let him threaten me with a stone in vain.”",
    "answer": "{FRŪSTRĀ / NĒQUĪQUAM} MINĒTUR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate into Latin using a subjunctive: “She hopes that she will see the sudden light.”",
    "answer": "SPĒRAT FORE UT VIDEAT LUCEM SUBITAM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author wrote about a flatterer in the Colax and a coquettish girl in the Tarentilla, claimed that it was fate that made the Metelli consuls, and composed a seven-book Saturnian historical epic?",
    "answer": "(GNAEUS) NAEVIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To what city was Naevius exiled for making this claim about the Metelli?",
    "answer": "UTICA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Though Naevius is known for inventing the fābula praetexta, some plays, such as Ariolus, seem to have been comedies in a Roman setting. What is the Latin term for such plays?",
    "answer": "FĀBULA {TOGĀTA / TABERNĀRIA}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who is the father of all the following? A daughter who married Bias, Pero; a shapeshifting son who died as an eagle, Periclymenus; and a son who spear-vaulted away from the Calydonian Boar, Nestor?",
    "answer": "NELEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Bias was able to marry Pero because Melampus got the cattle of what man, whose son Iphiclus he cured of impotence?",
    "answer": "PHYLACUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Nestor was the only surviving son of Neleus after Pylos was sacked because he was in what city? Advanced — Semifinals",
    "answer": "GERENIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate this sentence adapted from Seneca the Younger, found in a discussion of old age: Sī deus crāstīnum diem adiēcerit, laetī recipiāmus.",
    "answer": "[SEE BELOW]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give another translation of that sentence, interpreting the conditional differently.",
    "answer": "2: IF GOD {SHOULD GIVE // WERE TO GIVE} (US) A TOMORROW, WE WOULD HAPPILY TAKE IT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence, adapted from the preface of Seneca’s Quaestiōnēs Nātūrālēs: tantum inter philosophiam et cēterās artēs interest, quantum inter Deum et hominem. Advanced — Semifinals Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "THERE IS BETWEEN GOD AND MAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Described in one poem as “omnia nostrae tempora laetitiae,” who replaced Lycinna as the poet’s beloved, was distinguished for her ocellī, and was the chief subject of the Monobiblos?",
    "answer": "CYNTHIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Just as Lycinna was a lesser-known love interest of Propertius, Horace mentions Tibullus’s unhappy love for what woman, who never appears in his elegies?",
    "answer": "GLYCERA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The couplet that ends “omnia tū nostrae tempora laetitiae” begins “You alone are my [blank], Cynthia, you alone my [blank].” Fill in one of those blanks in English or Latin. DOMUS / HOME or PARENTĒS / PARENTS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Eastern emperor helped his co-ruler create dēfēnsōrēs cīvitātis and suppressed Procopius’s revolt, but died in battle after officials at the Danube bungled the admission of a host of Gothic refugees?",
    "answer": "VALENS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Valens also tried to restore Rome’s prestige on the Persian front after Jovian had surrendered what key fortress city to Shapur?",
    "answer": "NISIBIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In an especially striking example of the mistreatment of the Gothic refugees, Ammianus mentions that officials provided them with what sort of bad food in exchange for Gothic slaves?",
    "answer": "DOG MEAT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Known throughout Oechalia for her beauty, what woman was raped by Apollo and forced to bear a child named Amphissus, whom she had to leave behind after she became a lotus tree?",
    "answer": "DRYOPE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Dryope naturally kept her pregnancy a secret and soon afterwards married what mortal?",
    "answer": "ANDRAEMON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Antoninus Liberalis’s account, Apollo came to Dryope in the form of what animal?",
    "answer": "TORTOISE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What meaning is shared by all of the following words: caterva, turma, coetus, manus?",
    "answer": "CROWD / GROUP / MULTITUDE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What adjective meaning “dense” comes from the same root as a Latin verb meaning “to grow”?",
    "answer": "CRĒBER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give a meaning of the Latin verb conciliō, which is derived from the Latin noun concilium, meaning “council.”",
    "answer": "UNITE / WIN OVER / PROCURE / CONCILIATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence adapted from Cicero’s Dē Rēpublicā: Nōn satis est habēre virtūtem quasi artem, nisi utāre. Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "UNLESS YOU (ARE TO) MAKE USE OF IT."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence adapted from Cicero’s Dē Officiīs: Nē dubitēmus, quīn hominēs hominibus et prōsint et obsint plūrimum.",
    "answer": "BENEFIT AND HARM TO HUMANS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence adapted from Cicero’s Dē Ōrātōre: Quis est quī, sī clārōrum hominum scientiam arbitrētur, nōn antepōnat ōrātōrī imperātōrem?",
    "answer": "HE WERE TO JUDGE THE KNOWLEDGE OF DISTINGUISHED MEN?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What structure featured rows that ran horizontally and vertically, a podium for some sarcophagi, and niches for up to 1000 urns to store the mostly cremated remains of a family?",
    "answer": "COLUMBĀRIUM / COLUMBĀRIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where would you go to first have remains cremated before taking them to the columbārium?",
    "answer": "USTRĪNA(E)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the Latin term for the urns that populated the columbārium?",
    "answer": "ŌLLAE (OSSUĀRIAE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "A georgic inspired by Hesiod, a poetic calendar in twenty-seven books called Annālēs, and a praetexta on the sacrifice of Decius Mus are all minor works of what prolific tragedian from Pisaurum?",
    "answer": "ACCIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work of Accius, composed in nine books of mixed prose and verse, proposed a series of spelling reforms?",
    "answer": "DIDASCALI(C)A"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author dedicated his grammatical work Dē Antīquitāte Litterārum to Accius?",
    "answer": "(MARCUS TERENTIUS) VARRO REATINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After your doctor prescribes griseofulvin, you become jaundiced from elevated bilirubin levels. Under what general category of meaning do the roots of “griseofulvin,” “jaundice,” and “bilirubin” belong?",
    "answer": "COLOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What peculiarity is shared by the Latin roots of “parcel” and “couch”?",
    "answer": "DIFFERENT MEANINGS IN SINGULAR AND PLURAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What grammatical distinction is shared by the Latin nouns at the root of the infectious diseases “impetigo” and “lues”?",
    "answer": "TRIPTOTE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What war saw Aesernia and Venusia fall into enemy hands, twelve populī transfer a 500-member rival Senate to Bovianum, and Lucius Cato and Lucius Caesar fight against the likes of Papius Mutilus?",
    "answer": "SOCIAL WAR / MARSIC WAR / ITALIAN WAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "In a precursor to the Social War a generation earlier, what city in the Liris valley rebelled after the Senate pushed Fulvius Flaccus aside and sent him to Gaul?",
    "answer": "FREGELLAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What consul of 122 B.C., a son-in-law of Laelius and enemy of Gaius Gracchus, spoke out against another attempt to pass a bill enfranchising the Italians? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) FANNIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of animal was given a voice to argue about the sizes of certain organs before being beaten to death, ate the straw rope that Ocnus ceaselessly plaited, and inspired the ears that Apollo gave to Midas?",
    "answer": "ASS / DONKEY / DONKEY (SHREK)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What fertility god lost the argument to the donkey, and beat it to death?",
    "answer": "PRIAPUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What mythological group was said to have fled in fear of the braying of asses that Dionysus brought to the battle?",
    "answer": "GIANTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Augustus told Crassus’s grandson that what 5th-century man had been a consul, not a military tribune, when he dedicated in the temple of Jupiter Feretrius the panoply of a king of Veii, Lars Tolumnius?",
    "answer": "(AULUS CORNELIUS) COSSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Previous to his encounter with Cossus, Tolumnius had lost to a consul from what gēns, which would suffer humiliation in the 1st century B.C. when one of its members led a conspiracy in Rome?",
    "answer": "SERGII / (GĒNS) SERGIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Augustus had an interest in proving that Cossus was a consul because he wanted to deny Crassus the spolia opīma for his victory over the king of what tribe?",
    "answer": "BASTARNAE / BASTARNIANS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What dialogue, beginning with a description of boys skipping stones on the shores of Ostia, features Januarius and Caecilius Natalis debating Christianity with its author, Minucius Felix, as umpire?",
    "answer": "OCTAVIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "At one point, Caecilius Natalis mentions a speech by “our fellow native of Cirta,” referring to a recent attack on Christianity by what orator and letter-writer?",
    "answer": "(MARCUS CORNELIUS) FRONTO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The dispute begins when Octavius Januarius notices Natalis venerating a statue of what deity, a combination of Osiris and Apis?",
    "answer": "SERAPIS / SARAPIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "“Why are you laughing? Change the name and this story is about you” is a quote from what author, who also advocates choosing the golden middle path and mentions that even good Homer sleeps?",
    "answer": "HORACE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin for “this story is about you” in the first quote.",
    "answer": "DĒ TĒ FĀBULA NARRĀTUR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Fill in the blanks for this quote of Horace which would properly describe a movie underperforming expectations: parturient [blank], nāscētur rīdiculus [blank].",
    "answer": "MONTĒS, MŪS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What group sought refuge with Ceyx and then Theseus before sacrificing one of their own — Macaria — to ensure that Hyllus could kill their ancestral tormenter Eurystheus? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "HERACLIDS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After defeating Eurystheus, the Heraclids decided to conquer the Peloponnese and it took three tries. Hyllus died in the first expedition after dueling what king of Arcadia?",
    "answer": "ECHEMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give one of the explanations for how Aristodemus died in the second expedition. LIGHTNING BOLT or APOLLO KILLED HIM (WITH AN ARROW) or SONS OF PYLADES & ELECTRA",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into Latin using a future imperative: “Make war with the Carthiginians tomorrow so that we may rest today.”",
    "answer": "QUIĒSCĀMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into Latin using an imperative form of the verb faciō: “See to it that I become emperor at Rome within five days.”",
    "answer": "FAC(ITŌ) UT QUĪNQUE DIĒBUS IMPERĀTOR RŌMAE FĪAM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into Latin using the verb caveō with the most classical construction: “Don’t be lazy, my friends, even if I haven’t gotten up yet.”",
    "answer": "CAVĒ PIGRĪ / IGNĀVĪ SITIS, MĪ AMĪCĪ, ET(IAM)SĪ (EGŌ) NŌNDUM SURREXĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Listen to the following passage, which I will read twice, adapted from Claudius’s journey down towards hell in the Apocolocyntōsis. Answer in English the question that follows: Claudius ut vīdit fūnus suum, intellexit sē mortuum esse. Ingentī enim chorō nēnia anapaestīs cantābātur: “Fundite flētūs, ēdite planctūs, resonet tristī clāmōre forum: cecidit pulchrē cordātus homō.” Dēlectābātur laudibus suīs Claudius, et cupiēbat diūtius spectāre, sed Mercūrius eum dētrahit capite obvolūtō. The question: How is Claudius described in the last line of his funeral lamentation, cecidit pulchrē cordātus homō?",
    "answer": "(A MAN) BEAUTIFULLY {HEARTED / WISE} // HAVING A BEAUTIFUL HEART"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What meter was Claudius’s funeral lamentation sung in?",
    "answer": "ANAP(A)ESTS / ANAP(A)ESTIC"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What did Mercury do to Claudius before dragging him away?",
    "answer": "{COVERED / WRAPPED} HIS HEAD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Who advocated for verba ūsitāta and exhorted writers to avoid unusual words “as a steersman avoids a reef” in a 54 B.C. treatise on linguistic theories written while crossing the Alps — the Dē Analogiā?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) JULIUS CAESAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two-book pamphlet did Caesar compose as a response to Cicero’s elogium of a famous republican hero?",
    "answer": "ANTICATŌ(NĒS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What youthful poem did Caesar compose in praise of a hero who undertook such labors as killing the Nemean lion and cleaning the stables of Augeas?",
    "answer": "LAUDĒS HERCULIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The Latin words nummum, superum, and dīvom are all alternate forms in what case and number? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "GENITIVE PLURAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The Latin adverbs prīdiē and hodiē emerged from what fifth declension noun case form?",
    "answer": "LOCATIVE (SINGULAR)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Other than quibus, give an alternate dative or ablative plural form of the relative pronoun.",
    "answer": "QUĪS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What name is shared among a 65 B.C. censor who opposed his co-censor Crassus, a man whose autobiography described fighting the Cimbri with Marius, and the man who ended the 1st Punic War?",
    "answer": "LUTATIUS CATULUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "This first Lutatius Catulus, a staunch optimate, was also Caesar’s chief rival in the 63 B.C. elections for what position?",
    "answer": "PONTIFEX MAXIMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The peace treaty that C. Lutatius Catulus helped broker removed the Carthaginians from what Sicilian city, which had still not fallen to Rome?",
    "answer": "LILYBAEUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What region was home to the king who hacked his son Dryas to death, Lycurgus, the ghost of a boy who haunted a bloody bush, Polydorus, and the god that kidnapped Oreithyia, Boreas?",
    "answer": "THRACE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man also died in Thrace at the hands of the Ciconian women?",
    "answer": "ORPHEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Thrace was also home to what god of the Getae, who received messengers that were tossed onto a set of three spears? Advanced — Finals",
    "answer": "SALMOXIS / ZALMOXIS / GEBELZEIZIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, who spent a year teaching at Marquette High School in Wisconsin, attended Yale University, where he obtained a Masters in Classics that he often employed in producing his one-division tournament “K2”?",
    "answer": "MICHAEL KEARNEY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What protege of Michael Kearney, a current pre-med and Classics major at Yale University, is this year’s advanced finals moderator?",
    "answer": "MATTHEW THOMAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What up and coming Yale CS student, also a former mythologian for the Massachusetts advanced division team in 2020, is this year’s intermediate finals moderator? Moderator should inform the players that the questions after this will count for points.",
    "answer": "JIN(WOO) KIM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What meaning is shared by the nouns verecundia and pudor?",
    "answer": "MODESTY / SHAME / SHYNESS / BASHFULNESS [ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin noun meaning “weariness” is derived from the verb taedet?",
    "answer": "TAEDIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin noun meaning “freedom” is derived from the verb licet?",
    "answer": "LICENTIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was criticized by Caesar in an epigram for lacking vīs cōmica and being a dīmidiātus Menander, and by his contemporaries for contāminātiō in his 6 comedies?",
    "answer": "TERENCE // (P.) TERENTIUS (AFER)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Because Terence had been brought to Rome as an enslaved person, many people believed one of two prominent Romans wrote his comedies for him. Name either. (P. CORNELIUS) SCIPIO AEMILIANUS or (C.) LAELIUS (SAPIENS)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A legend probably invented to connect Terence with his comic predecessors says that Terence read the draft of his Andria to what great comic playwright and friend of Ennius for approval?",
    "answer": "CAECILIUS STATIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who — following in his brothers’ footsteps of settling lands like Thasus, Cilicia, and Phoenicia — came to southern Boeotia where he killed a serpent and sacrificed the cow he had followed?",
    "answer": "CADMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was special about the cow Cadmus had followed?",
    "answer": "IT HAD MARKINGS LIKE FULL MOONS ON ITS SIDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To what Phoenician goddess, associated with Athena, did Cadmus sacrifice the cow?",
    "answer": "ONCA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What emperor — who was forced to deal with two Egyptian pretenders, including Domitius Domitianus — attempted to clamp down on inflation with the “Edict on Maximum Prices” and reorganized the empire into a tetrarchy?",
    "answer": "DIOCLETIAN / DIOCLES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What co-emperor of his did Diocletian send to lead the army against the Persian king Narses?",
    "answer": "GALERIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To what Croatian location did Diocletian retire in 305 AD, as he preferred cultivating cabbages to governing his realm?",
    "answer": "SALONA / SPLIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the full Latin for what is commonly considered the highest academic degree, which terminates in a dissertation before a committee and is abbreviated PhD.",
    "answer": "PHILOSOPHIAE DOCTOR // DOCTOR PHILOSOPHIAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin for the two ranks of university honors above cum laude. MAGNĀ CUM LAUDE and SUMMĀ CUM LAUDE [ACCEPT EITHER ORDER]",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin for the M.A. and the J.D., two other high degrees. MAGISTER ARTIUM and IŪRIS / JŪRIS DOCTOR",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using two irregular verbs, say in Latin: “Why are you carrying books which will become food?”",
    "answer": "CŪR FERS LIBRŌS {QUĪ {CIBUS / CIBĪ} FĪENT // {CIBUM / CIBŌS} FUTŪRŌS}?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using the verb abeō, say in Latin: “I will avoid my tasks by leaving.”",
    "answer": "ABEUNDŌ {NEGŌTIA MEA // MŪNERA MEA // LABŌRĒS MEŌS} VITĀBŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using the verb ōdī, say in Latin: “Do the men I see standing in the forum hate you?”",
    "answer": "ANY WORD]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What prose work, structured almost entirely as a direct address to God, recounts events including the birth of Adeodatus and the piety of Monica, the mother of its author Augustine?",
    "answer": "CONFESSIONS / CŌNFESSIŌNĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "About what now-lost work of Cicero does Augustine write “but that book changed my feelings and turned my prayers towards you, Lord”?",
    "answer": "HORTĒNSIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In a moment of great spiritual crisis, Augustine heard “a voice, as if that of a boy or girl, chanting and repeating again and again” what phrase, encouraging him to open up the Bible? Either the two-word Latin phrase or an English translation is acceptable.",
    "answer": "TOLLE, LEGE // TAKE AND READ // PICK (IT) UP AND READ (IT)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After claiming to have fled home because his father had turned his tyranny from the Romans to his own family, what man was accepted into Gabii and executed the city’s nobles, allowing it to be taken by his father, Tarquinius Superbus?",
    "answer": "SEXTUS TARQUIN(IUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Not trusting the messenger, how did Superbus signal Sextus to execute Gabii’s nobles?",
    "answer": "[ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What other son of Superbus commanded the Etruscan cavalry at the Battle of Silva Arsia, where he died?",
    "answer": "ARRUNS (TARQUIN(IUS))"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What inseparable duo worked together to deny Salius a victory in the foot-race during the funeral game of Anchises and to gather information on the Latin forces in a night raid? NISUS and EURYALUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What had caused Nisus to trip before he subsequently tripped Salius?",
    "answer": "BLOOD (OF RECENTLY SACRIFICED BULL(OCK)S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin leader led a pursuit of Nisus and Euryalus, eventually killing Euryalus before he was in turn killed by Nisus?",
    "answer": "VOLCENS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "For the phrase quoddam calcar, give the ablative singular, keeping in mind that calcar is a neuter i-stem.",
    "answer": "QUŌDAM CALCĀRĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Change quōdam calcārī to the genitive plural.",
    "answer": "QUŌRUNDAM CALCĀRIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Using terribilis, give the genitive plural for the phrase “certain very frightful winters.”",
    "answer": "QUĀRUNDAM TERRIBILISSIMĀRUM {HIEMUM / BRŪMĀRUM}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What modern-day country, where a poet erected statues to himself instead of Augustus while serving as prefect, was the site of Juvenal’s banishment and a group of Greek philological scholars based in a famous library?",
    "answer": "EGYPT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Name that poet, an elegist whose Amōrēs sang the praises of Lycoris, the pseudonym of the actress Volumnia.",
    "answer": "(CORNELIUS) GALLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Roman poet imitated the style of the Alexandrian scholars with his learned epyllion Zmyrna, though he was torn to pieces in the confusion following Caesar’s death?",
    "answer": "(C. HELVIUS) CINNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "If a time traveller went to the city of Rome during the Late Republic, where would they be if they saw the Temple of Castor & Pollux and a collection of prows decorating a speaker’s platform?",
    "answer": "FORUM RŌMĀNUM // ROMAN FORUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where would they be if they saw the temple of Mars Ultor?",
    "answer": "FORUM OF AUGUSTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where would they be if they saw an altar to Hercules?",
    "answer": "FORUM BOĀRIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Only an ambidextrous Paeonian named Asteropaeüs was able to wound what man, who battles the god of the corpse-choked Scamander during his return to fighting in the Iliad?",
    "answer": "ACHILLES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Scamander was finally fed up with Achilles and began to attack him, what Olympian stepped in and stopped Scamander completely?",
    "answer": "HEPHAESTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "At the same time as Achilles is tearing it up on the battlefield, various gods are also duking it out. Whom did Hera smack on the ear with their own weapon for daring to challenge her?",
    "answer": "ARTEMIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Latin words meaning “a narrow pass” and “ambush” share what grammatical peculiarity along with words for “riches” and “weapons” — dīvitiae and arma?",
    "answer": "ONLY FOUND IN PLURAL // PLŪRĀLIA TANTUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Latin words meaning “hunger,” “distaff,” and “house” share what grammatical peculiarity?",
    "answer": "VARY IN DECLENSION // HETEROCLITES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The Latin words exsul, bōs, and parēns share what grammatical peculiarity?",
    "answer": "EITHER MASCULINE OR FEMININE // COMMON GENDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What conflict, immediately after which Libyan natives revolted in the so-called “Truceless War,” included a Spartan mercenary’s victory at Bagradas Valley and a Carthaginian naval victory at Drepana?",
    "answer": "FIRST PUNIC WAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What Carthaginian leader’s “greatness” failed to earn him a win in the Truceless War or at Aegates Islands?",
    "answer": "HANNO (THE GREAT)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "To attempt to pay back the debt they owed after the First Punic War, the Carthaginians entered Spain in search of silver. What city, founded by Hasdrubal, served as the capital of their Spanish empire, though it fell to Scipio Africanus via amphibious assault in 209 B.C.?",
    "answer": "CARTHĀGŌ NOVA // NEW CARTHAGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Note to players: There will be an extra clue after the sentence. Translate into English: Utinam nē bonī virī proeliō vīcissent! Note that the word utinam means “if only.”",
    "answer": "{WOULD THAT // IF ONLY} THE GOOD MEN HAD NOT WON (IN) THE BATTLE!"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into English: Hērōibus mortuīs, nunc est tempus scelera faciendī et domōs incendendī!",
    "answer": "{FOR COMMITTING CRIMES AND BURNING HOUSES // TO COMMIT…}! [ACCEPT EQUIVS.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Change the phrase scelera faciendī et domōs incendendī to use gerundives rather than gerunds.",
    "answer": "SCELERUM FACIENDŌRUM ET {DOMUUM / DOMŌRUM} INCENDENDĀRUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author asserted his divine descent in a funeral oration for his aunt, although he is more known for his unfinished work on the civil wars, and most famously his 8-book Commentāriī on the Gallic wars?",
    "answer": "(C. JULIUS) CAESAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Caesar’s Commentāriī Dē Bellō Gallicō was also unfinished, but the eighth book was added by which of Caesar’s lieutenants?",
    "answer": "AULUS HIRTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Aulus Hirtius is also believed to have written what work on Caesar’s campaigns in Egypt during the civil war?",
    "answer": "BELLUM ALEXANDRĪNUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who performed a sacrifice to the dryads after learning from the sea-god Proteus that because he had chased Eurydice to her death, the dryads went and killed all his bees?",
    "answer": "ARISTAEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was the mother of Aristaeus whom Apollo saw wrestling a lion on Mt. Pelion?",
    "answer": "CYRENE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How did Aristaeus learn that he had successfully appeased the dryads?",
    "answer": "SACRIFICED TO BE BUZZING WITH BEES"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What modern holiday’s name derives from three Latin words — the name of the Roman god of war, the word from which we derive “journal” and “diary,” and the word crassus, meaning “fat”?",
    "answer": "MARDI GRAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What modern holiday’s name derives from a verb meaning “to be strong”?",
    "answer": "VALENTINE’S DAY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "“Indigenous Peoples’ Day” has recently replaced “Columbus Day” as a holiday in many states. Give the Latin words, as well as their meanings, from which “indigenous” and “Columbus” are derived. {INDIGENA – NATIVE // GIGNŌ – BEGET} and COLUMBA / COLUMBUS – (MALE /",
    "answer": "FEMALE) DOVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Note to players: A description is acceptable. What concept, with versions known as per magistratum and sine suffrāgiō, was the subject of the Lēx Plautia Papīria, which helped end the Social War by granting a right that had been continually denied to the Italians?",
    "answer": "CITIZENSHIP / ENFRANCHISEMENT / CĪVITĀS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What tribune of 91 B.C., whose murder touched off the Social War, was the last Roman to unsuccessfully propose the enfranchisement of the Italians?",
    "answer": "(M.) LIVIUS DRUSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What city was destroyed in 125 B.C. by Lucius Opimius in an early conflict over citizenship rights? Advanced – Preliminary Round 2 Moderator should say: “I will now read one test question for no points. This question does not necessarily reflect the difficulty of the round that follows.”",
    "answer": "FREGELLAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of dog, which has a pronounced mandibular prognathism, was used in fighting with other animals and is also the mascot of Yale University?",
    "answer": "BULLDOG(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "The bulldogs are also the mascot of Yale’s football team, which plays an annual game against what other Ivy league?",
    "answer": "HARVARD (UNIVERSITY)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What dean of Harvard College is a professor of sociology that seemingly spends a lot of his time using his Instagram to share pictures of events at Harvard? Moderator should inform the players that the questions after this will count for points.",
    "answer": "(DEAN RAKESH) KHURANA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following words, if any, does not share its derivation with the others: eager, peregrine, pilgrim, agrestic? ",
    "answer": "EAGER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "After the death of his mentor, Damasus, what author left Rome for Bethlehem, where he learned the Hebrew necessary to translate the Old Testament into Latin in the first part of the Vulgate?",
    "answer": "(ST.) JEROME // (SOPHRONIUS EUSEBIUS) HIERONYMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was Jerome called by God in a dream, despite insisting that he was a Christian?",
    "answer": "CICERŌNIĀNUS // (A) CICERONIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Jerome had previously consulted the Hexapla, containing several different Greek translations of the Hebrew text, compiled by what author? He later feuded with Rufinus over the validity of that same author’s doctrine.",
    "answer": "ORIGEN(ES)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "If you’ve ever played a video game (which if you haven’t – seriously what are you doing with your life), you’ll know that every boss, no matter how big and scary, usually has a weakness, whether it’s its giant flaming eye, its mouth, or its head. Similarly, what beast, despite his gigantic size and fearsome physiology, apparently had a digestive weakness to cake — sops — which Psyche and Aeneas both exploited when they visited the Underworld to get past him?",
    "answer": "CERBERUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Aeneas knew about the cake trick not from any online game walkthrough (like most of us have probably done with video game bosses) but through the advice of what old prophetess?",
    "answer": "CUMAEAN SIBYL // DEIPHOBE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Psyche learned about the cake exploit from what usually-inanimate-but-in-Greek-mythologyapparently-not object?",
    "answer": "A (TALKING) TOWER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What sort of institution, usually located in a pergula, could receive a generous payment called a honorarium and saw pedisequi and paedagogi accompany kids to sit before a litterator or grammaticus?",
    "answer": "SCHOOL / LUDUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On what month and day would the school year begin?",
    "answer": "MARCH 24TH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What was the Latin term for the market days that were also holidays for schools?",
    "answer": "NUNDINAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What cognōmen is shared by a man who opposed Cato in senatorial debates before the Third Punic War and a Pontifex Maximus who led a mob in the Capitoline in 133 B.C. to kill Tiberius Gracchus, both of whom had the moniker Nasica?",
    "answer": "SCĪPIŌ (NĀSĪCA) [ACCEPT “NĀSĪCA” ALONE BEFORE IT IS READ]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Scipio Nasica Serapio — the younger of the two — was shuffled off the stage of history in 132 B.C. when he was sent on embassy to what city, which Rome had peacefully acquired the previous year?",
    "answer": "PERGAMUM / PERGAMON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Scipio Nasica Corculum — the elder of the two — was the son of a prominent general during the Second Punic War. Name this man and his brother, who both perished at the battle of Upper Baetis in PUBLIUS SCIPIO and GNAEUS SCIPIO",
    "answer": "211 B.C.?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Note to players: There will be an extra clue after the sentence. Translate the subordinate clause of this sentence into good Latin: “We choose to preserve the welfare of the state lest anyone be poor.” Know that the word aliquis, meaning “anyone,” drops the ali- after this conjunction.",
    "answer": "NĒ QUIS PAUPER SIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into Latin, knowing that the conjunction of the subordinate clause enacts the same change in aliquis: “If anyone should deny it, he would be deceiving you.”",
    "answer": "SĪ QUIS (ID) NEGET, FALLAT {TĒ / VŌS}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into Latin: “Guard the hostages, lest they escape anywhere.”",
    "answer": "OBSIDĒS {SERVĀ(TE) / CUSTŌDĪ(TE)} NĒ QUŌ (EF)FUGIANT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Perimele and five other nymphs were transformed into the Echinades Islands by what king of rivers, who came in three shapes to ask Oeneus for Deianeira’s hand before wrestling Heracles?",
    "answer": "ACHELOUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Book 8 of Ovid’s Metamorphoses, Achelous details these stories to Lelex and Theseus on their way back from what event, which saw Echion throw the first spear, Telamon trip on a tree root, and Nestor pole-vault to safety?",
    "answer": "CALYDONIAN BOAR HUNT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who came to the mouth of the Achelous River where he found new land formed by alluvial deposits that bypassed his mother Eriphyle’s curse?",
    "answer": "ALCM(A)EON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What irregular verb, one of whose compounds is a neutral passive verb meaning “to be sold,” fills in the blank in the quote “sīc [blank] ad astra” and lies at the root of “sedition” and “initial”?",
    "answer": "EŌ / ĪRE [PROMPT ON ĪTUR WITH “CAN YOU GIVE THE BASE FORM?”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What irregular verb lacks a present active participle until late Latin and has a possible alternate form for the future active infinitive?",
    "answer": "SUM / ESSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What irregular verb almost exactly follows first-conjugation patterns except that the -a- in most forms is short?",
    "answer": "DŌ / DARE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After ordering a massacre of ardent chariot racing fans in Thessalonica, what emperor served the public penance ordered by Bishop Ambrose, who may have convinced him to outlaw the Olympic games and paganism?",
    "answer": "THEODOSIUS {I // THE GREAT}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Ambrose also convinced the emperor Gratian to remove what object from the Cūria?",
    "answer": "ALTAR OF VICTORY // ĀRA VICTŌRIAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What half-Vandalic general was left in effective control of the western empire upon Theodosius’s death in 395 A.D.?",
    "answer": "STILICHO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Works of what genre were composed in honor of Claudius Marcellus and Fulvius Nobilior, celebrating their victories at Clastidium and Ambracia in the form of tragedies with a Roman theme?",
    "answer": "THEME” BEFORE “TRAGEDIES” IS READ]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Clastidium and Ambracia were written by Naevius and Ennius, respectively. Each of them also wrote one other praetexta. Name one. ROMULUS or SABĪNAE",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What type of fābula is named for a style of high Greek footwear and is also known as crepidāta?",
    "answer": "(FĀBULA) COTHURNĀTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "With what frequency should one take a medicine labeled q.h., given that its unabbreviated form is quāque hōrā?",
    "answer": "EVERY HOUR // HOURLY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A 17th century formal text called the “Medical Institutions” describes the fundamental principle of modern medicine as being that contrāria contrāriīs cūrantur. Translate this phrase.",
    "answer": "OPPOSITES ARE CURED BY OPPOSITES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between the medical abbreviations o.s. and a.s.",
    "answer": "(IN THE) LEFT EYE // (IN THE) LEFT EAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "During what war did an 11-day march by Marcius Philippus make up for Publius Crassus’s initial defeat and lead to the 168 B.C. battle of Pydna against Perseus, which forever ended the power of the kingdom once ruled by Alexander the Great?",
    "answer": "THIRD MACEDONIAN WAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What region, which had once been ruled by Pyrrhus, did Aemilius Paullus order to be devastated by Roman troops following the defeat of Perseus?",
    "answer": "EPIRUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "At what battle did Publius Crassus suffer this initial defeat in 171 B.C.?",
    "answer": "LARISSA / CALLINICUS [DO NOT ACCEPT “CALLICINUS”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The second work in what collection was circulated privately in writing due to its vitriol, though its other 13 speeches were actually delivered by Cicero in the manner of Demosthenes’s attacks on Philip II?",
    "answer": "PHILIPPICS / ANTŌNIĀNAE / PHILIPPICAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other set of speeches from early in Cicero’s career, which are valuable for our knowledge of the artwork on Sicily, was also divided into two parts, the second of which was never delivered?",
    "answer": "IN VERREM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which speech of Cicero was not delivered as he intended due to his fear, leading it to be one of his rare losses in a judicial case?",
    "answer": "PRŌ MILŌNE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What island was home to two different figures named Asterius? One was a king who married a woman brought to his island by a white cow. The other was a monster born from the union of Pasiphae and a bull.",
    "answer": "CRETE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name that woman who married king Asterius and brought up three famous sons with him.",
    "answer": "EUROPA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What giant, who had been presented to Europa as a present from Zeus, ran around the entire island of Crete three times a day to protect it from invaders?",
    "answer": "TALUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which of the following four Latin verbs is not synonymous with niteō: lūceō, fulgeō, candeō, palleō?",
    "answer": "PALLEŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Excluding the verbs listed in the tossup, as well as compounds of those verbs, give another synonym of niteō.",
    "answer": "SPLENDEŌ / MICŌ / CORUSCŌ / ĀRDEŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give a second-conjugation Latin verb that means “to be sad.”",
    "answer": "MAEREŌ / DOLEŌ / LUGEŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who helped Odysseus marry his niece Penelope in exchange for Odysseus’s advice to have all his daughter’s suitors vow to support whoever would marry her, which caused big problems when his daughter — Helen — was abducted?",
    "answer": "TYNDAREUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How many ships did Odysseus’s advice launch to save Helen, originating a famous phrase?",
    "answer": "A THOUSAND // 1000"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Despite having suggested this, Odysseus tried to feign madness and avoid fulfilling this oath until what son of Nauplius put Telemachus before his plow?",
    "answer": "PALAMEDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Note to players: There will be an extra clue after the sentence. Translate the sentence “Mārius proficiscitur urbem magnam captum,” keeping in mind that captum is an accusative supine and thus expresses purpose.",
    "answer": "MARIUS SETS OUT TO CAPTURE THE LARGE CITY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Why is the sentence “Mārius ariēte ūtēbātur mūrōs dēlētum” grammatically non-standard?",
    "answer": "TO EXPRESS PURPOSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate the sentence “Postquam hī convēnērunt, incrēdibile dictū est quam facile sociī factī sint.”",
    "answer": "EASILY THEY BECAME ALLIES"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Aulus Postumius Tubertus won a victory at what site in 431 B.C., almost 30 years after a battle at the same site where Minucius Esquilinus was saved from the Aequi by Cincinnatus?",
    "answer": "(MT.) ALGIDUS [ACCEPT “ALGIDUS PASS”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What priests, imported from the Aequi by Ancus Marcius, threw spears into enemy territory to formally declare war?",
    "answer": "FĒTIĀLĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Cincinnatus was once again made dictator in 439 B.C. to kill what man, who was suspected of attempting a coup d’etat by personally relieving a grain shortage?",
    "answer": "(SP.) MAELIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The phrases “fugiēbant aliī, sed aliī resistēbant” and “satis eloquentiae, sapientiae parum” both demonstrate what literary device, in which words are arranged in an ABBA pattern?",
    "answer": "CHIASM(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What literary device is found in this sentence: “Pauperem in villam suam rēcipere nōn dēdignātus est”?",
    "answer": "LITOTES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Besides rhetorical questions, identify two literary devices in the following sentence: “Domestica bona pudīcitiae, obsequiī, cōmitātis, facilitātis, lānificiī, studiī cūr memorem?” ASYNDETON and {PRAETERITIO / PRETERITION / APOPHASIS}",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Two epicēdīa, one for Marcellus and one for Cornelia, appear in the poetry of what self-described “Roman Callimachus,” who addressed the opening Monobiblos of his four books of elegies to Cynthia?",
    "answer": "(SEX.) PROPERTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What other woman, alongside Nemesis and Marathus, appears in the poetry of another elegiac poet roughly contemporary with Propertius?",
    "answer": "DELIA / PLANIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What man was the patron for that other elegiac poet, Tibullus, but not for Propertius or Vergil? Advanced – Preliminary Round 3 Moderator should say: “I will now read one test question for no points. This question does not necessarily reflect the difficulty of the round that follows.”",
    "answer": "(M. VALERIUS) MESSALLA CORVINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What city, known for its pizza, was founded in 1638 by English Puritans and in recent years has welcomed over 60 teams from all over the country to play the first collegiate tournament of the year at Yale?",
    "answer": "NEW HAVEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Italian city is home to the world’s largest pizza, which was prepared in 2012?",
    "answer": "ROME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The city of Rome is known for speaking what ancient language that may be tested in this round? Moderator should inform the players that the questions after this will count for points.",
    "answer": "LATIN // ANCIENT GREEK"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What emperor secured his reign by defeating rivals at Cyzicus and Lugdunum, then ended it just short of Caledonia with his death at Eboracum, leaving the empire to Geta and Caracalla?",
    "answer": "(L.) SEPTIMIUS SEVERUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Early in Severus’s reign, he overhauled the Praetorian Guard, perhaps because of what prefect, who had presided over Didius Julianus’s bidding war and had conspired with Eclectus and Marcia to kill Commodus?",
    "answer": "(Q. AEMILIUS) LAETUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What compromise did Septimius Severus make with one of his rivals, Clodius Albinus, so that he could focus first on defeating Pescennius Niger? A description is fine.",
    "answer": "DECLARED ALBINUS {CAESAR // JUNIOR EMPEROR}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate into Latin, using a passive periphrastic: “I will need to work tomorrow.”",
    "answer": "CRĀS MIHI LABŌRANDUM ERIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate into Latin, again using a passive periphrastic and the word cum: “I also need to help you, since you are my friend.”",
    "answer": "TŪ QUOQUE MIHI (AD)IŪVANDUS ES, CUM AMĪCUS MEUS SĪS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate into Latin: “The teacher feared that the students were not going to work with great enthusiasm.”",
    "answer": "DISCIPULĪ/-AE {LABŌRĀTŪRĪ/-AE ESSENT // LABŌRĀRENT} MAGNŌ CUM STUDIŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What hero fought various peoples including the Solymi, the Amazons, and eventually the Lycians since his taskmaster Iobates could not figure out how to kill him if the Chimaera couldn’t?",
    "answer": "BELLEROPHON(TES)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "In a stunning and idiotic display of hubris, Bellerophon flew to Olympus on Pegasus, only to be kicked off when what animal bit Pegasus?",
    "answer": "GADFLY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Though Bellerophon lived on being hated by the gods, he was still the father of three children by what daughter of Iobates?",
    "answer": "PHILONOE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work highlights Quintus Caedicius’s deeds, gets its title because it covers the founding of various Italian cities, was the first work of history in Latin prose, and was penned by Cato the Elder?",
    "answer": "ORĪGINĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In which of his works did Cato give advice to his son, including the maxim “have the contents clear, and the words will come of themselves” — “rem tenē, verba sequentur”?",
    "answer": "PRAECEPTAAD FĪLIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What 1st-century B.C. author wrote a Life of Cato as part of his Dē Virīs Illūstribus, which also included biographies of foreign commanders, most famously Hannibal?",
    "answer": "CORNELIUS NEPOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following provinces was furthest north: Belgica, Baetica, Asia, Aquitania?",
    "answer": "BELGICA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of those three provinces did not border the same body of water as the other three?",
    "answer": "ASIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which two of those provinces lie wholly or partially within the borders of the same modern country? BELGICA and AQUITANIA",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author recommends moistening the hand to feign tears, among many other scandalous pieces of advice, in a 3-book mock-didactic poem in elegiac couplets, the Ars Amātōria?",
    "answer": "OVID"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Ovid was quite the fellow when it came to matters of love. What work of his was a handbook on how to fall out of love, rather than how to fall in love?",
    "answer": "REMEDIAAMŌRIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which work of Ovid provides a wealth of useful antiquarian information, but was left unfinished, with only six out of twelve books completed?",
    "answer": "FASTĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin noun, which lies at the root of both the Spanish word “adios” and the French word “adieu,” appears in the motto of Arizona, ditat [blank]?",
    "answer": "DEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The Spanish word “sombrero” — like the English word “somber” — derives from what Latin noun with what meaning?",
    "answer": "UMBRA – SHADE / SHADOW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Spanish word “tostada” — a deep-fried or toasted flat tortilla covered in toppings — derives from what Latin verb with what meaning?",
    "answer": "TORREŌ / TORRĒRE – (TO / I) BURN / DRY UP / ROAST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of people were defeated by Quintus Caecilius Metellus in the Balearic Isles and near Cilicia by a general whom the Lēx Gabīnia empowered to hunt in the Mediterranean basin, Pompey?",
    "answer": "PIRATES"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Rome fought pirates in the First Illyrian War after what ruler of Illyria ordered a Roman envoy to be killed?",
    "answer": "TEUTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Mediterranean needed to be cleared of piracy due to the failure of what ex-praetor, who was defeated by Cretan pirates in 72 B.C. and thus earned the cognōmen “Creticus”?",
    "answer": "(M.) ANTONIUS (CRETICUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: “Multa perīcula passī, tandem domī maneāmus.”",
    "answer": "HAVING SUFFERED MANY DANGERS, LET US FINALLY REMAIN AT HOME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate the following sentence: “Eōdem ūsī cōnsiliō, fīnēs vōbīscum relinquēmus.”",
    "answer": "TERRITORY WITH YOU (ALL)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate the following sentence: “Nīl sine nūmine accidere rātī, deō grātiās agere dēcrēvimus.”",
    "answer": "WILL}, WE DECIDED TO {GIVE THANKS TO // THANK} GOD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What people were ruled by a queen who officiated the marriage between Jason and Medea, as well as a king who ordered the bard Demodocus to change his song to stop Odysseus’s crying?",
    "answer": "PHAEACIAN(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What had Nausicaa set out to do when she ran into the nude Odysseus?",
    "answer": "WASH HER CLOTHES // DO LAUNDRY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Euboean nymph is said to have raised Dionysus in the cave where Arete officiated the wedding?",
    "answer": "MACRIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author gives us all of the following quotes: “lēgēs sine mōribus vānae,” “ōdī profānum vulgus et arceō,” “exēgī monumentum āere perennius,” and “carpe diem”?",
    "answer": "HORACE // (Q. HORATIUS) FLACCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What university has taken the first quote from this question, “lēgēs sine mōribus vānae,” as its motto?",
    "answer": "UNIVERSITY OF PENNSYLVANIA // UPENN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What phrase does Horace use, literally translating to “the golden mean,” to promote avoiding both extremes in any situation?",
    "answer": "AUREA MEDIOCRITĀS // AUREAM MEDIOCRITĀTEM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A ruler of what kingdom described an approaching Roman force as “too few for an army, too many for an embassy” prior to a 69 B.C. battle in which Licinius Lucullus took his capital of Tigranocerta?",
    "answer": "ARMENIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was this arrogant king of Armenia?",
    "answer": "TIGRANES {I // THE GREAT} [PROMPT ON “TIGRANES”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Lucullus’s actions in Armenia comprised one theater of what larger conflict that lasted from 74 to 66",
    "answer": "THIRD MITHRIDATIC WAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "A consul in 68 A.D, what author so admired Vergil that he bought the man’s tomb and followed the Aeneid closely in his own work, though the result — his 17-book epic Pūnica — is often judged as one of the worst works of Latin literature?",
    "answer": "(TIB. CATIUS ASCONIUS) SILIUS ITALICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What other poet likely admired Vergil, but structured his epic poem in opposition to Vergil, removing any divine intervention and refusing to make anyone an epic hero?",
    "answer": "(M. ANNAEUS) LUCAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Silius Italicus died in 101 A.D., choosing to kill himself by what method after contracting an incurable disease?",
    "answer": "STARVATION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Note to players, a description is acceptable. What group of animals died on Mount Olympus while wandering back to Thrace, the land where they had consumed their own master during Heracles’s 8th labor?",
    "answer": "MARES OF DIOMEDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What youth was killed by the mares of Diomedes while watching over them for Heracles?",
    "answer": "ABDERUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What war-like people of Thrace was Diomedes the king of?",
    "answer": "BISTONES / BISTONIANS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The sentences “tēlō ictus est ut stāre nōn posset,” “mīrābilis adeō, ut amor hūmānī generis dīcerētur,” and “tam pulchra est ut omnēs eam ament,” all exemplify what type of subjunctive clause?",
    "answer": "RESULT CLAUSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the sentence “mīrābilis adeō, ut amor hūmānī generis dīcerētur” into English.",
    "answer": "THE LOVE OF HUMANKIND [ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate the sentence “tēlō ictus est ut stāre nōn posset” into English.",
    "answer": "STAND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whose military service under the patronage of Pomponius Secundus inspired his Bella Germāniae and introduced him to Titus, to whom he dedicated his compilation of all knowledge in 37 books, the Nāturālis Historia?",
    "answer": "PLINY THE ELDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who drew on the lost Bella Germāniae as one of the sources for his own ethnographic work Dē Orīgine et Sitū Germānōrum?",
    "answer": "(P. CORNELIUS) TACITUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Pliny also authored a monograph on fighting in what style?",
    "answer": "(HURLING SPEARS) ON HORSEBACK"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Roman commander, who secured the betrothal of his son Gaudentius to Galla Placidia the Younger, forced the Huns to withdraw from Gaul through his victory at Catalaunian Plains in 451 A.D.?",
    "answer": "AETIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Two years after Aetius’s success in Gaul, the city of Rome itself was saved from Attila’s destructive wrath through the timely diplomacy of what Pope?",
    "answer": "(POPE) LEO {I // THE GREAT}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the 420s A.D., Aetius burst onto the scene of history by leading a force of Huns in defense of what Italian usurper based at Ravenna?",
    "answer": "JOHN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of the words fēlēs, ursa, ovis, and piscis, which is being described in the following sentences: tondētur hūius pilus et in vestēs mūtātur. Hoc animal etiam herbam cōnsūmit et bālat — id est “BAAA” dīcit.",
    "answer": "OVIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the words fēlēs, ursa, piscis, and sīmia, which is being described in the following sentence: Hoc animal, cadēns, semper pedibus rēctīs terram attingit.",
    "answer": "FĒLĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the words cervus, leopardus, būbō, and taurus, which is being described in these lines of poetry? Sternit silvās rūpēsque lacessit īrātō rabidus cornū.",
    "answer": "TAURUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Holders of what title, first held by Phemonoë, were often described to be chewing leaves of laurel and were positioned next to the Omphalos stone as vapors rose from a cleft underneath her sacred tripod?",
    "answer": "PYTHIA / DELPHIC ORACLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Near Delphi was the spring Telphusa, whose waters supposedly killed what seer that was traveling with his daughter Manto?",
    "answer": "T(E)IRESIAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In exchange for the island of Calaureia, which Olympic god willingly gave up his share of the Delphic Oracle to Apollo?",
    "answer": "POSEIDON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What meaning is shared by the words dīmidia pars, sēmis, and dīmidium, which are all fractions?",
    "answer": "ONE-HALF"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate into Latin the fraction for “one third”.",
    "answer": "TERTIA PARS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate into Latin the fraction for “two thirds” using only one word. Advanced – Semifinals",
    "answer": "BES(SIS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Originally the caretakers of the temple of Ceres, what political office in Rome was given the additional responsibilities of administering the corn dole, public games, and public works projects?",
    "answer": "AEDILES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What political body conducted the elections of both aediles during the early republic?",
    "answer": "CONCILIUM PLEBIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man’s aedileship involved an exhibition of 320 pairs of gladiators and the unveiling of gleaming gold statues of Marius?",
    "answer": "(C. JULIUS) CAESAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "When the main clause is negated, what Latin conjunction can introduce result clauses or clauses of characteristic in place of ut nōn or quī nōn, but more often follows nōn dubitō?",
    "answer": "QUĪN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When a clause of characteristic takes on a causal sense, it is often introduced by one of three words. Give one. UT or UTPOTE or QUIPPE",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the sentence “tantum enim abest ut istum laudem, ut nēminem nēquiōrem esse dīcam,” identify, in order, the type of clause introduced by each ut. SUBSTANTIVE RESULT and (ADVERBIAL) RESULT (RESPECTIVELY)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who threw himself off of Mount Parnassus in a fit of grief over the loss of his daughter before being transformed into a hawk by Apollo?",
    "answer": "DAEDALION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name the daughter of Daedalion, who was raped by both Apollo and Hermes on the same day, and died when she boasted she was more beautiful than Artemis.",
    "answer": "CHIONE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Daedalion’s family was beset on all sides by tragedy. What brother of his died on a voyage to Apollo’s sanctuary at Claros?",
    "answer": "CEYX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate this alliterative sentence into English: Frāter ferrō ferit fūrem, ferentem feram in forum.",
    "answer": "ANIMAL INTO THE FORUM."
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate this alliterative sentence into Latin, knowing that farciō means “to stuff” and takes an ablative of means. Fretīs fartīs fraxinīs fractīs, frātrēs fortūnīs frūctī sunt.",
    "answer": "BROTHERS ENJOYED THEIR (GOOD) FORTUNES."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this alliterative sentence into English: Docēbis ducēs dulce dīcere, dum decus dēdicēs dīctōribus dignissimīs.",
    "answer": "{HONOR // ADORNMENT} TO/FOR THE WORTHIEST SPEAKERS."
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Who adapted his Greek models by adding the metaphor “more rapidly than ice in springtime” to a play about a “whip-bearing” hero and using an Italian water deity, Camena, in place of the Muse?",
    "answer": "LIVIUS ANDRONICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was this “whip-bearing” hero?",
    "answer": "AJAX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What rare imperative form in the opening line of the Odusia was modeled after the Greek form ἔννεπε [EN-nep-eh] in the Odyssey?",
    "answer": "ĪNSECE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in derivation between “vow” and “avow,” keeping in mind that the former is cognate with “devote” and the latter is cognate with “vouch” and “vowel.” VOVEŌ and {VOCŌ / VOX} [RESPECTIVELY]",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give two of the three words, with their meanings, from which the term “vamp” is derived.",
    "answer": "ANY TWO OF: AB – FROM; ANTE – BEFORE; PĒS – FOOT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin word with what meaning is “velour” derived, a type of fabric that resembles velvet?",
    "answer": "VILLUS – (TUFT OF) HAIR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of creatures were eaten by mares who had drunk from a well at Potniae, by Lamus and his people, and by a suitor of the nereid Galatea?",
    "answer": "HUMAN(S) / PEOPLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was the poor owner of the mares that drank from a well at Potniae?",
    "answer": "GLAUCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How many of Odysseus’s men did Polyphemus eat during their stay?",
    "answer": "SIX / 6"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The remnants of what road — an extension of the Via Appia around 130 B.C. — stretch from Albania to Turkey, the former sites of Dyrrachium and Constantinople?",
    "answer": "VIA EGNATIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name either the province that contained Dyrrachium or the province that contained Constantinople during the reign of Trajan. MACEDONIA (DYRRACHIUM) or THRACE (CONSTANTINOPLE)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What city near Constantinople’s end of the Via Egnatia is equivalent to modern Izmit?",
    "answer": "NICOMEDIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author published three works in 197 A.D. — Ad Nātiōnēs, Dē Testimōniō Animae, and most famously Apologēticum — which established him as the first major Latin Christian apologist?",
    "answer": "(Q. SEPTIMIUS FLORENS) TERTULLIAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To what fanatical sect of Christianity did Tertullian convert in 213 A.D.?",
    "answer": "MONTANISM / MONTANISTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work, which takes a firm stand against all heresies and schisms, was the magnum opus of a later bishop of Carthage, Cyprian?",
    "answer": "DĒ CATHOLICAE ECCLĒSIAE ŪNITĀTE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What foreign ruler, the patron of Paul of Samosata, overran Egypt but was checked first by the magister equitum Probus and then in successive battles at Antioch and Emesa, ultimately losing the empire nominally ruled by Vaballathus?",
    "answer": "ZENOBIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Greek philosopher and chief advisor to Zenobia was executed after the sack of Palmyra?",
    "answer": "(CASSIUS) LONGINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What general of Zenobia commanded forces at Antioch and Emesa?",
    "answer": "ZABDAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On their way home, the Argonauts rested at the Amber Islands at the mouth of what river, where tears dripping from poplar trees on the riverbank were said to have created the islands shortly after a son of Clymene and Helios fell, flaming, from the sky?",
    "answer": "ERIDANUS (RIVER)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Besides the Heliades, what king of the Ligurians was also known for grieving for Phaethon?",
    "answer": "CYCNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What evidence of Phaethon did the Argonauts see as they passed through the islands?",
    "answer": "FALLEN INTO THE RIVER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which two of the following impersonal verbs are most closely synonymous: taedet, rēfert, placet, cōnstat, interest? INTEREST and RĒFERT",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Using either rēfert or interest, say “It is in the interest of both me and the republic to seek the consulate.”",
    "answer": "PETERE // UT CŌNSULĀTUM PETAM}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a first-conjugation impersonal verb, say in Latin “I have time to read books.”",
    "answer": "VACAT MIHI LIBRŌS LEGERE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What emperor feuded with Asinius Gallus over Cicero’s legacy and exiled another prominent author to Corsica, perhaps leading to his “pumpkinification” in that author’s Apocolocyntōsis?",
    "answer": "CLAUDIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What emperor wrote two autobiographies, one of which survives in an inscription from Ancyra?",
    "answer": "AUGUSTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What emperor addressed his animula vagula blandula in one poem and wrote another one humorously responding to the poet Florus?",
    "answer": "HADRIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb pacīscor, give the second-person singular future imperative.",
    "answer": "PACĪSCITOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now, for the verb pangō, give the first-person plural pluperfect active subjunctive.",
    "answer": "PEPIGISSĒMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Finally, for the verb sternō, give the third-person singular perfect active subjunctive.",
    "answer": "STRĀVERIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What city, the site of Tiberius’s death, served as the headquarters of the fleet on the Bay of Naples and the location of a conference between Sextus Pompey and the Second Triumvirate in 39 B.C.?",
    "answer": "MISENUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What eastern city served as the other main Roman navy base in Italy?",
    "answer": "RAVENNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Legal control of what two islands was granted to Sextus Pompey as part of the pact of Misenum? SARDINIA and SICILY",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What work combines its genre’s conventions, like songs in “amoebean” form, with mentions of civil war and land confiscations, leading some to identify characters like Menalcas and Tityrus with its author?",
    "answer": "ECLOGUES / BUCOLICS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the Eclogues, Vergil’s references to Muses or other sources of inspiration often center around what region, the native land of his model Theocritus?",
    "answer": "SICILY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which Eclogue demonstrates this phenomenon with its opening line “Sīcelides Mūsae, paulō māiōra canāmus”?",
    "answer": "FOURTH ECLOGUE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin phrase describes something as being done surreptitiously or with confidentiality, and uses the name of a plant associated with Venus and Cupid?",
    "answer": "SUB ROSĀ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other plant-related phrase, which comes from Vergil’s Eclogues, is generally used to describe a “hidden danger,” and particularly a traitorous friend?",
    "answer": "ANGUIS IN HERBĀ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Greek-derived word for “cabbage” is described as repetīta in a Juvenal quote essentially meaning “the same old stuff”?",
    "answer": "CRAMBĒ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What emperor used the large brick-factory of Domitius Afer for disaster relief after rushing back from Antium to Rome, eager to personally oversee the relief efforts and portion out space for his opulent new palace complex?",
    "answer": "NERO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "The fire was soon followed by the Pisonian Conspiracy, in which an important role was played by what colleague of Tigellinus as Praetorian Prefect?",
    "answer": "(L.) FAENIUS RUFUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Tacitus mentions that only four regions of Rome remained intact after the fire. How many regions did Rome have in total after Augustus’s division of the city?",
    "answer": "FOURTEEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Say in good Latin, using a syncopated verb form: “We did not know whether our friend had fought well.”",
    "answer": "PUGNĀSSET / DĪMICĀSSET."
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Now say in good Latin: “Whether he fought well or fled, he should not have joined battle so quickly.”",
    "answer": "PROELIUM COMMITTERE [NOT DEBET OR COMMĪSISSE]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now say in good Latin: “I know that I would not have done this.”",
    "answer": "SCIŌ MĒ HOC NŌN {FACTŪRUM / FACTŪRAM} FUISSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What mountain, on which Zeus made a golden cloud for him and Hera to sleep in, saw a student of Rhea refuse to treat her dying ex-husband, and was home to a Dardanian prince before Achilles chased him away?",
    "answer": "MT. IDA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other god was present in the form of a bird on Mount Ida when Zeus and Hera got together?",
    "answer": "HYPNOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Aeneas was only one of the people Achilles encountered on Mount Ida. What two sons of Priam had Achilles caught shepherding before ransoming and releasing them? They were later killed by Agamemnon. ISUS and ANTIPHUS Advanced – Finals",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Forms of what Latin word are found in all of the following: the proverb nūlla [blank] sine līneā, the line nūlla [blank] umquam memorī vōs eximet aevō, and the Catholic hymn [blank] Īrae?",
    "answer": "DIĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Identify the author of either the proverb nūlla diēs sine līneā or the line from the tossup.",
    "answer": "PLINY (THE ELDER) // VERGIL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Nūlla diēs sine līneā, whose message is similar to our “practice makes perfect,” comes from Pliny’s description of the Greek painter Apelles. The same description also contains the advice nē suprā crepidam sūtor iūdicāret. What general meaning does this quote express?",
    "answer": "STICK TO WHAT YOU KNOW // COBBLER, STICK TO YOUR LAST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which poem of Catullus, which some editors have wanted to split into two, combines reminiscences of Lesbia with the myth of Protesilaus and forms the last of his carmina docta?",
    "answer": "(CATULLUS) 68"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Catullus 67 is narrated by what sort of object, which forms the center of an important motif in elegy, the so-called paraklausithyron?",
    "answer": "DOOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What author included the myth of Protesilaus in a poem called Protesilaodamia, part of his Erōtopaegnia?",
    "answer": "LAEVIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between the verbs expergīscor and experior.",
    "answer": "(TO / I) AWAKE / ROUSE & (TO / I) TRY / PROVE [RESPECTIVELY]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the meaning of the deponent verb ringor?",
    "answer": "(TO / I) SNARL // SHOW THE TEETH // CHAFE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the meaning of the deponent verb opperior?",
    "answer": "(TO / I) WAIT (FOR) // AWAIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What woman, who was lovingly raised by Penelope as her own, abandoned the royal house for Eurymachus and treated people poorly unlike her father Dolius?",
    "answer": "MELANTHO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Eurymachus had about as much class as Melantho when it came to interacting with the disguised Odysseus. What object did he throw at Odysseus, only to hit a cupbearer instead?",
    "answer": "(FOOT)STOOL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Though Melantho and Eurymachus were lovers, he was still pursuing Penelope. What beautiful gift did Eurymachus offer to Penelope in book 18?",
    "answer": "GOLDEN {CHAIN / NECKLACE} (WITH AMBER BEADS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, whose widow later married Marcus Brutus and was a daughter of Cato the Younger, headed the fleet patrolling the Adriatic for Pompey and opposed Caesar after a rowdy mob dumped feces on his head and broke his fascēs in 59 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(M. CALPURNIUS) BIBULUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what year did a compromise proposed by Bibulus and Cato result in a sole consul for much of the year?",
    "answer": "52 B.C."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What cognōmen is shared by two consuls — one named Marcus in 51 B.C., and the other Gaius in 50 B.C. — who were opposed to Caesar in the Senate in the years leading up to the civil war and rejected his proposals for compromise?",
    "answer": "MARCELLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English the following sentence, adapted from Lucan’s Pharsālia: “Dēsit mihi sepulchrum rogusque, dum metuar semper.”",
    "answer": "LET A TOMB AND PYRE BE LACKING FOR ME, AS LONG AS I AM ALWAYS FEARED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate the following lines, also adapted from the Pharsālia: “Dabitis poenās prō pāce petītā, et nihil esse discētis tūtius quam duce mē bellum.”",
    "answer": "WAR {WITH ME AS (YOUR) LEADER // UNDER MY LEADERSHIP}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate the following slightly adapted lines from the Pharsālia, keeping in mind that Poenus here is an adjective, and that the word order is quite distorted: “Nec pavet hic populus prō lībertāte ea subīre, obsessum Poenō gessit quae Mārte Saguntum.”",
    "answer": "CARTHAGINIAN {MARS // WARFARE // MILITARY STRENGTH}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who cries as he watches Turnus evade a spear thrown by his suppliant Pallas, since he became the patron deity of Pallanteum after killing a fire breathing son of Vulcan?",
    "answer": "HERCULES"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What son of Hercules was also on the battlefield, donning a lion’s pelt and a shield with the hydra?",
    "answer": "AVENTINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, who gives his name to a group of priests associated with the Pinarii, founded the rites of Hercules at Pallanteum?",
    "answer": "POTITIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two men, ruling 15 years apart in different kingdoms, were defeated by Metellus Macedonicus and Marcus Perperna in 148 and 129 B.C., and both usurped power by claiming to be illegitimate sons of rulers of Macedonia and Pergamum, respectively? ANDRISCUS [PROMPT ON “PSEUDO-PHILIPPUS”] and {ARISTONICUS // EUMENES III}",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Identify the kings whom Andriscus and Aristonicus respectively claimed to be children of. PERSEUS and EUMENES II [RESPECTIVELY]",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Syrian man styled himself as King Antiochus before being defeated by Piso and Publius Rupilius?",
    "answer": "EUNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After receiving a potion from Photis that was meant to turn him into an owl, who sets off on a quest to eat roses and regain his human form in Rome’s only fully extant novel, Apuleius’s Metamorphōsēs?",
    "answer": "LUCIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The initial sentence of the Metamorphōsēs connects it with what genre, which had been written in Latin by a historian of the late Republic?",
    "answer": "MILESIAN TALES // FĀBULAE MĪLĒSIAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The other major Roman novel, the Satyricon, begins with a discussion on the decline of oratory between Encolpius and what fictional teacher of rhetoric?",
    "answer": "AGAMEMNON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "The works of Martial and Phaedrus both contain the form corcodīlus, which exemplifies what phenomenon relative to its correct form crocodīlus? This phenomenon can also be seen in the form accersō.",
    "answer": "METATHESIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The adjective endings -ālis and -āris are actually the same in Latin. If -ālis is the “original,” so to speak, consider the following adjectives, and explain what about the base of the words causes -āris to be used: vītālis, immortālis, tālāris, mīlitāris and capulāris.",
    "answer": "THE L (IN THE BASE CAUSES THE L IN THE SUFFIX TO DISSIMILATE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What explains the first long a in contāminātiō, the long e in tēla, which means “web” and is cognate with “toilet,” and the long o in the alternate spelling “cōsul”? PRONUNCIATION [cf. *contagminātiō, *texla, consul]",
    "answer": "CONSONANT, VOWELS CAN BE LENGTHENED TO PRESERVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Said to own a shrine dedicated to Orpheus, Abraham, Christ, and Apollonius, what emperor refused to personally fight Ardashir — a ruler of the newly-formed Sassanid Dynasty — and was ultimately overthrown in favor of a Thracian peasant of immense stature?",
    "answer": "SEVERUS ALEXANDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Ardashir had become master of the near east in 227 A.D. after dispatching what Parthian monarch, to whose daughter Caracalla had proposed marriage?",
    "answer": "ARTABANUS V"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In an attempt to unify his numerous new subjects, Ardashir fiercely promoted what religion?",
    "answer": "ZOROASTRIANISM // RELIGION OF ZOROASTER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in derivation between “mill” and “milliner,” the latter of which is derived from the name of a city.",
    "answer": "{MOLŌ - GRIND // MOLA - MILLSTONE} AND MEDIOLĀNUM - MILAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two similar-sounding words are mulberry and demur from respectively?",
    "answer": "MŌRUS & MORA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin word and its meaning from which the English word atelier, an artist’s studio, is derived.",
    "answer": "AXIS - AXIS OR HASTA - SPEAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What genre’s first major author was described as “muddy” by its second author, whose work includes a conversation with Damasippus, a banquet with Nasidienus, and a journey to Brundisium?",
    "answer": "SATIRE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Even though Horace judged Lucilius “muddy,” both Horace’s banquet of Nasidienus and journey to Brundisium were modeled after episodes in the work of Lucilius. Name both the parvenu in Lucilius’s 30th book and the destination of his journey in his third book. GRANIUS and SICILY",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Juvenal's 12th Satire attacks people who engage in what activity, which is discussed by Ulysses and Tiresias in one of Horace’s Satires?",
    "answer": "LEGACY HUNTING [ACCEPT EQUIVS.; PROMPT ON “BUILDING UP AN ESTATE”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following noun forms cannot be vocative: Leōnidā, Atlanta, Ēlectra, nympha, Aenēā?",
    "answer": "ATLANTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following noun forms cannot be accusative: aethera, Dīdō, āera, comēta, mȳthon?",
    "answer": "COMĒTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What are the three possible accusative forms of the name Periclēs?",
    "answer": "PERICLEM, PERICLEA, PERICLĒN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man’s funeral — which came about when he was mistaken for a pirate on Rhodes and killed by his son Althaemenes — did Menelaus leave for while Paris was in Sparta?",
    "answer": "CATREUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What sister of Althaemenes accompanied him to Rhodes but ultimately died when he kicked her in the stomach, thinking she had slept with a random man and not a god?",
    "answer": "APEMOSYNE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "During Althaemenes’s time on Rhodes, he founded a town and a shrine. Give either the name of the town or the god to which the shrine was dedicated. CRETINIA or ATABYRIAN ZEUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What festival saw householders make the mano fico sign as they walked barefoot through their house, spitting or tossing nine black beans for the potentially begrudging ghosts?",
    "answer": "LEMŪRIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What other Latin term, besides lemūrēs, could be used to describe the spirits of dead household members believed to haunt the household during the Lemūria?",
    "answer": "LARVAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other public festival concerning the dead ended the Parentālia by bringing food to tombs?",
    "answer": "FĒRĀLIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What emperor of noble ancestry collaborated on a vast three-pronged invasion of North Africa — which spectacularly failed to dislodge the Vandals — in 468 A.D. before becoming the fourth emperor deposed by Ricimer and passing the throne to Olybrius?",
    "answer": "ANTHEMIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was the Eastern emperor at the time with whom Anthemius collaborated on this failed invasion? He was succeeded briefly by his grandson of the same name, and then by Zeno.",
    "answer": "LEO I"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Leo I was elected thanks to the intervention of what Eastern kingmaker, whom he soon had executed after realizing he had no desire to be a puppet?",
    "answer": "ASPAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate this sentence into Latin, knowing that the word for trophy is tropaeum and that an additional clue will be given after two readings: Xerxes values your trophies more than you. In that sentence, a good word for “value” is aestimō.",
    "answer": "PLŪRIS TROPAEA {VESTRA / TUA} XERXĒS AESTIMAT {QUAM VŌS / TĒ / TŪ}"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence from English into Latin: “Does it not shame them to be conquered not even by a fight of the enemy but by a story?”",
    "answer": "NŌN PUDET (EŌS) NĒ PUGNĀ QUIDEM HOSTIUM SED FĀBULĀ VINCĪ?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence from Latin into English: “Dēlīberat Agamemnōn, an Īphigenīam immolet negante Calchante aliter nāvigārī fās esse.”",
    "answer": "CALCHAS DENYING THAT IT IS RIGHT {(FOR IT) TO BE SAILED // TO SAIL} OTHERWISE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What native Greek speaker began writing Latin poetry in 395 A.D. and distinguished himself with works like Dē Bellō Gothicō and other panegyrics of Stilicho and Honorius?",
    "answer": "(CLAUDIUS) CLAUDIAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author of a seven-book history complementing Augustine's Dē Cīvitāte Deī called Claudian a “pagānus pervicācissimus”?",
    "answer": "(PAULUS) OROSIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Against what eunuch did Claudian write several invectives?",
    "answer": "(FLAVIUS) EUTROPIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Note to players: a description is acceptable. During what conflict did the following occur? The world was shrouded in darkness to hide a plant that granted immortality. Sounds of asses and a conch shell caused panic. Burning oaks were thrown towards heaven, and mortals assisted gods in killing the semi-immortal enemies.",
    "answer": "GIGANTOMACHY // WAR OF THE GODS AND GIANTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What giant, who was said to be as strong as Alcyoneus, attempted to rape Hera before being blasted into Tartarus by Zeus’s thunderbolts?",
    "answer": "PORPHYRION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Hyginus, what constellation represented the donkeys that stirred panic among the giants with their braying during the Gigantomachy?",
    "answer": "ASELLUS BOREALIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What does the Lexicōn Recentis Latīnitātis call a “nāvis sīderālis,” which serves as the main map of the hit game that the Romans might’ve called “Inter Nōs”?",
    "answer": "STARSHIP / SPACESHIP"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin verb, with what meaning, do we derive the noun “crewmate”?",
    "answer": "CRĒSCŌ, (TO / I) GROW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a gerundive and the noun impostor, impostōris, say in Latin: “We must condemn the impostor for his foul crime.”",
    "answer": "CRĪMEN/SCELUS/FACINUS IMPOSTOR NŌBĪS DAMNANDUS / CONDEMNANDUS (EST)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Holders of what political office were given sacrosanctity by the lēx sacrāta of 494 B.C., had the right to propose plebiscites to the concilium plēbis, and generally defended the common people against the excesses of the patricians?",
    "answer": "(PLEBEIAN) TRIBUNATE/TRIBUNE // TRIBUNE (OF THE PLEBS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The lēx sacrāta was an important concession made to the plebeians after what man persuaded them to return from their first secession?",
    "answer": "AGRIPPA MENENIUS (LANATUS) / MENENIUS AGRIPPA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After the last plebeian secession, what plebeian dictator passed a law named after himself which ensured that plebiscites were binding on all citizens?",
    "answer": "(Q.) HORTENSIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Described by Propertius as “something greater than the Iliad,” what 12-book work was published by Varius Rufus on Augustus’s orders, even though it was left unfinished on the untimely death of its author Vergil?",
    "answer": "(VERGIL’S) AENEID"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other man, along with Varius Rufus, had been charged with burning the poem until the emperor intervened?",
    "answer": "PLOTIUS TUCCA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other work of Vergil consists of ten hexameter poems that cover a variety of pastoral themes?",
    "answer": "ECLOGUES / BUCOLICS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What meaning is shared among the nouns aequor, pontus, and mare?",
    "answer": "SEA / OCEAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the literal meaning of aequor based on its etymology?",
    "answer": "LEVEL SURFACE / PLANE [FROM AEQUUS; ACCEPT EQUIVS.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Latin word for “salt” can also be used poetically to mean “sea”?",
    "answer": "SAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What name in mythology is shared by a king of Corinth who promised his daughter’s hand in marriage to Jason and a king of Thebes who refused to allow Antigone to bury her brother, Polyneices?",
    "answer": "CREON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Creon of Corinth was also entrusted with raising what daughter of Alcmeon, who shares her name with one of the Furies?",
    "answer": "TISIPHONE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which son of Creon of Thebes was betrothed to Antigone and killed himself after he found out that Antigone had been killed?",
    "answer": "HAEMON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Forms of what word can be found in the phrase “ēheu fugācēs lābuntur [blank]” and as the ‘A’ in",
    "answer": "ANNUS [ACCEPT ANNĪ OR ANNŌ]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What word fills the blank in “[blank] dat quī cito dat,” reinforcing the idea that those who give swiftly seem to proverbially give more than once?",
    "answer": "BIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What word fills the blank in “[blank] aurum probat, miseria fortēs virōs” comparing blacksmithing to how adversities test strong people?",
    "answer": "IGNIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who atoned for his hasty execution of Aulus Caecina and protracted love affair with a Jewish queen after succeeding his father in 79 A.D. and successfully handling three disasters during his short reign?",
    "answer": "TITUS (FLAVIUS VESPASIANUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was this Jewish queen, whom Titus dismissed as soon as he took power?",
    "answer": "(JULIA) BERENICE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "While Titus had had ample opportunities to gain political experience before becoming emperor, his brother Domitian had been thrust into obscurity ever since what Syrian general of Vespasian took over the regency of Rome in late 69 A.D.?",
    "answer": "(C. LICINIUS) MUCIANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What woman sits upside down on a chair in the stars after she saw her daughter, whom she claimed to be more beautiful than the Nereids, almost die to a sea monster?",
    "answer": "CASSIOPEIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Luckily, Cassiopeia’s daughter, Andromeda, was saved by Perseus. Before Perseus could take her hand in marriage, he had to defeat which uncle of Andromeda to whom she was originally betrothed?",
    "answer": "PHINEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Perseus had only been traveling through Ethiopia to visit Chemmis, the home of which of his ancestors, who traveled to the area after having all of his daughters kill their husbands?",
    "answer": "DANAUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the form for the personal pronoun in the following sentence if it were translated into the best classical Latin: “Nor does the man wish that this mistake be taken away from me.”",
    "answer": "MIHI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the form for the indefinite pronoun in the following sentence if it were translated into the best classical Latin: “We were discovered on account of a certain man.”",
    "answer": "QUENDAM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the form for the intensive pronoun in the following sentence if it were translated into the best classical Latin: “The men sharing in the conspiracy itself were caught.”",
    "answer": "IPSĪUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The earliest reference to Christianity in a secular Latin source appears in the works of what legātus of Bithynia, who frequently wrote letters to Trajan asking for advice on governance?",
    "answer": "PLINY THE YOUNGER / C. PLINIUS CAECILIUS SECUNDUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Pliny’s political rise was indebted to the involvement of Trajan. In what year had Trajan appointed Pliny cōnsul suffectus?",
    "answer": "100 A.D."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What speech did Pliny deliver in that year to thank Trajan for this appointment and generally praise his administration?",
    "answer": "PANĒGYRICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What English verb, derived from a Latin noun meaning “breath of life,” has meanings varying from “enliven” to “produce a moving character through a series of still images”?",
    "answer": "ANIMATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What noun, derived from the same word, is a genre of Japanese television content?",
    "answer": "ANIME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Let’s consider a Latin derivative of the word anima. In book 4 of the Aeneid, one line, whose subject is Dido’s sister Anna, reads: sēmianimemque sinū germānam amplexa fovēbat. What does the word derived from anima mean in this sentence?",
    "answer": "HALF-ALIVE / HALF-DEAD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the modern-day name of the country which contained the Garumna, Sequana, and Rhodanus rivers.",
    "answer": "FRANCE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the modern name of the Sequana river?",
    "answer": "SEINE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other French river, which along with the Sequana divides the Belgae from the other inhabitants of Gaul, is now known as the Marne?",
    "answer": "MATRONA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Alfenus Senecio and Ulpius Marcellus are closely associated with what structure that was built by Platorius Nepos between the Solway Firth and the River Tyne in Britain by order of Hadrian?",
    "answer": "HADRIAN’S WALL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What governor would later extend the Roman frontier by building a wall between the Firth of Forth and the Firth of Clyde under orders from the emperor Antoninus Pius?",
    "answer": "LOLLIUS URBICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Due to Senecio’s extensive repairs of Hadrian’s Wall in 205 A.D., many later Romans believed that the barrier was actually first built during the reign of which emperor?",
    "answer": "SEPTIMIUS SEVERUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which of the following works was not written by the Latin author Quintus Ennius: Ambracia, Annālēs, Bellum Pūnicum, Saturae, Hedyphagētica?",
    "answer": "BELLUM PŪNICUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who wrote the Bellum Pūnicum?",
    "answer": "(CN.) NAEVIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What type of work, which is a Latin tragedy dealing with a Roman subject, was Ambracia?",
    "answer": "FĀBULA PRAETEXTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Supposedly worshipped in Boeotian Orchomenus in the form of meteorites, what group of deities generally appear collectively as personifications of beauty and attendants of Aphrodite?",
    "answer": "GRACES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Though she is simply named Charis by Homer, what name did Hesiod give to the wife of Hephaestus, who was also one of the Graces?",
    "answer": "AGLAEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which Grace, the youngest, was given to Hypnos as a bribe and bride for forcing Zeus to sleep?",
    "answer": "PASITHEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What meaning is shared between the impersonal verbs fulgurat and fulminat?",
    "answer": "IT LIGHTENS / THERE IS LIGHTNING"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using two verbs in the impersonal passive, say “They go to the place where there is fighting.”",
    "answer": "ĪTUR EŌ/AD (EUM/ILLUM) LOCUM UBI PUGNĀTUR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using the verb faveō impersonally, say “I will be favored by the goddesses.”",
    "answer": "MIHI Ā DEĀBUS FAVĒBITUR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which Oceanid could not persuade Helius to forgive her for the death of Leucothoë, and followed the Sun’s progress with her eyes until she turned into a sunflower?",
    "answer": "CLYTIË"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "As what mother of Leucothoë did Helius disguise himself in order to seduce Leucothoë?",
    "answer": "EURYNOME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After Leucothoë was buried alive by her father, Helius tried reviving her until he gave up and transformed her into what?",
    "answer": "FRANKINCENSE (TREE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the ablative can be found in the sentence “Agrum vēndidit sēstertium sex mīlibus”?",
    "answer": "(DEFINITE) PRICE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the ablative can be found in the sentence “Doleō tē aliīs malīs labōrāre”?",
    "answer": "CAUSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the ablative can be found in the sentence “Ex animō cōnstāmus et corpore”?",
    "answer": "MATERIAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which Roman historian showed his dislike of Cicero by perhaps writing an Invectīva against him, in addition to diminishing his role in the events of 63 B.C. within his Bellum Catilīnae?",
    "answer": "(C.) SALLUST(IUS CRISPUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Sallust also styled his works in opposition to Cicero. What Latin term is used to describe his imbalanced and asymmetric style, full of non-parallel constructions and unexpected turns of phrase?",
    "answer": "INCONCINNITĀS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Though Sallust often takes up a moralizing tone in his works and criticizes the greed of the nobility, he himself committed extortion while governor of what province?",
    "answer": "AFRICA (NOVA) / NUMIDIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After suffering a defeat near Dijon, who was starved into surrender when a complex double line of earthworks was built around the hill-city of Alesia in 52 B.C.?",
    "answer": "VERCINGETORIX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Vercingetorix was a chieftain of what tribe, which had previously fought against the Romans under their king Bituitus?",
    "answer": "ARVERNĪ / ARVERNIANS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who enlisted the help of the freedman admiral Anicetus in a botched attempt to murder his mother Agrippina in a collapsible boat in the bay of Naples?",
    "answer": "NERO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What city on the bay of Naples served as the base for Anicetus’ fleet?",
    "answer": "MISENUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who, following in the footsteps of fish he had just captured, ate some grass himself before he dove into the sea and became a sea god, fully abandoning his life as a fisherman from Anthedon?",
    "answer": "GLAUCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What nymph became the victim of Circe’s jealousy for Glaucus?",
    "answer": "SCYLLA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Described by Ovid as the second major elegiac poet after Cornelius Gallus and by Quintilian as “tersus atque ēlegāns,” who wrote love poetry to Marathus, Nemesis and Delia?",
    "answer": "(ALBIUS) TIBULLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What poetess’s six poems to Cerinthus are featured alongside the works of Tibullus in the manuscript tradition?",
    "answer": "SULPICIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following words, if any, is NOT synonymous with the others? rīvus, lītus, ōra, ripa.",
    "answer": "RĪVUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the following words, which, if any, can NOT mean “boat” or “ship”? puppis, scapha, carīna, linter.",
    "answer": "ALL BELONG / NONE OF THEM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the following words, which two are most closely synonymous? rūpēs, mōnstrum, scopulus, acervus, sordēs. RŪPĒS and SCOPULUS Advanced – Preliminary Round 2",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Augustan-age author depicts Tiresias instructing Ulysses in the art of legacy-hunting, recounts the banquet of Nasidienus, and describes a journey to Brundisium in his Satires, though he is better known for adapting the lyric meters of Alcaeus in his Odes?",
    "answer": "HORACE / (Q.) HORATIUS (FLACCUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which work of Horace, which takes inspiration from Archilochus, is a collection of 17 short poems on varied topics such as garlic and the poetaster Maevius?",
    "answer": "EPODES / IAMBĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Horace’s “nunc est bibendum” Ode, like his ninth Epode, celebrates a victory at what battle?",
    "answer": "(BATTLE OF) ACTIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: “Obsidēs dabimus pācis cōnfirmandae causā.”",
    "answer": "STRENGTHENING/CONFIRMING PEACE."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Rewrite that sentence to use a gerund instead of a gerundive, without changing the base words.",
    "answer": "OBSIDĒS DABIMUS PĀCEM CŌNFIRMANDĪ CAUSĀ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate into Latin using a gerundive and the adjective idoneus: “These hostages are more suitable for strengthening peace than those.”",
    "answer": "CŌNFIRMANDAM SUNT ILLĪS / QUAM ILLĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Named after a son of Zeus and Niobe, what city saw Gelanor give the throne to Danaus and a later king named Adrastus lead the Seven against Thebes?",
    "answer": "ARGOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What river-god, the father of Io, was the first inhabitant of the land that would become the Argolid?",
    "answer": "INACHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Eventually, after Perseus had killed his grandfather Acrisius, he traded Argos for Tiryns with what son of Proetus?",
    "answer": "MEGAPENTHES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In one section within the first Catilinarian, Cicero provides a lengthy list of Catiline’s various transgressions against the republic, followed by the words ac iam illa omittō, an example of what literary device — the calling of attention to a point by seeming to disregard it?",
    "answer": "PRETERITION / PRAETERITIŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Excluding sound effects, what literary device can be found within the following lines from the Aeneid, in a scene where the Carthaginians are making themselves hospitable to the Trojans? “Dant famulī manibus lymphās, Cereremque canistrīs expediunt.”",
    "answer": "METONYMY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Amōrēs 1.9, what literary device does Ovid use with the phrase lectus et umbra?",
    "answer": "HENDIADYS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Though he was not Constantius II’s first choice as Caesar, who quickly proved himself with a major victory at Argentoratum — now called Strasbourg — and soon became emperor from 361-363 A.D., leading an ultimately futile pagan revival?",
    "answer": "JULIAN (THE APOSTATE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Julian’s reign was cut short when he was wounded while retreating from what Persian capital?",
    "answer": "CTESIPHON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What emperor in the East faced a rebellion from Julian’s Gallic legions under Procopius, then turned his attention to fighting the Goths in Thrace?",
    "answer": "VALENS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence, adapted from the Dē Rē Pūblicā of Cicero, into English: Vereor nē Rōmulus rēx barbarōrum fuerit.",
    "answer": "I FEAR THAT ROMULUS WAS A KING OF BARBARIANS."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate this line from Quintus Ennius, as quoted by Scipio Africanus in the Dē Rē Pūblicā: Quālem tē patriae cūstōdem dī genuērunt!",
    "answer": "BIRTHED YOU! [ACCEPT “WHAT A PROTECTOR … CREATED/BIRTHED IN YOU”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence from the Dē Rē Pūblicā: Mortuō rēge Pompiliō, Tullum Hostīlium populus rēgem creāvit.",
    "answer": "MADE TULLUS HOSTILIUS KING."
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What nōmen is shared by a 1st century B.C. historian and praefectus fabrum from Mytilene surnamed Theophanes, a ruthless Social War commander who sacked Asculum and was surnamed Strabo, and a member of the first Triumvirate who cleared the Mediterranean of pirates and defeated Mithridates?",
    "answer": "POMPEIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What praenōmen was shared by a Byzantine emperor surnamed Apsimar, deposed by Justinian the Slit-nosed, and the son of Drusus II who was meant to co-inherit the empire with Caligula?",
    "answer": "TIBERIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What cognōmen was shared by an eastern commander with the nōmen Statius who burned Artaxata in the reign of Marcus Aurelius and a Stoic philosopher with the nōmen Helvidius who was exiled and killed by Vespasian?",
    "answer": "PRISCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who claimed that indignātiō was his inspiration to write his verses, which were filled with scathing mockery of societal vices like the masses’ craving for pānem et circēnsēs?",
    "answer": "(DECIMUS IUNIUS) IUVENALIS / JUVENAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "How many individual satires did Juvenal write?",
    "answer": "SIXTEEN / 16"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which of Juvenal’s satires is considered one of the most ferociously misogynistic documents of all time, describing suicide as a viable alternative to marriage?",
    "answer": "(SATIRE) 6 // SIXTH (SATIRE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "As you are strolling through ancient Rome, you come across a Latin inscription. Naturally, the inscription has no long marks. Given this information, which of the following Latin adjective forms, if any, could NOT agree with the noun form pirata on the inscription: alio, ignave, noti, senex?",
    "answer": "NOTI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On the same inscription, you see the noun form navis. Again, noting that there are no long marks on the inscription, which adjective form, if any, could NOT agree with navis: albas, latae, celeris, fracta?",
    "answer": "ALL COULD AGREE [NAVĪS CAN BE ACC. PL.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "You continue reading the inscription and find the noun form carminis. How many unique forms of the adjective vester, vestra, vestrum could modify carminis on the inscription?",
    "answer": "ONE / 1 (GENITIVE SINGULAR)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Thracian king achieved favor with Athens by helping King Pandion in his dispute over territory with Thebes, but committed adultery with his sister-in-law, Philomela, then cut out her tongue to silence her?",
    "answer": "TEREUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Philomela eventually revealed what happened through her weaving. As a punishment, Procne and Philomela decided to kill what young son of Tereus and serve it to him?",
    "answer": "ITYS / ITYLOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Upon eating his child, Tereus was transformed into what form?",
    "answer": "HOOPOE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What ancient African nation, restored to Roman control by Cornelius Dolabella during the reign of Tiberius, first came to prominence during the Second Punic War under its competing chieftains Syphax and Massinissa?",
    "answer": "NUMIDIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was the Numidian chieftain who revolted during Tiberius’s reign and was put down by Dolabella?",
    "answer": "TACFARINAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Syphax joined forces with Carthage after winning the hand of Sophonisba, the daughter of what Carthaginian chieftain whom Scipio defeated at Ilipa?",
    "answer": "HASDRUBAL (SON OF) GISCO/GISGO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between pendō and pendeō. (TO / I) WEIGH and (TO / I) HANG [RESPECTIVELY]",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between torreō and torqueō. (TO / I) PARCH / ROAST / BAKE / BURN and (TO / I) TURN / TWIST [RESPECTIVELY]",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between lūcus, lūcī and lūctus, lūctūs. WOOD / GROVE and GRIEF [RESPECTIVELY]",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Known for both killing Clytius in the Gigantomachy and helping Demeter look for Persephone, what goddess was associated with crossroads and dark magic?",
    "answer": "HECATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which Colchian sorceress had Jason sacrifice to Hecate under the name Brimo?",
    "answer": "MEDEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Under the name Crataeis, Hecate is sometimes said to have been the mother of which monster encountered by Odysseus in the Straits of Messina?",
    "answer": "SCYLLA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Calceolāriī and soleāriī would both engage in what type of profession, whose practitioners would most generally be referred to as sūtōrēs?",
    "answer": "[ACCEPT “COBBLERS” OR “SHOES” BEFORE “PROFESSION” IS READ]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Assuming that a soleārius never made anything other than soleae, what type of footwear did they make?",
    "answer": "SLIPPERS / SANDALS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of footwear might be seen on a Roman manual laborer or soldier?",
    "answer": "CALIGAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What work existed in partial versions such as the Vetus Latīna and the Greek Septuagint before an author living in Bethlehem taught himself Hebrew in order to produce a standard translation of it, the Vulgate?",
    "answer": "THE (HOLY) BIBLE / OLD TESTAMENT [ACCEPT “VULGATE” BEFORE THE LAST WORD]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author of Dē Cīvitāte Deī expressed his concern that Jerome’s Vulgate might provoke a separation from the Eastern church, since it was completely independent from the Septuagint?",
    "answer": "(AURELIUS) AUGUSTINUS / (ST.) AUGUSTINE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Two of Jerome’s minor works, the Chronicon and Dē Virīs Illūstribus, are reminiscent of what late Republican author who was praised for setting forth all of world history in three books?",
    "answer": "CORNELIUS NEPOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Though they had already signed a treaty with Rome in 354 B.C., what tribe’s attack on the Sidicini prompted Capua to appeal to Rome for aid, starting the first of three wars with them in the 4th century",
    "answer": "SAMNITES"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "The Second Samnite War also began with an appeal from Capua, followed by the siege of what Greek colony?",
    "answer": "NEAPOLIS/NAPLES"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "The Third Samnite War was finally put to an end by what consul of 290 B.C., who would later also lead the defeat of Pyrrhus at Beneventum?",
    "answer": "(M.’) CURIUS DENTATUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "If the following sentence were to be translated into Latin, what use of the subjunctive would be contained within? “I will wait provided that you return within three days.”",
    "answer": "(DUM) PROVISO CLAUSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate that sentence into Latin.",
    "answer": "TRIBUS DIĒBUS REDEĀS / REDEĀTIS [DO NOT REVEAL OTHER OPTIONS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Besides the one you just used, give two other particles commonly used to introduce proviso.",
    "answer": "[EXCLUDING WHICHEVER ONE THEY USED IN B1]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In book 12 of Ovid's Metamorphoses, Nestor compares the invulnerability of Cycnus to that of which Lapith, who had been raped by Poseidon and transformed from a woman to a man?",
    "answer": "CAENEUS [DO NOT ACCEPT CAENIS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "During the battle of the Lapiths and Centaurs, how was Caeneus eventually defeated?",
    "answer": "CRUSHED UNDER A HEAP OF (OAK) TREES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Though many believed that Caeneus was dead, Mopsus claimed that he actually transformed into what type of animal?",
    "answer": "(GOLDEN) BIRD [IMPOSSIBLE TO BE MORE SPECIFIC]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the English for the motto of Princeton University, “Deī sub nūmine viget.”",
    "answer": "FLOURISHES [ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin and English for the motto of the University of Pennsylvania.",
    "answer": "MORALS ARE USELESS [ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Cornell, of course, is the only Ivy without a Latin motto, so let’s fix that. Please translate this Latinized motto of the university back into English: “Scholam condere velim ubi quīlibet doctrīnam in quālibet disciplīnā invenīre potest.”",
    "answer": "INSTRUCTION IN ANY STUDY/DISCIPLINE [ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "“The Brothers,” “The Mother-in-Law,” “The Self-Tormentor,” and “The Eunuch” are all titles attributed to what Roman author who “contaminated” Greek originals to produce his 6 comedies?",
    "answer": "TERENCE / (P.) TERENTIUS (AFER)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the original titles and corresponding English for any 2 of the comedies mentioned in the toss-up.",
    "answer": "HEAUTONTIMOROUMENOS (“THE SELF-TORMENTOR”); EUNUCHUS (“THE EUNUCH”)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, who was sent off to govern Cyprus in 58 B.C. by the tribune Clodius, indirectly caused the First Triumvirate to form because of his stubborn refusal to compromise the strict Republican morality he inherited from his great-grandfather?",
    "answer": "(M. PORCIUS) CATO UTICENSIS/THE YOUNGER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Plutarch, Caesar lamented that Cato’s suicide after Thapsus had denied him the chance to do what action?",
    "answer": "SPARE CATO’S LIFE/PARDON HIM [ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What goddess gained the epithet Ramnusia from her chief cult center in Attica and is known for having caused Narcissus to fall in love with himself?",
    "answer": "NEMESIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What animal form did Aphrodite take to pretend to chase the swan Zeus, allowing him to take refuge in the lap of Nemesis?",
    "answer": "EAGLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Five books with verses in various meters, an unfinished epic on the life of a Greek hero at Troy, and 12 books on a pair of quarreling Theban brothers make up the literary canon of what author who wrote the Silvae, Achilleid, and Thebaid?",
    "answer": "(PUBLIUS PAPINIUS) STATIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Statius, a big fan of Thebes, also wrote a pantomime named for what Theban princess?",
    "answer": "AGAVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Taking tegumentum to mean “mask,” translate the following sentence from Latin into English: “Sī tegumentum ē meō ōre dētrahās, multus dolor sit.”",
    "answer": "FROM MY FACE / MOUTH, THERE WOULD BE MUCH PAIN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate: “Rogō utrum sentiās tē praeesse necne.”",
    "answer": "I ASK WHETHER YOU FEEL THAT YOU ARE IN CHARGE OR NOT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate: “Nūllīus intererat quis essem donec tegumentum induī.” Advanced – Preliminary Round 3",
    "answer": "NO ONE CARED WHO I WAS UNTIL I PUT ON THE MASK"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who reunited the four republics of Macedon by claiming to be the long-lost son of Perseus before being defeated at the second battle of Pydna in 148 B.C.?",
    "answer": "ANDRISCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What commander, who would later survive an assassination attempt by the tribune Gaius Atinius, delivered this finishing blow to Andriscus as praetor?",
    "answer": "(Q. CAECILIUS) METELLUS MACEDONICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Which nephew of Metellus Macedonicus had his command against Jugurtha given to Marius even though he had defeated Jugurtha at the Muthul river in 109 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(Q. CAECILIUS) METELLUS NUMIDICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Welcome to the Mūsica Rōmāna! In “Live While We’re Young” by One Direction, Niall, Liam, Louis, Harry, and Zayn sing, “Let's go crazy, crazy, crazy 'til we see the sun/I know we only met but let's pretend it's love/And never, never, never stop for anyone/Tonight let's get some and live while we're young.” In Latin, what use of the subjunctive would be exemplified by these petitions?",
    "answer": "HORTATORY / JUSSIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On “Last First Kiss,” Harry Styles sings, “Girl what would you do, would you wanna stay/If I were to say…I wanna be your last first kiss?” In Latin, what type of conditional, and which tense of the subjunctive, would be used to render this question?",
    "answer": "“PRESENT CONTRARY-TO-FACT” – A&G §514 B. 2.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On “Tell Me a Lie,” the boys sing, “Tell me anything, but don't you say he's what you're missing, baby.” Give a subjunctive construction that could be used to render this latter, negative command into the best classical Latin. A description is fine.",
    "answer": "[PROMPT “WHAT TENSE” IF THEY DON’T SPECIFY]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What pupil of Papirius Fabianus addressed a Dē Cōnsōlātiōne to his mother Helvia while he was in exile, displaying the Stoic fortitude that he also preached in his Epistulae Mōrālēs to Lucilius?",
    "answer": "(L. ANNAEUS) SENECA THE YOUNGER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "To what island had Seneca been exiled for his involvement in the adultery of Julia Livilla?",
    "answer": "CORSICA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "While he extolled the benefits of being in exile to Helvia, Seneca is often accused of hypocrisy, because he simultaneously tried to secure his return with a second Dē Cōnsōlātiōne. To what freedman of Claudius is this work of vile flattery addressed?",
    "answer": "(C. JULIUS) POLYBIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate this excerpt from St. Augustine’s Confessions, written as a conversation with God, from Latin into English: “Laudāre tē vult homō, aliqua portiō creatūrae tuae.”",
    "answer": "MAN, A/SOME PORTION OF YOUR CREATION, WISHES TO PRAISE YOU."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this excerpt, also adapted from the Confessions: “Laudāre tē volumus, quia fēcistī nōs ad tē.”",
    "answer": "IMAGE."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this excerpt, adapted from the same work: “Dā mihi, domine, scīre et intellegere quid sit optimum.”",
    "answer": "GIVE/GRANT ME, LORD/MASTER, TO KNOW AND UNDERSTAND WHAT IS THE BEST."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After Acastus had abandoned Peleus on Mt. Pelion, which centaur, who had Aristaeus, Actaeon, and Jason as his pupils, saved him?",
    "answer": "CHIRON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which Oceanid and mother of Chiron slept with Cronus when he was in the form of a horse, leading to Chiron being born a centaur?",
    "answer": "PHILYRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Horrified by her affair with Cronus, Philyra asked Zeus to be transformed into what form?",
    "answer": "LINDEN TREE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Suscēnseō, supplicō, invideō, and resistō are verbs that take what case in Latin?",
    "answer": "DATIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the dative can be found in the sentence “Rēx locum optāvit rēgnō”?",
    "answer": "PURPOSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the dative can be found in the phrase “Facilis dēscēnsus Avernō”?",
    "answer": "DIRECTION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "To what work of Latin literature did one of the consuls of 43 B.C. add an eighth book describing the final clean-up operations after the original author, Julius Caesar, had mostly completed his conquest of Gaul?",
    "answer": "(COMMENTĀRIĪ) DĒ BELLŌ GALLICŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was this consul of 43 B.C. who died at Mutina?",
    "answer": "AULUS HIRTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Caesar’s Dē Bellō Cīvīlī also received three continuations — the so-called Corpus Caesariānum — all of whose titles begin with Bellum. Name one of them. ANY ONE OF: BELLUM ALEXANDRĪNUM or BELLUM ĀFRICUM or BELLUM HISPĀNIĒNSE",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what general cardinal direction would you travel to go from Miletus to Olisipo?",
    "answer": "WEST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what general cardinal direction would you travel to go from Cyzicus to Rhegium?",
    "answer": "WEST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what general cardinal direction would you travel to go from Hierosolyma to the Pontus Euxīnus?",
    "answer": "NORTH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Originally a guardian of an oracle of Themis or Gaea, what monster tried to kill Leto, knowing that her son was fated to kill him before establishing his oracle at Delphi?",
    "answer": "PYTHON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "However, most accounts say that Python did not try to kill Leto entirely out of a sense of self-preservation, but rather was instigated by which deity?",
    "answer": "HERA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In some versions, the Python raised which monstrous offspring of Hera that shot flames from his eyes and terrorized the gods, forcing them to flee in the forms of various animals?",
    "answer": "TYPHON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Tacitus, members of what group were “burned for night-time illumination” or “died from the ravening of dogs” when Nero needed a convenient scapegoat after the Great Fire, and were named after a man “executed by the procurator Pontius Pilate”?",
    "answer": "CHRISTIANS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "At the outbreak of the fire, Nero had been staying at what seaboard town, which had been wrested from the Volscians during the Great Latin War?",
    "answer": "ANTIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What 3rd-century emperor began the first large-scale persecution of the Christians in 250 A.D. in an effort to restore the pāx deōrum, though this didn’t save him from dying at Abrittus a year later?",
    "answer": "DECIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "A praetexta about Lucius Aemilius Paullus’s victory at Pydna was written by what Latin author, who wrote 12 cothurnātae and was considered the greatest tragedian by Cicero?",
    "answer": "PACUVIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In addition to writing, Pacuvius was one of the first Roman men of rank to practice what art?",
    "answer": "PAINTING"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which cothurnāta of Pacuvius depicted the famous scene where Eurycleia recognizes her master’s scar?",
    "answer": "NIPTRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What four-word quotation from Cicero’s First Catilinarian idiomatically means “these are bad days” and literally means “O the times! O the customs!”?",
    "answer": "“Ō TEMPORA! Ō MŌRĒS”"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What three-word quotation from Cicero’s On the Laws idiomatically means “military power must be subordinate to civil authority”?",
    "answer": "“CĒDANT ARMA TOGAE”"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What three-word quotation from Cicero’s First Catilinarian idiomatically means “silence speaks volumes”?",
    "answer": "“CUM TACENT, CLĀMANT”"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who saved Dexamenus' daughter Mnesimache from the centaur Eurytion, shared wine with the centaur Pholus, and killed the centaur Nessus when he tried to abduct his wife Deianeira?",
    "answer": "HERACLES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Unfortunately, Pholus died because the poor centaur had dropped an arrow coated with what substance on his hoof?",
    "answer": "POISON / BLOOD OF THE LERNEAN HYDRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Heracles killed Nessus, he and Deianeira had been trying to cross what river, which had received its name from the father of Marpessa?",
    "answer": "EVENUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which city in Italy was recaptured by Fabius Maximus in 209 B.C. and later hosted a conference of the Second Triumvirate in 37 B.C., but is better known for hiring Pyrrhus and his mercenary army as a defense against Roman expansion in 280 B.C.?",
    "answer": "TARENTUM / TARANTO"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What other Italian city was nearly the site of a civil war between Antony and Octavian in 40 B.C. but instead saw the peace reconfirmed by Antony’s betrothal to Octavian’s sister Octavia?",
    "answer": "BRUNDISIUM / BRINDISI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What city served as the birthplace of the Second Triumvirate by hosting the initial gathering of Lepidus, Antony and Octavian in 43 B.C.?",
    "answer": "BONONIA / BOLOGNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following English words, if any, does not belong by derivation: revel, revelation, duel, rebellion?",
    "answer": "REVELATION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin words and their meaning from which the words “revel” and “revelation” are derived. BELLUM, WAR and VELUM, SAIL",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of these four English words, if any, does not belong by derivation: reprobate, reproach, reproof, fireproof?",
    "answer": "REPROACH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What goddess — said to have taught the young Dionysus his rites and Oenone her powers of prophecy — appears in the Aeneid where she extinguishes Aeneas’ burning ships, which were made of the wood from her sacred grove on Mt. Dindymus?",
    "answer": "CYBELE / CYBEBE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Cybele was often identified with what Greek Titaness?",
    "answer": "RHEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On the same day that the Argonauts worshipped Cybele on Mt. Dindymus, they ran into four sons of what earlier figure, who had escaped to Colchis to avoid the wrath of his stepmother Ino?",
    "answer": "PHRIXUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin word is at the root of Latin adjectives such as “anceps,” “praeceps,” and “biceps,” which literally means “two-headed”?",
    "answer": "CAPUT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the genitive singular of any of those adjectives, which shows their derivation from caput and distinguishes them from the genitive of prīnceps, which comes from capiō. ANCIPITIS or PRAECIPITIS or BICIPITIS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Define the words anceps and praeceps. TWO-HEADED/DANGEROUS/UNCERTAIN and HEADLONG/HEADFIRST (RESPECTIVELY)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Book 4 of what poem contains a harsh attack on the passions of love, though it was supposedly written per intervālla īnsāniae by an author driven mad by a love potion, Lucretius?",
    "answer": "(LUCRETIUS’S) DĒ RĒRUM NĀTŪRĀ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of event, whose description draws heavily on Thucydides, concludes the Dē Rērum Nātūrā?",
    "answer": "PLAGUE (AT ATHENS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give Lucretius’s full name — praenōmen, nōmen, and cognōmen.",
    "answer": "TITUS LUCRETIUS CARUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb scindō, scindere, give the 2nd person plural, perfect active subjunctive.",
    "answer": "SCIDERĪTIS [ACCEPT “SCICIDERĪTIS BUT THAT’S THE ARCHAIC FORM”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the same form for the verb sternō.",
    "answer": "STRĀVERĪTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the same form for the verb linō.",
    "answer": "LĒVERĪTIS / LĪVERĪTIS / LINĪVERĪTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, the last emperor with ties to the aristocracy of the Republic, had previously served as censor under Decius and is most famous for being captured alive by the Sassanid king Shapur I?",
    "answer": "(P. LICINIUS) VALERIAN(US) [DO NOT READ FULL NAME]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What usurper of Moorish descent, who was killed by his troops after a reign of just three months, did Valerian replace as emperor in 253 A.D.?",
    "answer": "(M. AEMILIUS) AEMILIANUS / AEMILIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What Roman commander of the Second Punic War would ultimately meet his end in a battle on the upper courses of the Baetis River in Spain, but is more well known for co-leading Roman forces at the disastrous Battle of Trebia and being rescued by his young son after being wounded at the battle of Ticinus River?",
    "answer": "PUBLIUS CORNELIUS SCIPIO / SCIPIO THE FATHER OF AFRICANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What impatient consul served as the other Roman commander at the Battle of Trebia?",
    "answer": "(TI.) SEMPRONIUS LONGUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man took refuge in Ocaleae after being driven from his home in Crete and established a reputation for fairness and justice, ultimately being honored with serving as one of the judges of the Underworld?",
    "answer": "RHADAMANTHUS / RHADAMANTHYS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Rhadamanthus was originally exiled from Crete after a dispute with his brothers over the love of which handsome youth?",
    "answer": "MILETUS / ATYMNIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Though its introductory dedication to Septicius Clarus and its first few chapters on Julius Caesar are lost, what work’s collection of gossip and humorous anecdotes makes it an invaluable historical source on the first 12 Caesars?",
    "answer": "(SUETONIUS’S) DĒ VĪTĀ CAESARUM [PROMPT ON “THE TWELVE CAESARS”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work of Suetonius consists of biographies of writers and includes subsections like Dē Poētīs and Dē Grammaticīs et Rhētoribus?",
    "answer": "DĒ VIRĪS ILLŪSTRIBUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What meaning is shared by the verbs at the roots of “arraign” and “amputate”?",
    "answer": "TO THINK (REOR AND PUTŌ)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the meaning of the verb at the root of “vegetable”?",
    "answer": "TO BE ALIVE/LIVELY / TO MOVE/EXCITE/AROUSE (VEGEŌ)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the meaning of the verb at the root of “nice”? Advanced – Semifinal Round",
    "answer": "TO (NOT) KNOW (SCIŌ / NESCIŌ)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When his herdsman Tyrrhus drove his people into a frenzy, what king, remembering the oracle of his father Faunus, refused to declare war on the foreigner to whom he had promised his daughter Lavinia?",
    "answer": "LATINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What goddess took matters into her own hands and cast open the doors of Janus, beginning the war anyway?",
    "answer": "JUNO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which Latin elder favored Aeneas over Turnus and tried to convince Latinus to stop sending his citizens into danger for naught?",
    "answer": "DRANCES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between mulceō and mulgeō. (TO / I) STROKE / GRAZE / SOOTHE and (TO / I) MILK [RESPECTIVELY]",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between mānsuētūdō and cōnsuētūdō. TAMENESS / MILDNESS / GENTLENESS and CUSTOM / HABIT [RESPECTIVELY]",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the two distinct definitions of the Latin word iūs, iūris. LAW / RIGHT and BROTH / SOUP / JUICE",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following provinces was annexed latest: Aegyptus, Cilicia, Syria, Macedonia?",
    "answer": "AEGYPTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of Cilicia, Syria, Macedonia, and Britannia was annexed earliest?",
    "answer": "MACEDONIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of those same four provinces had part of its territory cut off to create Achaea in 27 BC?",
    "answer": "MACEDONIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Because the work begins after the death of Augustus, what Silver Age historical work was intended to be a continuation of Livy and is transmitted in manuscripts under the title Ab Excessū Dīvī Augustī?",
    "answer": "ANNĀLĒS / ANNALS [ACCEPT “AB EXCESSŪ…” BEFORE THE LAST CLAUSE]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "In the Annālēs, Tacitus includes a portrait of what man, an author and a member of Nero’s court who was most valued for his refined and elegant tastes?",
    "answer": "(TITUS) PETRONIUS (NIGER) / PETRONIUS (ARBITER)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Annālēs end in the middle of the account of what Stoic senator’s death?",
    "answer": "(P. CLODIUS) THRASEA PAETUS(’S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Using home-field advantage to gain the upper hand, what chieftain was able to defeat five Roman generals in quick succession, entrapping and signing a treaty with a proconsul of 141 B.C., but soon met his downfall at the hands of assassins hired by Servilius Caepio?",
    "answer": "VIRIATHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was this proconsul of 141 B.C., mistakenly referred to by Cary and Scullard as a consul?",
    "answer": "(Q. FABIUS MAXIMUS) SERVILIANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Against what people had the Romans fought for many years, ostensibly to control safe routes to their newly acquired Spanish provinces, but really just as a way for ambitious Romans to win triumphs, as exemplified by Popillius Laenas’s honorless assault on an unoffending tribe in 173 B.C.?",
    "answer": "LIGURĒS / LIGURIANS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using only three words, say in Latin: “I have come to avenge my father.”",
    "answer": "THEY MUST USE THE SAME WORD IN THE BONUS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Using the same three root words, without adding any extras, say that sentence with a different grammatical construction.",
    "answer": "OTHER OF VĒNĪ ULTUM/ULTŪRUS PATREM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What type of conditional sentence in Latin might have an apodosis such as “Quid futūrum fuit?”",
    "answer": "[CF. “DĪCIT FUTŪRUM FUISSE” OR “ROGŌ QUID FUTŪRUM FUERIT”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was hailed as redditor lūcis aeternae in 296 AD after recapturing Britannia from the usurper Allectus, and died at Eboracum ten years later, allowing his son Constantine to come to power?",
    "answer": "CONSTANTIUS I / CHLORUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What naval commander had initially led Brittania into revolt against the tetrarchy in 287 AD but was later murdered by Allectus?",
    "answer": "CARAUSIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What Praetorian Prefect of Constantius led the army that defeated Allectus at the battle of Silchester in 296 AD?",
    "answer": "ASCLEPIODOTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Latin poet tells of Jupiter Feretrius, Tarpeia, Hercules and Cacus, and other Roman etiological legends in his 4th book of poetry, following the example set by the Aitia of his model Callimachus?",
    "answer": "(SEXTUS) PROPERTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name one of the people to whom Propertius addressed an epicēdion in the last two books of his elegies.",
    "answer": "MARCELLUS / CORNELIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work of Apuleius exposes the real name of Propertius’s lover Cynthia, as well as the mistresses of many other love poets?",
    "answer": "APOLOGIA / DĒ MAGĪĀ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which mortal, who accompanied Heracles to defeat the giant Alcyoneus, established an altar to “Heracles the Glorious Victor” to avoid Heracles’ wrath for being the first to breach the walls of Troy?",
    "answer": "TELAMON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which daughter of Laomedon — who had ransomed her brother Priam for her veil — bore the Greek archer Teucer to Telamon?",
    "answer": "HESIONE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "After the Trojan war, Telamon banished Teucer from Salamis for not coming back with Ajax the Greater alive. To which island did Teucer venture where Belus set him up as king?",
    "answer": "CYPRUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Note to players: there will be an extra clue at the end of this sentence. Feel free to wait if you are unsure. Translate into idiomatic English the sentence “Neque tū is es quī nesciās,” in which the pronoun “is” roughly means “the sort” or “the type.”",
    "answer": "NOR ARE YOU THE TYPE TO NOT KNOW / WHO WOULD/DOES NOT KNOW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate into English: “Quī morī velint facilius reperiuntur quam quī dolōrem ferant.”",
    "answer": "EASILY THAN THOSE WHO (WOULD) BEAR PAIN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: “Nēmō tam dūrus fuit quīn tantam fortūnae mūtātiōnem dolēret.”",
    "answer": "PAIN AT/MOURN/LAMENT SUCH A GREAT CHANGE OF FORTUNE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Livy, who claimed he had been busy resolving a dispute between a father and a son at Rome as an excuse for being late to a meeting of Latin leaders in the grove of Ferentina, though this was not enough to satisfy his critic Turnus Herdonius?",
    "answer": "(L.) TARQUINIUS SUPERBUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How did Tarquinius Superbus frame Herdonius in a fictitious plot to assassinate him? A description is acceptable.",
    "answer": "(THEN REVEALED THEM TO THE LATIN LEADERS) [ACCEPT EQUIVS.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Livy contrasts Tarquinius’s unjust actions in peacetime with his successful capture of what Volscian city, whose spoils he planned to use to fund the temple of Jupiter Capitolinus?",
    "answer": "SUESSA POMETIA [DO NOT ACCEPT “SUESSIA POMETIA,” KETAN IS WRONG]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Consider the following lines from Book 1 of the Aeneid: “Dederatque comam diffundere ventīs, nūda genū, nōdōque sinūs collēcta fluentīs.” The word genū in this excerpt shows what use of the accusative?",
    "answer": "GREEK / SYNECDOCHICAL / RESPECT / SPECIFICATION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Consider this phrase from Juvenal’s second Satire: “Quī Curiōs simulant et Bacchānālia vīvunt.” What use of the accusative is Bacchānālia in this excerpt?",
    "answer": "COGNATE / INTERNAL / INNER OBJECT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Consider these lines from Ennius’ Euhemerus: “Itaque pactus est cum Sāturnō, utī sī quid līberum virīle secus eī nātum esset, nē quid ēducāret.” What use of the accusative is secus?",
    "answer": "ADVERBIAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Appendix Perottīna contains part of the corpus of what Thracian lībertus Augustī, who gave a voice to the lower classes in his Aesopic fables?",
    "answer": "PHAEDRUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What other freedman of Augustus, who was placed in charge of the Palatine library, wrote a commentary on Vergil and a work on the origins of bees?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS JULIUS) HYGINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "A much later author, Avianus, wrote 42 Aesopic fables dedicated to what other writer, who penned a seven-book dialogue set in December of 384 AD, discussing Vergil and a wide variety of antiquarian subjects?",
    "answer": "(AMBROSIUS THEODOSIUS) MACROBIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Greek author is referenced in a four-word quotation from Horace idiomatically meaning “you can’t win ‘em all” — “quandōque bonus dormītat [blank]”?",
    "answer": "HOMER / HOMĒRUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What three-word Latin phrase from Quintilian expresses a similar sentiment, literally meaning “they abound with lovely faults”?",
    "answer": "ABUNDANT DULCIBUS VITIĪS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What pentameter line of Martial means “that person truly grieves who grieves without witness”?",
    "answer": "ILLE DOLET VĒRĒ QUĪ SINE TESTE DOLET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On what island did Polites hear the sweet singing of a woman, who served his party a brew of yellow honey and Pramnian wine that turned them all into swine, save Eurylochus?",
    "answer": "AEAEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Odysseus came to Circe’s home, she wasn’t able to transform him since Hermes had given him what milk-white flower that was black at its root?",
    "answer": "MOLY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After leaving Aeaea, Odysseus and his crew learn of Elpenor’s death and come back to Aeaea where they bury him. On his burial mound, they fix what kind of object, another of which would later be carried by Odysseus and mistaken for a winnowing-fan?",
    "answer": "OAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After becoming the new captain-general of the Hellenic confederacy created by Antigonus Doson, who gave refuge to Demetrius of Pharos and signed a treaty of mutual assistance with Hannibal in 215 B.C., sparking the First Macedonian War?",
    "answer": "PHILIP V (OF MACEDON)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Roman commander was sent by the Senate in 214 BC to undermine Philip’s position by gaining the friendship of the Aetolian league and the city of Pergamum?",
    "answer": "(M.) VALERIUS LAEVINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where in 205 BC did Philip and the Romans meet to discuss a peace treaty that earned Philip both land on the Adriatic coast and the enmity of the Romans?",
    "answer": "PHOENICE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of subordinate clause is found in the sentences “Ut nēminem alium rogāsset, scīre potuit” and “Licet mors impendeat, nōn tamen cēdam”, is more commonly introduced by particles like etsī and quamquam, and is one of the main types of cum clauses?",
    "answer": "CONCESSIVE CLAUSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the Ovidian sentence “Ut terram inveniās, quis eam tibi trādet habendam?” in which ut means “even if”.",
    "answer": "EVEN IF YOU (SHOULD) FIND LAND, WHO WILL GIVE IT TO YOU TO HAVE/BE HAD?"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the Plinian sentence “Quamquam levium pūmicum cāsus tamen metuēbātur,” knowing that it is a standalone sentence expressing a complete thought about the eruption of Mount Vesuvius, and that a pūmex is a pumice stone.",
    "answer": "FEARED [ACCEPT IDIOMATIC EQUIVS.]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Coeranus used an herb brought by a snake to revive a son of Minos, and instructed Bellerophon on how to tame the winged horse Pegasus?",
    "answer": "POLY(E)IDUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was this son of Minos, whom Polyidus found when he spotted an owl standing near the storage room where this son was stuck?",
    "answer": "GLAUCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Which son of Polyidus chose to fight in the Trojan war knowing he would die there?",
    "answer": "EUCHENOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What emotion, derived from a Latin verb meaning “to strangle,” might be induced by an intense Certamen match, in which scores are close and only one team can advance?",
    "answer": "ANXIETY / ANXIOUS / ANGUISH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What English adjective, derived from the name of a Roman god, describes the disposition of someone with a short temper, or whose mood rapidly changes?",
    "answer": "MERCURIAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other English adjective, also derived from the name of a Roman god, describes the disposition of someone who is melancholic or consistently solemn?",
    "answer": "SATURNINE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Proculian and Sabinian schools both focused on what subject matter, most famously set forth by Papinian and Ulpian in the third century and systematized in various Cōdicēs during the late Empire?",
    "answer": "LAW/JURISPRUDENCE [ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which friend of Cicero and author of a Liber Annālis, portrayed as a somewhat embarrassed Epicurean, discusses legal theory with Cicero and his brother Quintus in the Dē Lēgibus?",
    "answer": "(T. POMPONIUS) ATTICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Enticed by the allure of flowers colored with a deep Tyrian purple, what woman plucked off a few blossoms, only to find blood falling from the branches of the lotus tree?",
    "answer": "DRYOPE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Ovid’s Metamorphoses, immediately after Iole finishes telling Dryope’s story, she and Alcmene encounter what man, looking “almost like a boy” after he was rejuvenated by Hebe?",
    "answer": "IOLAUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "The activity and reign of Julian forms the majority of the extant portion of what author’s historical work, which begins with the reign of Nerva, continuing where Tacitus left off?",
    "answer": "AMMIANUS MARCELLINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Ammianus Marcellinus’s historical work ends with the death of what emperor?",
    "answer": "VALENS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Alexandrian meter’s use of four short syllables in a row near the end of each line gave it a frenzied, orgiastic rhythm perfect for describing Attis’s self-castration and the wild rites of Cybele in Catullus 63?",
    "answer": "GALLIAMBIC(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which meter was used in Ennius’s Epicharmus and the Pervigilium Veneris, as well as the Plautine lines that would’ve been spoken with musical accompaniment?",
    "answer": "TROCHAIC TETRAMETER CATALECTIC / TROCHAIC SEPTENARII"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "The prefatory poem of Persius’s Satires and the mimiambs of Matius were both composed in what meter, which is also known as scazons or limping iambic trimeter?",
    "answer": "CHOLIAMBIC"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What meaning is shared by all of the following verbs: reserō, pandō, patefaciō, and rēclūdō, which is an antonym of claudō?",
    "answer": "TO OPEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the meaning of the Latin word opīmus?",
    "answer": "FAT/RICH/NOBILE/FERTILE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "You might have recognized the word opīmus from “spolia opīma,” but the word is also used outside of that expression. Tacitus, in the proem to his Historiae, says “Opus aggredior opīmum cāsibus.” Give a contextually appropriate translation of this sentence.",
    "answer": "I AM APPROACHING/BEGINNING/ATTACKING A WORK RICH WITH EVENTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What emperor was able to persevere through such disasters as the Persian occupation of Lazica and the Nika riots of 532 A.D. while still striving to reconquer former Roman territory in Africa, Italy, and Spain?",
    "answer": "JUSTINIAN I / THE GREAT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what structure, equivalent to the Roman Circus Maximus, did the Nika rebellion begin?",
    "answer": "HIPPODROME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What nephew of Anastasius I and supposed supporter of the Green Faction was proclaimed emperor by the mob in the Hippodrome during the Nika Rebellion?",
    "answer": "HYPATIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: “Fūgērunt propter metum nē proditī essent.”",
    "answer": "HAD BEEN BETRAYED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give the best translation of the following sentence adapted from Ennius: “Vīvam an moriar, nūllus in mē est metus.”",
    "answer": "THERE IS NO FEAR IN ME (AS TO) WHETHER I LIVE OR DIE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence: “Huic quaestiōnī aut etiam aut nōn respondēbō.”",
    "answer": "TO THIS QUESTION I WILL ANSWER EITHER YES OR NO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What city, founded by Car, had an eponymous king who lost his son Euippus to the Cithaeronian lion, then gave the throne to Euippus’ avenger, Alcathous?",
    "answer": "MEGARA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Alcathous became king of Megara, he built the walls with which god?",
    "answer": "APOLLO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Description acceptable. What interesting phenomenon would take place if you struck any of the wall’s stones with a pebble?",
    "answer": "A LYRE [ACCEPT OBV. EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Members of what group did not require a tūtor, prepared the mola salsa, and oversaw sacred objects such as the Palladium?",
    "answer": "VESTAL VIRGINS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was the age range in which a young girl could become a Vestal Virgin?",
    "answer": "SIX TO TEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When a treaty was being signed, a member of which other priestly college would kill a pig with a flint stone, pronouncing a curse on Rome if it was the first to break the treaty?",
    "answer": "FĒTIĀLĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What late poet advertised the beauty of the region near Trier in a 483-line epyllion on the river that flows through it – the Moselle – while supervising the instruction of the emperor’s young son Gratian?",
    "answer": "(DECIMUS MAGNUS) AUSONIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other famous work of Ausonius concerned a German enslaved woman who was set free?",
    "answer": "BISSULA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What pupil of Ausonius, a fellow native of Bordeaux, did he attempt in vain to dissuade from devoting himself to the church?",
    "answer": "(PONTIUS MEROPIUS ANICIUS) PAULINUS OF NOLA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "In Plautus’s Pseudolus, Calidorus attacks the pimp Ballio verbally with many insults, including “Lēgirupa.” Translate this, keeping in mind that it is a noun of agency formed from lēx and rumpō.",
    "answer": "LAW-BREAKER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Ballio accepts each of Calidorus’s insults openly. After being called “Periūre,” he says, “Vetera vāticināminī.” Keeping in mind that vāticinor is a compound of vātēs and canō, what does this retort idiomatically mean?",
    "answer": "SONG [L&S] / THAT’S COMMON KNOWLEDGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what two Latin words do we derive the Plautine compound būcaeda? BŌS and CAEDŌ",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Who killed Damasus while defending the Greek wall at Troy and is said to have been born on the same day Eurytion led the Centaurs to disrupt the wedding of his parents, Pirithous and Hippodameia?",
    "answer": "POLYPOETES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What son of Coronus was Polypoetes’ inseparable companion who co-led the Lapith contingent at Troy?",
    "answer": "LEONTEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Where did Polypoetes and Leonteus travel to overland following the Trojan War?",
    "answer": "COLOPHON (NEAR EPHESUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What possibly plebeian consul of 486 B.C., portrayed in the literary accounts as a forerunner of the Gracchi, proposed an agrarian law but was condemned to death in the following year, even though he had been instrumental in forging a treaty with the Latin League seven years earlier?",
    "answer": "SPURIUS CASSIUS (VECELLINUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Spurius Cassius’s condemnation was secured by members of what gēns, whose members held one consulship every year from 485 to 479 until they made a failed attempt to capture Fidenae?",
    "answer": "GĒNS FABIA / FABII"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other man’s scheming was foiled by L. Minucius Rufus Augurinus, who discovered that his relieving of a grain shortage in 440 B.C. out of his own pocket was part of an attempt to make himself a tyrant?",
    "answer": "SPURIUS MAELIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "That Ares killed him at Phlegra, or Zeus killed him with thunderbolts, or Hephaestus killed him with missiles of red-hot metal, are all explanations for the death of what giant?",
    "answer": "MIMAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In an Arcadian tradition, who led some giants to protect Rhea as she gave birth to Zeus?",
    "answer": "HOPLADAMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Apollonius of Rhodes, what name is given to the “Earthborn” tribe of giants that were killed by Heracles and the Argonauts in Mysia?",
    "answer": "GEGENEES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a substantive clause of result, translate into the best Classical Latin: “It follows that the defeated enemies must be spared.”",
    "answer": "SEQUITUR UT HOSTIBUS VĪCTĪS PARCENDUM SIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Knowing that the substantive “ināne” means “a void” or “empty space,” and keeping in mind that fateāre exemplifies a common alternate ending, translate into English: “Esse in rēbus ināne fateāre necessest.”",
    "answer": "IT IS NECESSARY FOR YOU TO CONFESS THAT THERE IS EMPTY SPACE IN THINGS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: “Tantum abest ut poētam ōderit, ut etiam eum rogāverit ut dē sē carmen scrīberet.”",
    "answer": "HIM TO WRITE A POEM ABOUT HIM(SELF)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Myrmidon and Putātōrēs are the two titles that remain of the works of what 1st-century author, who became famous for the moral maxims drawn from his mimes?",
    "answer": "PUBLILIUS SYRUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the Latin title for Syrus’s moral maxims?",
    "answer": "SENTENTIAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author of mimes during the early empire was known for his bloody stage effects in works such as Laureolus and Phasma?",
    "answer": "CATULLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Eastern emperor, whose wife became notorious for her fight with John Chrysostom, had his policy in dealing with Alaric and Stilicho influenced by his praetorian prefect Rufinus, an appointee of his father Theodosius the Great?",
    "answer": "ARCADIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was this wife of Arcadius?",
    "answer": "EUDOXIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other Praetorian Prefect and grandfather of a future emperor served as the power behind the throne of the young Theodosius II, the son of Arcadius, upon his ascension in 408 AD?",
    "answer": "ANTHEMIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "In grammar, a “metaplast” is a word with more than one stem. For the metaplast femur, give two possible forms for the genitive singular. FEMORIS and FEMINIS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "For the metaplast mūnus, give two possible forms for the nominative plural. MŪNERA and MŪNIA",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "For the heteroclite satiās, give two possible forms for the ablative singular. SATIĀTE and SATIĒ",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What pair of twins, at the age of six, received Armenia, Parthia, Media, Cyrenaica, and Libya through the Donations of Alexandria in 34 B.C., which were carried out by their father Marcus Antonius? ALEXANDER HELIOS and CLEOPATRA SELENE",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In a perhaps forged will of Antony revealed to Augustus by Munatius Plancus, what man was declared the true heir and successor to Julius Caesar?",
    "answer": "CAESARION // PTOLEMY XV CAESAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Along with Caesarion, what son of Antony and Fulvia and brother of Iullus Antonius was executed by the forces of Octavian in 30 B.C.?",
    "answer": "(M. ANTONIUS) ANTYLLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Preserved in some adverbs such as aliquī, what case that merged with the ablative during the development of Latin is the source of uses such as manner, accompaniment, and means?",
    "answer": "INSTRUMENTAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the meaning of the adverb aliquī, related to the adverb quī?",
    "answer": "SOMEHOW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What case is described with the Greek word ὀρθή (or-THĒ) as the “cāsus rēctus” to differentiate it from the oblique cases?",
    "answer": "NOMINATIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What approximate meaning is shared by the Latin words from which “inextricable” and “nugatory” are derived?",
    "answer": "TRIFLES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what simple verb is the English word “stray” derived? STERNŌ - SPREAD/STRETCH or VAGOR - WANDER",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "In one derivation, “stray” comes from the participle strāta, in the phrase via strāta. What English noun, also derived from the participle in this phrase, is a direct translation of via strāta?",
    "answer": "STREET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Dē Extīs, Dē Auguriō Prīvātō, and Dē Sphaerā Graecānicā are all minor works of what neo-Pythagorean philosopher, who is most famous for his 29-book work entitled Commentāriī Grammaticī?",
    "answer": "NIGIDIUS FIGULUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In which book of Lucan’s Pharsālia does Nigidius Figulus make a brief appearance uttering dark prophecies about the civil war?",
    "answer": "BOOK 1 / ONE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What other author similarly juxtaposed grammatical and antiquarian topics in his prolific writings, as exemplified by his Dē Antīquitāte Litterārum dedicated to Accius?",
    "answer": "(M. TERENTIUS) VARRO REATINUS/OF REATE // THE REATINE VARRO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "“All places beyond are impassable by both the wise man and the fool.” This translation of Pindar describes what famous monuments — located at Calpe and Abyla — established by a hero who had recently returned a golden cup to Helios?",
    "answer": "PILLARS OF HERACLES / HERCULES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On what island could one find the graves of the Boreades — two columns, also erected by Heracles, of which one would sway in the north wind?",
    "answer": "TENOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "The Greeks claimed that what mythological figure was depicted in a huge seated colossus in Egyptian Thebes that would emit a musical note when struck by the rays of the rising sun?",
    "answer": "MEMNON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Welcome to the 9th annual Yale Certamen! Translate the following sentence into Latin: We hope that you will enjoy this competition! or SPĒRĀMUS FORE UT HŌC CERTĀMINE FRUĀMINĪ!",
    "answer": "SPĒRĀMUS VŌS/TĒ HŌC CERTĀMINE FRUCTŪRŌS/-ĀS/-UM/-AM ESSE!"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Bene factum! Now translate this sentence into Latin: We encourage you to use both knowledge and speed. ŪTĀMINĪ/ŪTĀRIS or ET SCIENTIĀ ET CELERITĀTE",
    "answer": "HORTĀMUR (VŌS/TĒ) (UT) SCIENTIĀQUE CELERITĀTEQUE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Finally, using potior , say in Latin: If you play well, you will obtain a wonderful reward. (or PRAEMIĪ MĪRĀBILIS/MĪRĪ/MĪRANDĪ)",
    "answer": "MĪRĀBILĪ/MĪRŌ/MĪRANDŌ POTIĒMINĪ/POTIĒRIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Zeus Katachthonios was an epithet of what god, who snatched up Persephone as she was picking flowers and carried her down to the Underworld? adHADES",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What epithet of Hades meant “The Unseen One”?",
    "answer": "AÏDONEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "At what lake near Naples did Aeneas enter the Underworld?",
    "answer": "AVERNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which of the following verbs, if any, has a reduplicated third principal part: cēdō, pergō, pellō, stertō?",
    "answer": "PELLŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Define the verb pellō and provide all principal parts.",
    "answer": "PELLŌ, PELLERE, PEPULĪ, PULSUS / PULSUM = (TO / I) BEAT / DRIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Define the verb pergō and provide all principal parts.",
    "answer": "PROCEED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author dedicated his first poem to Cornelius Nepos and addressed the sparrow of Lesbia in his second?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS VALERIUS) CATULLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was Lesbia’s real name, according to Apuleius?",
    "answer": "CLODIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "The marriage of what mythological couple was the subject of Catullus’ 64th poem? PELEUS and THETIS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After what Roman military disaster did the Samnites receive possession of Fregellae and force the conquered soldiers to walk under a yoke of spears?",
    "answer": "CAUDINE FORKS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "In what year did the Battle of the Caudine Forks occur?",
    "answer": "321 B.C."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Six years later, what commander’s forces were caught in the defile of Lautulae as he was trying to recover the coastal road to Campania?",
    "answer": "(QUINTUS FABIUS MAXIMUS) RULLIANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What daughter of Evenus was allowed to choose between Apollo and Idas, selecting the latter because he would not leave her when she grew old?",
    "answer": "MARPESSA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What daughter of Idas and Marpessa married Meleager?",
    "answer": "CLEOPATRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How did Marpessa die?",
    "answer": "COMMITTED SUICIDE (AFTER IDAS’ DEATH)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What English noun, derived from a verb meaning “to shine” is “a branched, often ornate, lighting fixture suspended from a ceiling?”",
    "answer": "CHANDELIER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What English adjective derived from an adverb meaning “secretly” means “executed in concealment?”",
    "answer": "CLANDESTINE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What English verb derived from a noun meaning “heel” means “to instill by persistent instruction.”",
    "answer": "INCULCATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What imitator of Thucydides became the first popular monographist in Latin literature when he wrote Bellum Catilīnae and Bellum Iugurthīnum?",
    "answer": "SALLUST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Although the two monographs are Sallust’s most famous works, what annalistic work did he also begin to write before dying?",
    "answer": "HISTŌRIAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What politician saved Sallust from disgrace and obtained for him the governorship of Africa Nova? After this man died, Sallust fell into disgrace a second time and retired to private life for good.",
    "answer": "JULIUS CAESAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Soon after Caecilius Metellus defeated Critolaus in central Greece, Lucius Mummius overran what city, razing it in 146 B.C.?",
    "answer": "CORINTH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Into what newly-formed Roman province was Corinth incorporated?",
    "answer": "ACHAEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The sack of Corinth and creation of Achaea occurred in the same year as the sack of what city following the end of the Third Punic War?",
    "answer": "CARTHAGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A “handbook that is kept constantly at hand for consultation” can be known by what two-word Latin phrase meaning “go with me”?",
    "answer": "VADE MECUM / VĀDE MĒCUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "An “inquisitive or gossipy person” can be known by what Latin word meaning “what now”?",
    "answer": "QUIDNUNC / QUIDNUNC"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The “latest possible date for something” can be known by what three-word Latin phrase meaning “limit before which”?",
    "answer": "TERMINUS ANTE QUEM / TERMINUS ANTE QUEM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Reared by the Oceanid Capheira and the Telchines, what god spent most of his time at a watery palace at Aegae?",
    "answer": "POSEIDON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Poseidon first courted his wife Amphitrite, she initially fled, but was persuaded to marry Poseidon by what minor sea deity?",
    "answer": "DELPHIN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Helius and Poseidon competed for the patronage of Corinth, who arbitrated the dispute?",
    "answer": "BRIAREUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Māiālis, nefrēns, scrōfa, verrēs, and sūs were all words for what animal?",
    "answer": "PIG / SWINE / SOW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In ancient Rome, what was defrūtum?",
    "answer": "(GRAPE) JAM / JELLY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What ancient Roman dish was a hash-like mixture comprising fish, eggs, and cheese?",
    "answer": "TYROTARĪCHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat “ūdus” vel “hūmidus”?",
    "answer": "WET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat “formīdō” vel “pavor”?",
    "answer": "FEAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat “ūrō” vel “torreō”?",
    "answer": "BURN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Welcome to the Mūsica Rōmāna! What “recent” mega-hit might be translated alliteratively into Latin as “Vetus Via Vīcī”?",
    "answer": "“OLD TOWN ROAD”"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a double dative, translate into Latin the title of Ed Sheeran’s recent hit, “I Don’t Care”?",
    "answer": "MIHI NŌN EST CŪRAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "[Note to moderator: please read song title enthusiastically] Using an emphatic Latin form, translate into Latin the title of Taylor Swift’s hit song, ME!",
    "answer": "MĒMĒ! / MĒMET!"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who quoted the stoic soldier Vulteius, a character from his own epic poem Pharsālia, while committing suicide at the order of Nero?",
    "answer": "LUCAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give another title for the Pharsālia.",
    "answer": "BELLUM CĪVĪLE // DĒ BELLŌ CĪVĪLĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of what town in Spain was Lucan a native?",
    "answer": "CORDUBA / CÓRDOBA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "At various times, what man considered Marcus Claudius Marcellus, Marcus Vipsanius Agrippa, and Gaius and Lucius Caesar as heirs, only to outlive them all as Rome’s first emperor?",
    "answer": "AUGUSTUS / OCTAVIAN / OCTAVIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Lucius and Gaius Caesar were the sons of what woman, Augustus’ daughter?",
    "answer": "JULIA (THE ELDER)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In 2 B.C., Julia was found guilty of adultery and treason, causing Augustus to exile her to what island?",
    "answer": "PANDATERIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "Who were punished in the Underworld by being bound to a pillar with snakes because they had piled up mountains in order to storm Olympus? OTUS and EPHIALTES // ALOADAE",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of animal sat on the pillar to which Otus and Ephialtes were bound in the Underworld?",
    "answer": "(SCREECH-)OWL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On what island did Otus and Ephialtes accidentally kill each other with javelins?",
    "answer": "NAXOS / DIA / STRONGYLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage, which I will read twice, then answer in ENGLISH the questions that follow: Cornēlius erat gubernātor ingentiōris nāvis, \"Scylla\" nōmine. Ūnō diē, quandō in \"Marī Nostrō\" nāvigābat, maxima tempestās coorta est. Omnēs valdē timēbant, sed nōn Cornēlius. Is undās, quae maiōrēs villīs erant, superāvit et tūtus nāvem in portum dērigit. The question: What was the name of Cornelius’ ship?",
    "answer": "“SCYLLA”"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was Cornelius’ position on the ship?",
    "answer": "HELMSMAN / STEERSMAN / PILOT [DO NOT ACCEPT “CAPTAIN”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How big were the waves which Cornelius overcame in the Mediterranean?",
    "answer": "BIGGER THAN VILLAS / (COUNTRY-)HOUSES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into English: sī Aenēās ā Graecīs occīsus esset, fortasse Rōma numquam condita esset.",
    "answer": "ROME WOULD NEVER HAVE BEEN FOUNDED"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into English: nescīrēmus Graecōs Trōiam dēlēvisse nisī Homērus Īliadem scrīpsisset.",
    "answer": "TROY IF HOMER HAD NOT WRITTEN THE ILIAD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Finally translate this sentence: etsī Homērus rē vērā vīxit, dubitō an caecus fuerit.",
    "answer": "IN A TRUE WAY, I DOUBT WHETHER HE WAS BLIND."
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "“Cicerōniānus es, nōn Chrīstiānus” is how God supposedly replied to what author, a native of Stridon, when he was in the Desert of Chalcis prior to beginning his translation of the Bible into Latin?",
    "answer": "(EUSEBIUS SOPHRŌNIUS) HIERŌNYMUS // (SAINT) JEROME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the name of the translation?",
    "answer": "VULGATE // BIBLIA SACRA VULGĀTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What famous phrase did gladiators give to the master of ceremonies before starting the show?",
    "answer": "MORITŪRĪ TĒ SALŪTANT // MORITŪRĪ TĒ SALŪTĀMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin for the wooden sword a gladiator receives after winning.",
    "answer": "RUDIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who became infatuated with Chrysippus, the illegitimate son of Pelops, and carried him off to Thebes, gaining the throne and marrying Jocasta?",
    "answer": "LAÏUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author was born to pagan parents in Carthage but converted to Montanism because of his strict religious views, which is evident in works such as Dē Praescrīptiōne Haereticōrum, Dē Spectāculīs, and Dē Cultū Fēminārum?",
    "answer": "(QUINTUS SEPTIMIUS FLORENS) TERTULLIAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name one of the three works of Tertullian which was composed in 197 A.D. to defend Christianity against the attacks of pagans.",
    "answer": "AD NĀTIŌNĒS / APOLOGĒTICUM / DĒ TESTIMŌNIŌ ANIMAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat “lateō”?",
    "answer": "(TO / I) LURK / LIE HIDDEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat “micō”?",
    "answer": "(TO / I) DART / QUIVER / GLEAM / FLASH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat “pōscō”?",
    "answer": "(TO / I) DEMAND / CLAIM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Please translate the following Latin phrase: Nihil tam mūnītum quod nōn expugnārī pecūniā possit.",
    "answer": "NOTHING IS SO FORTIFIED THAT IT CANNOT BE CONQUERED BY MONEY."
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "To which Latin author are both of those phrases attributed? Advanced – Preliminary Round 2",
    "answer": "(MARCUS TULLIUS) CICERO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What province was safeguarded by Vettius Bolanus from 69 to 71 A.D. and expanded by Petillius Cerialis to Eboracum, which is now called York?",
    "answer": "BRITANNIA / BRITAIN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Brigantine client queen protected the northern borders of the province?",
    "answer": "CARTIMANDUA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Agricola succeeded Frontinus and Cerialis, winning major battles against the Caledonians. Under which emperor’s reign did his accomplishments occur?",
    "answer": "DOMITIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the Latin word for “eyebrow”?",
    "answer": "SUPERCILIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the Latin word for “thumb”?",
    "answer": "POLLEX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What is the Latin word for “skin”?",
    "answer": "CUTIS / TEG(U)MEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What work of Latin literature is narrated by the character Encolpius and is most famous for the Cēna Trimalchiōnis?",
    "answer": "SATYRICON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What genre, other than novel, is the Satyricon classified as because of its mix of prose and poetry?",
    "answer": "MENIPPEAN SATIRE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who wrote the Satyricon?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) PETRONIUS (ARBITER)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Rescuing the infant Dionysus from the flames that destroyed Semele, stealing back the sinews of Zeus from Typhon, and killing Argus Panoptes were all deeds performed by what god?",
    "answer": "HERMES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What deity did Hermes father with Penelope after Odysseus drove her out of Ithaca?",
    "answer": "PAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Zeus sent an eagle to steal the sandal of what goddess while she bathed in the river Achelous so that Hermes could be with her?",
    "answer": "APHRODITE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the context of the Roman baths, what was a lacōnicum, also known as a sūdātōrium?",
    "answer": "SWEATING ROOM / SAUNA (ROOM)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the context of the Roman baths, what was unguentum?",
    "answer": "(RUBBING) OIL / PERFUME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What sort of slave brought unguentum and strigilēs to the bathers?",
    "answer": "CAPSĀRIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Please translate the following Latin legal phrase: Audī alteram partem.",
    "answer": "HEAR THE OTHER SIDE [ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Please translate the following Latin legal phrase: Errantis voluntās nulla est.",
    "answer": "A MISTAKEN / ERRING MAN / ONE [ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Please translate the following Latin legal phrase: Dēlēgāta potestās nōn potest dēlēgārī.",
    "answer": "[ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage, which I will read twice, then answer in ENGLISH the questions that follow: Subitō Herculēs, ā Iūnōne sollicitātus, in maximam īram cecidit. Propter hanc īram hērōs putāvit suam uxōrem et suōs līberōs inimīcōs esse. Statim līberōs apprehendit et exclāmāvērunt: \"nunc est tempus in quō omnēs inimīcī pereant.\" Līberōs necāvit et cōnfestim resipīvit. The question: What happened to Heracles when he was incited by Juno?",
    "answer": "[ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "As a result of his anger, what did Heracles think?",
    "answer": "EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What happened when Heracles killed his children?",
    "answer": "[ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Identify the speaker of the following lines from Book 1 of Apollonius of Rhodes’ Argonautica: “Let no one offer this honor to me. For I will not consent, and I will forbid any other to stand up. Let the hero who brought us together, himself be the leader of the host.”",
    "answer": "HERACLES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On what island does Heracles chastise the Argonauts with the following lines: “No fair renown shall we win by thus tarrying so long with stranger women; nor will some god seize and give us at our prayer a fleece that moves of itself.”",
    "answer": "LEMNOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who speaks the following lines in Book 4: “For I deem that I alone can subdue for you that man, whoever he be, even though his frame be of bronze throughout, unless his life too is everlasting. But be ready to keep your ships here beyond the cast of his stones, till he yield victory to me.”",
    "answer": "MEDEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, a governor of Bithynia and consul of 100 A.D., delivered a Panegyricus in honor of Trajan but is most famous for his ten books of letters?",
    "answer": "PLINY THE YOUNGER / (GAIUS) PLINIUS CAECILIUS (SECUNDUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To whom did Pliny the Younger address a letter about the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius?",
    "answer": "(PUBLIUS CORNELIUS) TACITUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the title of Pliny the Elder’s 37-book encyclopedic work?",
    "answer": "NATURALIS HISTORIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What type of conditional statement can be found in the following sentence: Dēfessa fuissem, sī nōn dormīvissem.",
    "answer": "PAST CONTRARY TO FACT // PAST CONTRAFACTUAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Keeping all else the same, change the sentence to a present contrary to fact conditional.",
    "answer": "DĒFESSA ESSEM, SĪ NŌN DORMĪREM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Finally, keeping all else the same, change the sentence to a future less vivid conditional.",
    "answer": "DĒFESSA SIM, SĪ NŌN DORMIAM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Roman emperor abolished the sales-tax and adopted his cousin Tiberius Gemellus before his megalomania-inducing illness?",
    "answer": "CALIGULA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which kingdom revolted as a result of Caligula putting to death its king Ptolemy, son of Juba?",
    "answer": "MAURETANIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In what city in Judaea did Caligula demand a statue and worship from the locals, causing much outrage?",
    "answer": "JERUSALEM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Book 12 of Vergil’s Aeneid, who takes the form of Metiscus to assist her brother, Turnus, in fighting the Trojans?",
    "answer": "JUTURNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Also in Book 12, what woman kills herself because she wrongly thinks Turnus has died?",
    "answer": "AMATA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "At the end of Book 12, Aeneas considers sparing Turnus, but is overcome with anger and decides to kill him after seeing what object?",
    "answer": "(THAT TURNUS TOOK FROM PALLAS WHEN TURNUS KILLED PALLAS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into alitterative Latin: We gave two gifts to two goddesses in two days.",
    "answer": "DUO DŌNA DUĀBUS DEĀBUS DUŌBUS DIĒBUS DEDIMUS."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into English: strigilibus fragilibus vigilibus nōbilibus ūtendum est.",
    "answer": "THE NOBLE WATCHMEN MUST USE THE FRAGILE STRIGILS/SCRAPERS."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into English: Spurius spopondit sē sēmina Spartae sparsūrum esse.",
    "answer": "SPRINKLE/SCATTER SEEDS IN/AT SPARTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin verb with what meaning do we derive “joust” and “junction”?",
    "answer": "IUNGŌ – (TO / I) JOIN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin verb with what meaning do we derive “poison” and “potion”?",
    "answer": "PŌTŌ – (TO / I) DRINK"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin verb with what meaning do we derive “decay” and “deciduous”?",
    "answer": "CADŌ – (TO / I) FALL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whose murky biography consists mostly of slander by Jerome, although we are confident he was the actual author of the Dē Rērum Natūrā?",
    "answer": "LUCRETIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Lucretius’ Dē Rērum Natūrā is often considered an Epicurean example of what genre?",
    "answer": "EPIC / DIDACTIC"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Jerome’s slander of Lucretius included some specific life details. To what cause does Jerome attribute Lucretius’ death?",
    "answer": "MADNESS CAUSED BY LOVE POTION(S)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The mountains of Magnesia were home to what tribe of creatures, whose members included Eurytion, Nessus, and Cheiron?",
    "answer": "CENTAURS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Centaur Eurytion was killed by Heracles after he carried off what daughter of Dexamenus?",
    "answer": "MNESIMACHE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man is said to have fathered the Centaurs when he had sex with a cloud he believed to be Hera?",
    "answer": "IXION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Roman’s image as Pater Patriae was tarnished when he gave his troops license to massacre the townsfolk of Veii?",
    "answer": "(M. FURIUS) CAMILLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "For how many years did Veii hold out before it fell to Camillus in 396 B.C.?",
    "answer": "TEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "From Veii’s spoils, what object was dedicated to Apollo as Rome’s first offer to repay its debt to Greece?",
    "answer": "GOLDEN BOWL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The nouns pars, fidēs, hortus, sāl, carcer, and castrum all share what grammatical peculiarity?",
    "answer": "DIFFERENT MEANINGS IN THE SINGULAR AND PLURAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē signifcat: salēs?",
    "answer": "WITTICISMS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Distinguish in meaning between castrum and castra.",
    "answer": "FORT AND CAMP [RESPECTIVELY]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A work concerning fishing on the Pontus Euxīnus, a compilation of letters from mythological heroines to their lovers, and a three-book work on how to win love are all attributed to what Golden Age author of the Metamorphōsēs?",
    "answer": "(PUBLIUS) OVID(IUS NASO)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the name of Ovid’s work which purports to compile letters from mythological heroines to their lovers?",
    "answer": "HĒRŌIDĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work of Ovid describes how to fall out of love?",
    "answer": "REMEDIA AMŌRIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Hic cibus magis idoneus bōbus illō est.",
    "answer": "THIS FOOD IS MORE SUITABLE FOR COWS THAN THAT (FOOD)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Alter frāter erat perītior pugnandī, alter pingere māluit.",
    "answer": "FIGHTING, THE OTHER PREFERED TO PAINT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What name in ancient Rome was abbreviated “Cn.”?",
    "answer": "GNAEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What name in ancient Rome was abbreviated “Sp.”?",
    "answer": "SPURIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Shields were used for the first time during a duel between what two brothers, who began quarrelling before they left the womb and did not stop until they had torn the kingdom of Argos into two parts? ACRISIUS and PROËTUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What father of Acrisius and Proëtus bequeathed Argos to the brothers jointly?",
    "answer": "ABAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "According to Aulus Gellius, what two authors both presented a tragedy before the aediles on the same day in the late 2nd century B.C.? One of these authors came from Pisaurum, while the other came from Brundisium. (LUCIUS) ACCIUS and (MARCUS) PACUVIUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Dedicated to a certain Baebius, what nine book work of Accius proposed a series of spelling reforms based on the principles of analogy?",
    "answer": "DIDASCALICA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb expergīscor, expergiscī, give the second person plural, pluperfect subjunctive.",
    "answer": "EXPERRĒCTĪ ESSĒTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Keeping all else the same, change that form to the future imperative.",
    "answer": "CAN’T BE DONE / DOESN’T EXIST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Besides its conjugation, to what two categories of verbs does expergīscor belong?",
    "answer": "DEPONENT, INCEPTIVE / INCHOATIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into Latin: The legate informed the commander that the soldiers were angry about his smell.",
    "answer": "FĒCIT MĪLITĒS DĒ ODŌRE (EIUS) IRĀTŌS ESSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into Latin: The soldiers did not come themselves because they were afraid that they would be killed by the odor. or CUM TIMĒRENT/METUERENT/VERĒRENTUR/PAVĒRENT…",
    "answer": "NĒ ODŌRE INTERFICERENTUR/NECĀRENTUR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into Latin: The odor was so foul that the legate could scarcely breathe in the commander’s presence. or APUD IMPERĀTŌREM/DUCEM Advanced – Preliminary Round 3",
    "answer": "SPĪRĀRE POSSET CŌRAM IMPERĀTŌRE/DUCE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The noun forms magnī, floccī, plūrīs, quantī, and tantī are often used to exemplify what use of the genitive case?",
    "answer": "GENITIVE OF (INDEFINITE) VALUE // GENITIVE OF QUALITY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What use of the genitive follows verbs such as damnō, absolvō, and arguō?",
    "answer": "GENITIVE OF CHARGE / PENALTY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Although usually expressed by the accusative case in prose, what corresponding use of the genitive can chiefly be found in poetry, as borrowed from Ancient Greek?",
    "answer": "GENITIVE OF EXCLAMATION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who combined the tradition of bugonia with the story of Aristaeus and Eurydice to end the fourth book of his Georgics?",
    "answer": "VERGIL / PUBLIUS VERGILIUS MARO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The story of Aristaeus replaced Vergil’s praise of what elegist when Augustus ordered its removal?",
    "answer": "CORNELIUS GALLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other work of Vergil discusses bees at length in the context of an extended metaphor about laboring north African citizens?",
    "answer": "AENEID"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On what island did Philoetius, Melantheus, and Eumaeus all serve as herdsmen in service of Odysseus?",
    "answer": "ITHACA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the suitors of Penelope was the first to die at the hands of Odysseus?",
    "answer": "ANTINOUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After the slaughter of the suitors, Odysseus spared a herald and a bard. Name either of these men. MEDON (THE HERALD) or PHEMIUS (THE BARD)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two Roman groups were first allowed to intermarry by the Lēx Canulēia, whose adoption ended the third secession of one of them? PLEBEIANS / PLEBS and PATRICIANS // PLĒBS and PATRĒS / PATRICIĪ",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The Lēx Canulēia was passed only four years after a group of decemvirī adopted what codification of Roman law?",
    "answer": "TWELVE TABLES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the decemvirī lusted after the girl Verginia, driving her father, Verginius, to kill her to defend her honor?",
    "answer": "APPIUS CLAUDIUS (CRASSUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the full Latin phrase and its English translation for the abbreviation loc. cit.",
    "answer": "IN A PREVIOUSLY CITED PLACE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the full Latin phrase and its English translation for the abbreviation s.l.",
    "answer": "SINE LOCŌ, WITHOUT (A) LOCATION / PLACE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the full Latin phrase and its English translation for the abbreviation s.l.a.n., an extension of the previous phrase.",
    "answer": "SINE LOCŌ ANNŌ (VEL) NŌMINE, WITHOUT PLACE, YEAR, (OR) NAME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage, which I will read twice and which has been adapted from a Latin translation of Shakespeare's Julius Caesar, then answer in LATIN the questions that follow: Amīcī, Cīvēs, Quirītēs, date mihi aurēs vestrās: adsum ut sepeliam Caesarem, nōn ut laudem. Quae scelesta hominēs fēcerint, mortuīs supervīvunt; quae bene, simul cum ossibus sepulcrō abscondī solent. Haec Caesaris sors estō. Nōbilis noster Brūtus dīcit Caesarem ambitiōsum esse: quod sī ita esset, gravissimum eius crīmen fateor: gravissimam poenam certē Caesar dat. The question: Quae mortuīs supervīvunt?",
    "answer": "QUAE SCELESTA FĒCĒRUNT / FĒCERINT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Antōnius dīcit sē facere nōlle?",
    "answer": "(DĪCIT SĒ) CAESAREM LAUDĀRE (NŌLLE)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Secundum Brūtum, quālis est Caesar?",
    "answer": "AMBITIŌSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which of the following Latin words does not belong because of meaning: īlex, iecur, farnus, cerasus?",
    "answer": "IECUR [OTHERS ARE TREES]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between farnus and fagus. ASH (TREE) and BEECH (TREE)",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which two of the following words refer to the same species of tree: ablēs, īlex, larīx, quercus, palma? ĪLEX and QUERCUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "In Book 15 of the Iliad, Zeus saves Hector by snapping the bow of what Greek archer, who then picks up a shield and a spear to fight beside his brother, Ajax?",
    "answer": "TEUCER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After Teucer returned home to Salamis, what father of his banished him because he believed Teucer to be complicit in the death of Ajax?",
    "answer": "TELAMON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Apollo’s oracle told Teucer that he should found a new Salamis on what island, where King Cinyras gave Teucer one of his daughters in marriage?",
    "answer": "CYPRUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The protests of Naevolus, Virro’s dinner party, Umbricius’ abandonment of Rome, and Domitian wondering how to cook a massive turbot are all contained within what author’s collection of 16 satires?",
    "answer": "(SATIRES OF) JUVENAL / OF (DECIMUS IŪNIUS) IUVENĀLIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Please answer the following question by giving your answer in Roman numerals with the use of your fingers: into many books did Juvenal divide his 16 satires?",
    "answer": "STUDENT SHOULD MAKE A “V” WITH TWO FINGERS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Please answer the following question by giving your answer in Roman numerals with the use of your fingers: in which of his satires did Juvenal declare “difficile est saturam nōn scrībere”?",
    "answer": "STUDENT SHOULD MAKE A “I” WITH ONE FINGER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What island did the Romans call Hibernia?",
    "answer": "IRELAND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What modern-day country most closely equates to the Roman region of Calēdonia?",
    "answer": "SCOTLAND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What city in modern-day England did the Romans call Colōnia Camulodūnum?",
    "answer": "COLCHESTER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What punctuation mark perhaps originally derives from the Latin interjection iō, reaching its modern form as the “i” gradually moved above the “o”?",
    "answer": "EXCLAMATION POINT(!)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The ampersand originated as a ligature of what Latin word for “and”?",
    "answer": "ET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "It is theorized that the question mark derives from the abbreviation qo, the shorthand of what Latin word?",
    "answer": "QUAESTIŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "To atone for the sins of the Second Punic War, the aediles commissioned what man to compose a maiden’s hymn in praise of Juno? He is, however, better known for translating Homer’s Odyssey into Latin.",
    "answer": "(LUCIUS) LIVIUS ANDRONICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "How many girls sang in the chorus of Andronicus’ hymn? It is the same number of girls that sang in the chorus of Horace’s Carmen Saeculāre some 200 years later.",
    "answer": "27"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After composing the Partheneion, into what professional organization was Andronicus admitted? The group was known to convene in the Temple of Minerva located on the Aventine Hill.",
    "answer": "COLLĒGIUM SCRĪBĀRUM HISTRIŌNUMQUE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What daughter of Theseus and Helen was given to Clytemnestra to be raised and eventually ended up as a priestess of Artemis living among the Taurians?",
    "answer": "IPHIGEN(E)IA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Hyginus, what woman almost blinded Iphigenia because she thought Iphigenia had killed Orestes?",
    "answer": "ELECTRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Strophius, a companion of Orestes, accompanied him to the land of the Taurians in hopes of curing Orestes’ madness?",
    "answer": "PYLADES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What emperor celebrated the memory of Julius Vindex, who had revolted in favor of him, after becoming the first of the four emperors to rule in 69 A.D.?",
    "answer": "(SERVIUS SULPICIUS) GALBA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Vindex committed suicide after losing a battle at Vesontio to what commander of Germania Superior?",
    "answer": "(LUCIUS) VERGINIUS RUFUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name, in order, the three emperors who ruled after Galba in 69 A.D.",
    "answer": "OTHO, VITELLIUS, VESPASIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which of the following words, if any, is not derived from the same Latin root as the others: appraise, entrepreneur, prison, reprehensible?",
    "answer": "APPRAISE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin noun with what meaning is “appraise” derived?",
    "answer": "PRETIUM – PRICE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which of these words, if any, is not derived from the same Latin root as the others: acquaintance, reconnoiter, notion, note.",
    "answer": "NOTE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate into Latin: The students asked their teacher from where the storm had arisen. or PETĪ(V)ĒRUNT Ā MAGISTRŌ/-Ā",
    "answer": "ESSET /"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate into Latin: The teacher responded by asking why the students were not working.",
    "answer": "DISCIPULĪ/-AE NŌN LABŌRĀRENT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate into Latin: Nevertheless, he was wondering whether the storm was a sign from the gods. or ...MĪRĀBĀTUR TEMPESTĀSNE ESSET... (-ne on first word in ind. question)",
    "answer": "SIGNUM/PORTENTUM/ŌMEN Ā DEĪS."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who advised selling slaves when they grew old in his treatise Dē Agrī Cultūra?",
    "answer": "CATŌ MAIOR / CATŌ CĒNSŌRĪNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work of Cato was a history of Rome in seven books?",
    "answer": "ORĪGINĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Cato’s Dē Agrī Cultūra was also known as Dē Rē Rūsticā. Name one author, besides Cato the Elder, who wrote a Dē Rē Rūsticā.",
    "answer": "REATINUS / VARRO OF REATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Roman general won the last notable triumph of Roman armies in the West by beating back the Hunnic chieftain Attila at Chalons?",
    "answer": "(FLAVIUS) AETIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What tribe’s help was enlisted in this victory?",
    "answer": "VISIGOTHS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What emperor executed Aetius because of corrupt political influences?",
    "answer": "VALENTINIAN III"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "At what city did all of the following events occur: King Codrus repelled an invasion through the voluntary sacrifice of his life; the demagogue Menestheus overthrew a famous king who had invited war with the Dioscuri; and king Cecrops ended the practice of human sacrifice?",
    "answer": "ATHENS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What king of Athens, the son of Hephaestus and Ge, was given to the daughters of Cecrops in a chest?",
    "answer": "ERICHTHONIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Codrus was the last king of Athens, which instituted the archonship shortly after his death?",
    "answer": "MEDON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Uh-oh... someone was listening to a lot of Kesha while writing their certamen questions... translate into English this line from Kesha’s debut studio album: Nōn meā interest quid vulgus loquātur. PEOPLE/CROWD/MULTITUDE/MASSES SAY(S) or IS/ARE SAYING",
    "answer": "IT DOESN’T MATTER TO ME / IT MAKES NO DIFFERENCE TO ME WHAT THE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now try this line from the lead single of the same album: Hāc nocte pugnātūra sum donec lucem sōlis vīderimus. or THIS NIGHT I’M ABOUT TO/GOING TO/INTENDING TO FIGHT UNTIL WE or (WILL) HAVE SEEN",
    "answer": "SEE THE LIGHT OF THE SUN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Drawing evidence from a surviving Etruscan painting of 300 B.C., what king of Rome was known to the later emperor Claudius as an Etruscan named Mastarna?",
    "answer": "SERVIUS TULLIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On the Aventine hill, the plebeian quarter of the city, Tullius established a cult to what deity?",
    "answer": "DIANA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the Pleiades was transformed into a doe by Artemis and repaid the goddess by stamping the golden horns of the Cerynitian Hind with Artemis’ name?",
    "answer": "TAŸGETE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Despite Artemis’ interventions, Zeus and Taÿgete had what son, an eponym of Sparta?",
    "answer": "LACEDAEMON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The character Terapontigonus must have been much less talkative than Plautus’ other braggart soldiers, given that he appears in what play, the shortest Plautine comedy at only 729 lines?",
    "answer": "CURCULIŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What play of Plautus features a botched exchange of prisoners-of-war when Hegio attempts to rescue one son, only to end up with both of them?",
    "answer": "CAPTĪVĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage, which I will read twice, then answer in LATIN the question that follows: Post paucōs diēs M. Cicerō cōnsul in senātū litterās recēpit, quās Allobrogēs per celerrimum nūntium miserant, in quibus scrīptum erat L. Catilīnam arma cēpisse cum magnā multitūdine comitum. Cicerō ubi intellegit, quantum perīculum reī pūblicae inpendēret, legiōnēs arcessīvit et in Etrūriam īvit. The question: Quid in litterīs scrīptum est?",
    "answer": "L. CATILĪNAM ARMA CĒPISSE (CUM MAGNĀ MULTITŪDINE COMITUM)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now answer in English. Where was Cicero when he received the letter?",
    "answer": "IN THE SENATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How did the letter reach Cicero from the Allobroges? Advanced – Semifinals",
    "answer": "VIA THE SWIFTEST MESSENGER / MESSAGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following interjections conveys a different feeling from the others: heu, ēn, ehem, ecce, ō?",
    "answer": "HEU"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Define heu.",
    "answer": "ALAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give an interjection that can mean “hey!”, as in the act of calling someone.",
    "answer": "HEUS / EHO / EHODUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Lacking the physical power to back up his “territorial aggression,” what man saw his insolence brutally punished when Odysseus snapped his jaw with a single, vicious right hook?",
    "answer": "ARNAEUS / IRUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What favor did Irus do for the suitors in exchange for getting scraps from their table?",
    "answer": "HE ACTED AS THEIR MESSENGER [ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What suitor forced Irus to box with the disguised Odysseus?",
    "answer": "ANTINOUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between frīgō and fricō. (TO / I) FRY // ROAST and (TO / I) RUB [RESPECTIVELY]",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between paviō and paveō. (TO / I) STRIKE and (TO / I) TREMBLE [RESPECTIVELY]",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between sapor and sopor. TASTE and SLEEP [RESPECTIVELY]",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Besides Scipio Aemilianus himself, name two authors who are considered members of the “Scipionic Circle”.",
    "answer": "POLYBIUS, FURIUS PHILUS, RUTILIUS RUFUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name another.",
    "answer": "[SEE ABOVE]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name another.",
    "answer": "[SEE ABOVE]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What device still kept time when placed in the house and during the night, as it was a water clock?",
    "answer": "CLEPSYDRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What time-keeping device did the Romans call either hōrologium or sōlārium?",
    "answer": "SUN-DIAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin term referred to both the panels in Roman wall decorations and the Roman tool for counting and math?",
    "answer": "ABACUS / ABACĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Are you a fan ~OF~ the genitive? If so, please translate this sentence into Latin using three different genitive constructions: The sailor’s son was not ashamed of his love for pirates.",
    "answer": "FĪLIUM NAUTAE NŌN PUDĒBAT/PUDUIT AMŌRIS PĪRĀTĀRUM."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Perhaps you are more devoted ~TO~ the dative? In that case, please translate this sentence into Latin using four different datives: The knife had to be snatched away from the boy by the father lest it be a disaster for the whole family.",
    "answer": "FAMILIAE ESSET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Finally, for those of you who love a good old-fashioned accusative, please translate this sentence into Latin using four different accusatives: We heard that the dog had concealed the bone smelling of meat from the farmer.",
    "answer": "AUDĪVIMUS CANEM OS CARNEM (RED)OLĒNS AGRICOLAM CĒLĀVISSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin word with what meaning do we derive the English word “fossil”?",
    "answer": "FODIŌ – (TO / I) DIG (UP)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin word with what meaning do we derive the English word “insinuate”?",
    "answer": "SINUS – CURVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin word with what meaning do we derive the English word “plunge”?",
    "answer": "PLUMBUM – LEAD"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, a native of Gaza, wrote two books of Īnstrūctiōnēs, which were two books of eighty hexameter poems, and books of acrostics?",
    "answer": "COMMODIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Carthaginian lawyer wrote a work on the metaphorical marriage of Mercury and philology?",
    "answer": "MARTIANUS CAPELLA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What professor, born in Burgidala, was a tutor for the late emperor Gratian and the author of the Bissula, a poem on a German slave woman?",
    "answer": "AUSONIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who successfully beat back the Alemanni on the Rhine frontier in 256 A.D. when his father Valerian left to meet Shapur in the East?",
    "answer": "GALLIENUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How many pretenders to the throne did Gallienus dispose of?",
    "answer": "THIRTY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Though his son was successful, Valerian met a tragic end at what town, resulting in his capture and death?",
    "answer": "EDESSA/CARRHAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man was punished not once but twice for his crimes, once by being a slave for eight years to the god Ares, and again by being transformed into a snake at the end of his life?",
    "answer": "CADMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Before his transformation, Cadmus became king of what group of people after he usurped the previous ruler’s throne?",
    "answer": "ILLYRIANS / ENCHELEANS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who aided Cadmus in this final conquest by marrying Lycotherses, Cadmus’ predecessor, and then killing him?",
    "answer": "AGAVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage, which I will read twice and which has been adapted from Cato’s Dē Agrī Cultūrā, then answer in ENGLISH the questions that follow: Pater familiās ubi ad vīllam vēnit, ubi larem familiārem salūtāvit, fundum eōdem diē, sī potest, circumeat; sī nōn eōdem diē, at postrīdiē. Ubi cognōvit, quōmodo fundus cultus sit operaque quae facta īnfectaque sint, postrīdiē vīlicum vocet et roget quid operis sit factum. Vocet quoque quid restet, possitne quae reliqua sint cōnficere, et quid factum vīnī, frūmentī aliārumque rērum omnium. The question: What should the pater familiās do on the same day as he arrives to the villa, if he is able?",
    "answer": "GO AROUND THE ESTATE [ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After asking the vīlicus what work has been done, what remains to be done, and whether it is possible to complete the remaining work, what should the pater familiās ask him?",
    "answer": "[ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The instances of sit in this passage have been changed from what archaic form, which derives from the Indo-European optative mood?",
    "answer": "SIET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Valerius Antias, Licinius Macer, Cato the Elder, Claudius Quadrigarius, Fabius Pictor, and Polybius were all used as sources for what work, whose numerous books were grouped into divisions of decades by their author?",
    "answer": "(LIVY’S) AB URBE CONDITĀ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which two of the authors mentioned in the tossup wrote in Greek? FABIUS PICTOR and POLYBIUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which of the authors mentioned in the tossup wrote an Annālēs in at least 75 books?",
    "answer": "VALERIUS ANTIAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What U.S. state says “with the sword [it] seeks tranquil peace under liberty” with the motto “ēnse petit placidam sub lībertāte quiētem?”",
    "answer": "MASSACHUSETTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What state says that “he who transplanted, sustains” with the motto “quī trānstulit, sustinet?”",
    "answer": "CONNECTICUT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What territory says that “John is his name” with the motto “Jōannēs est nōmen eius?”",
    "answer": "PUERTO RICO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Distinguish in meaning between the verbs esse and ēsse.",
    "answer": "(TO / I) BE AND (TO / I) EAT [RESPECTIVELY]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give one of the second person plural future imperatives of edō. EDITŌTE or ĒSTŌTE",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What English derivative of edō describes someone who is voraciously hungry or greedy?",
    "answer": "ESURIENT / EDACIOUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What god probably regretted hiding his lover Elare from his ever-jealous wife, since their son was the giant Tityus, who chased another of his lovers, Leto, across the earth?",
    "answer": "ZEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "How did Zeus manage to hide Elare?",
    "answer": "HE HID HER UNDERGROUND / IN THE EARTH [ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Before his death at the hands of the archer twins, Tityus had a daughter Europa, who herself bore what son and Argonaut to Poseidon?",
    "answer": "EUPHEMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After the Romans suffered the deaths of both Publius and Gnaeus Scipio, Scipio Africanus turned around the war in Spain by capturing what stronghold in 209 B.C., giving the Romans access to a large amount of silver, ships, and weapons?",
    "answer": "NEW CARTHAGE / CARTHĀGŌ NOVA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "In what battle of 206 B.C. did Scipio Africanus carry out a highly complicated double outflanking maneuver, which succeeded in defeating the Carthaginians so thoroughly that they had no field forces remaining in Spain?",
    "answer": "ILIPA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "The Roman victory at what battle can be partially credited to an intercepted message of Hasdrubal, which asked his brother to meet him in Umbria?",
    "answer": "METAURUS RIVER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into English: Caesar ā senātū poposcit ut sibi absentī licēret alterum cōnsulātum petere.",
    "answer": "CONSULSHIP/ ... THAT IT BE PERMITTED FOR HIM, ABSENT, TO SEEK…"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into English: Cum cōnsulēs Caesarī suscēnsērent, nōn poterant tamen eum impedīre quōminus mīlitēs in Italiam dūceret.",
    "answer": "FROM LEADING HIS SOLDIERS INTO ITALY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into English: Senātōribus ad Graeciam fugientibus, Caesar vacuam urbem ingressus dictātōrem sē fēcit.",
    "answer": "CAESAR, HAVING ENTERED THE EMPTY CITY, MADE HIMSELF DICTATOR."
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author structured his magnum opus in opposition to Lucan, claiming to sing of “wars between brothers” as opposed to Lucan’s “wars more than civil” and publishing a mythological poem as opposed to Lucan’s historical one with the Thebaid?",
    "answer": "PAPINIUS STATIUS [PROMPT ON “STATIUS”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work of Statius was unfinished and was concerned with the life of Achilles?",
    "answer": "ACHILLEID"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work of Statius was five books of verses in various meters?",
    "answer": "SILVAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Book 8 of the Aeneid, Turnus sends a herald to persuade what hero and founder of Argyripa to come to his aid?",
    "answer": "DIOMEDES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What seer did Turnus send to ask for Diomedes’ help?",
    "answer": "VENULUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "At the same time in the narrative of the Aeneid, Aeneas goes to Pallanteum, where the inhabitants are performing a sacred rite dedicated to what local hero, who rid the area of a great monster?",
    "answer": "HERCULES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Later granted the title of corrēctor Lūcāniae, what former emperor of the imperium Galliārum was defeated at Campī Catalaunīī and marched in the triumph of Aurelian along with Zenobia?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS PIUS) TETRICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who had preceded Tetricus as emperor of the imperium Galliārum?",
    "answer": "VICTORINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Emboldened by the Roman disaster at Cannae, who in 215 B.C. entered into a compact of mutual assistance with Hannibal after consolidating the Greek confederacy?",
    "answer": "PHILIP V"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Instead of a war of attrition, where did the Romans decisively defeat the phalanxes of Macedon in the Second Macedonian War?",
    "answer": "CYNOSCEPHALAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Betrothed to the princess Clisithera, who seduced the Cretan queen at the suggestion of Nauplius, later killing her and his fiancée to seize the throne from his adoptive father Idomeneus?",
    "answer": "LEUCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "An alternate ending to Idomeneus’ return to Crete says that when his fleet was stranded in a storm, he vowed to do what?",
    "answer": "[ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Aelius Lampridius, Aelius Spartianus, Flavius Vopiscus, Julius Capitolinus, Trebellius Pollio, and Volcacius Gallicanus were all the supposed authors of what historical work, which contained biographies of emperors from Nerva to Carinus and Numerian?",
    "answer": "HISTORIA AUGUSTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What late Latin author wrote a history that was supposed to be a continuation of Tacitus’ Historiae?",
    "answer": "AMMIANUS MARCELLINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which of the following words, if any, is not derived from the same Latin root as the others: pellet, pillow, platoon, pill?",
    "answer": "PILLOW"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin word with what meaning is “pillow” derived?",
    "answer": "PULVĪNUS – LITTLE CUSHION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin word with what meaning are all the others ultimately derived?",
    "answer": "PĪLA – BALL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of the defective verbs odī, meminī, and coepī, which verbs, if any, lack the future infinitive?",
    "answer": "MEMINĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Of the defective verbs odī, meminī, and coepī, which verbs, if any, lack the imperative? COEPĪ and ODĪ",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "As you may know, odī, meminī, and coepī are verbs that have lost the present system and only decline in the perfect. Name two verbs that have lost the perfect system and only decline in the present. Advanced – Finals",
    "answer": "FĀRI, QUEŌ, NEQUEŌ, QUAESŌ, OVĀRE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using the verbs serō and sērō, translate the apodosis of the following sentence into Latin: If the senators had come too late for the sake of joining words, Cincinnatus would have already sowed his fields and bolted his door.",
    "answer": "ET IĀNUAM/PORTAM SĒRĀVISSET"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate the protasis of that sentence, using a different serō and a different sērō. SĪ SENĀTŌRĒS SĒRŌ VĒNISSENT VERBA SERENDĪ (or VERBŌRUM",
    "answer": "SERENDŌRUM) CAUSĀ/GRATIĀ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into Latin, using the verbs metō and mētior: If we had measured the field more diligently, we would have reaped more grain.",
    "answer": "MESSUISSEMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work subtly attacks the sycophantic and artificial nature of rhetoric during the Empire by claiming that tragedy has replaced the role of rhetoric in society? It is framed as a conversation between Vipstanus Messalla, Marius Aper, and Curiatius Maternus at which its author, Tacitus, claimed to have been present.",
    "answer": "DIALOGUS (DĒ ŌRĀTŌRIBUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work of Quintilian also discusses the decline of oratory in Rome, although he was more straightforward with his criticisms, probably due to his good favor with the emperor Vespasian?",
    "answer": "DĒ CAUSĪS CORRUPTAE ĒLOQUENTIAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Under which two of the Five Good Emperors did Tacitus enjoy most of his literary and political success, claiming that he would save the biographies of their lives for his old age as it was “richer and less risky material?” He died, however, before he did so. NERVA and TRAJAN",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The harbor at Ithaca was named after what god, who became the grandfather of Polyphemus through his daughter Thoösa, father of Scylla by the nymph Crataeis, and the progenitor of many other monsters by the sea-monstress Ceto?",
    "answer": "PHORCYS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "However, Apollonius of Rhodes claims that Crataeis is simply an epithet of what goddess?",
    "answer": "HECATE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What monstrous half nymph, half speckled snake was a child of Phorcys and Ceto?",
    "answer": "ECHIDNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Distinguish in meaning between the idioms poenam dāre and poenam sūmere, which are opposites.",
    "answer": "TO BE PUNISHED AND TO PUNISH [RESPECTIVELY]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give a one-word Latin synonym for the Latin idiom ter et quater.",
    "answer": "IDENTIDEM / SAEPENUMERŌ / CRĒBRŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give a two-word Latin idiom that is synonymous with the Latin noun perfidia.",
    "answer": "FIDĒS PŪNICA"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "At what battle of 506 B.C. did other Latin cities seek freedom from the Etruscans, having felt encouraged by Rome’s example?",
    "answer": "(BATTLE OF) ARICIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What ruler of Cumae assisted the Latin forces to achieve this victory?",
    "answer": "ARISTODEMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which ally of Superbus and king of Clusium was on the losing end of Aricia?",
    "answer": "(LARS) PORSENNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author was born in the same Spanish town as Quintilian in the fourth century A.D. and wrote a poem entitled Psychomachia, discussing the struggle between the virtues and vices in the human soul?",
    "answer": "PRUDENTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence into English: Tabernam ingressus, vir Rōmānus duōs digitōs tollit et “velim,” inquit, “potiōnēs quīnque.” HAVING ENTERED A TAVERN/INN/etc., A ROMAN MAN LIFTS/HOLDS UP TWO",
    "answer": "FINGERS AND SAYS “I’D LIKE FIVE DRINKS”"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence: Tabernārius, arbitrāns virum iam ēbrium esse, mentītus est sē nihil habēre nisī vīnum vapidum.",
    "answer": "SPOILED/BAD/FLAT WINE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence: Hīs verbīs audītīs, trēs partēs aliōrum bibentium discessērunt ad novam tabernam reperiendam.",
    "answer": "DRINKERS/DRINKING PEOPLE LEFT TO FIND A NEW TAVERN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What group of monsters often brought about rain, hail, and snow with their magic as sorcerers on the island of Rhodes and once nursed the infant Poseidon to protect him from Cronos?",
    "answer": "TELCHINES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What fanged and taloned women, daughters of Nyx, carried off the bodies of the dead to the underworld and represented the inevitability of death?",
    "answer": "KERES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What group of nymphs from the Aegean islands were loyal to Dionysus and were attacked and defeated by Perseus in an attempt to prevent the intrusion of the god into Argos?",
    "answer": "HALIAE / WOMEN OF THE SEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the terms monopodium, cathedra, sella curūlis, and mēnsa delphica, which refers to an armless chair with a curved back that was frequently used by teachers of rhetoric?",
    "answer": "CATHEDRA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the chairs mentioned in the toss-up was a stool with curved legs of ivory used by magistrates?",
    "answer": "SELLA CURŪLIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the chairs mentioned in the toss-up was a three-legged chair?",
    "answer": "MĒNSA DELPHICA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage, which I will read twice and which has been adapted from Livy’s description of Cicero’s death, then answer in ENGLISH the questions that follow: Taedium tandem eum et fugae et vītae cēpit; regressusque ad superiōrem vīllam, “Moriar,” inquit, “in patriā saepe servātā.” Satis dīcitur servōs fortiter fidēliterque parātōs fuisse ad dimicandum; sed ipsum quiētōs patī iussisse. Caput praecīsum est nec satis crūdēlitātī mīlitum fuit. Manūs quoque praecīdērunt. Ita relātum est caput ad Antōnium iussūque eius inter duās manūs in Rōstrīs positum. The question: To where did Cicero, tired of flight and life, return?",
    "answer": "PRECEDING VILLA // THE VILLA HE USED TO LIVE IN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where does Cicero say he will die?",
    "answer": "IN THE FATHERLAND HE HAS OFTEN SAVED [ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What were Cicero’s slaves prepared to do for him?",
    "answer": "FIGHT / ATTACK [ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A short hexameter poem that describes the morning ritual of the average Roman peasant farmer, a sketch in elegiac couplets that describes a female innkeeper who draws customers to her inn by dancing, and an epyllion of the story of the father-betraying Scylla are all contained in what collection of poems perhaps written by a young Vergil?",
    "answer": "APPENDIX VERGILIĀNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the name of the first poem described in the toss-up?",
    "answer": "MORĒTUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What is the name of the second poem described in the toss-up?",
    "answer": "CŌPA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After winning all of the events at the Panathenaic Games, who was ambushed on his return home to Crete, necessitating the tribute which Athens paid to king Minos?",
    "answer": "ANDROGEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Under what name was Androgeus worshipped at games in Athens dedicated in his honor?",
    "answer": "EURYGYES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Androgeus was survived by two sons, who were kidnapped by Heracles during his adventures. Name these two sons, one of whom shares his name with the father of Amphitryon and the other of whom shares his name with the father of Eurystheus. ALCAEUS and STHENELUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Sēnī, vīcēnī, dēnī, septēnī, and bīnī are all examples of what type of numeral?",
    "answer": "DISTRIBUTIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin interrogative word can be answered by the use of distributive numerals?",
    "answer": "QUOTĒNĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Distinguish in meaning between terna rostra and trīna rostra. ROSTRA(S) / SPEAKING-PLATFORMS IN THREES and",
    "answer": "THREE ROSTRA(S) / SPEAKING-PLATFORMS [RESPECTIVELY]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Jugurtha was summoned to Rome to testify in a bribery investigation of what consul of 111 B.C., who was the first to invade Numidia during the Jugurthine War?",
    "answer": "(LUCIUS CALPURNIUS) BESTIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After Bestia had agreed to a peace settlement that heavily favored Jugurtha, what tribune demanded an investigation of Bestia and asked Jugurtha to be brought to Rome on safe conduct?",
    "answer": "MEMMIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "While Jugurtha was in Rome, he killed which of his cousins, who was residing in Rome in hopes that the Romans would recognize him as king of Numidia?",
    "answer": "MASSIVA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the motto of the University of Cambridge: Hinc lūcem et pōcula sacra.",
    "answer": "ENLIGHTENMENT AND PRECIOUS KNOWLEDGE [ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin for the motto of Oxford University.",
    "answer": "DOMINUS ILLŪMINĀTIŌ MEA"
  },
  {
    "category": "faulty",
    "question": "Translate the motto of University College London: Cūnctī adsint meritaeque expectent praemia palmae.",
    "answer": "[ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat “ringor”?",
    "answer": "(TO / I) SNARL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat “scobs”?",
    "answer": "SAWDUST / FILINGS / SCRAPINGS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat “cassis”?",
    "answer": "SNARE / NET"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Because his son Clinia wanted to marry a poor girl, Menedemus sends him to war in Asia. Due to great remorse, Menedemus toils endlessly on his land as self-imposed penance. This is the beginning of the plot of what play of Terence, his third to be performed?",
    "answer": "HEAUTONTĪMŌRŪMENOS / (THE) SELF-TORMENTER / (THE) SELF-PUNISHER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "The original Heautontīmōrūmenos was written by what Greek playwright?",
    "answer": "MENANDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What comedy of Terence compares two different systems of upbringing, as one of its main characters, Demea, raises his son Ctesiphon with the utmost strictness, while his other son, Aeschinus, is raised very freely by his brother Micio?",
    "answer": "ADELPHOE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After handing over the Balkan peninsula to the Goths, what emperor later rushed back to repel the invaders from the peninsula, although his attempt was cut short by his defeat and death at Abrittus?",
    "answer": "DECIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Decius’s defeat at Abrittus was partially due to the disloyalty of what governor of Moesia, whose troops had proclaimed him emperor?",
    "answer": "TREBONIANUS GALLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Trebonianus Gallus had ruled alongside him as joint Augustus?",
    "answer": "VOLUSIANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what two Latin nouns with what meanings do we derive the English word “portcullis”? PORTA -- GATE and COLUM – STRAINER",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin noun with what meaning do we derive the English word “bail”?",
    "answer": "BAIULUS – CARRIER / STEWARD / PORTER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin word with what meaning do we derive the English word “search”?",
    "answer": "CIRCUS – CIRCLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Heracles faced off against Echemus in an attempt to regain the Peloponnese, though he failed to due to his inability to interpret the oracle which told him to wait for the “third crop”?",
    "answer": "HYLLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Two generations later, what descendant of Heracles finally won back the Peloponnese after winning a duel against king Tisamenus of Argos?",
    "answer": "TEMENUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In 88 B.C., which tribune proposed to distribute the newly enfranchised Italians among all the pre-existing thirty-five tribes and to transfer the command in the war against Mithridates from Sulla to Marius?",
    "answer": "SULPICIUS RUFUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "After this legislation, Sulla marched on Rome. Though he did not interfere with the consular elections, which successful candidate did he restrain from changing the newly amended Roman constitution?",
    "answer": "(L. CORNELIUS) CINNA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What unfortunate king of Orchomenus lost two children to a prophecy fabricated by his second wife, two to the murderous tendencies of his third, and the last to the insanity that plagued him as punishment for taking care of the infant Dionysus?",
    "answer": "ATHAMAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name Athamas’ third wife, who intended to kill the sons of Athamas and Ino but ended up being tricked into killing her own children?",
    "answer": "THEMISTO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Italian rhetorician took part in Julian’s expeditions against the Parthians and wrote a work mimicking Livy’s magnum opus not only in concept, as it recorded Roman history from Romulus to the death of Jovian, but also in name?",
    "answer": "EUTROPIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was the name of Eutropius’ work?",
    "answer": "BREVIĀRIUM AB URBE CONDITĀ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a single word, give the Latin for the fraction “seven-twelfths.”",
    "answer": "SEPTUNX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give a Latin synonym for “dimidium.”",
    "answer": "SĒMIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give a single Latin word meaning “three-fourths.”",
    "answer": "DŌDRĀNS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What man won the corōna grāminea for his bravery in the Social War and fought against the Cimbri and Teutones before he famously twice marched on Rome and became dictator?",
    "answer": "(LUCIUS CORNELIUS) SULLA (FELIX)"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What consul of 82 B.C. and son of Sulla’s great rival was killed at Praeneste after it was captured by Sulla’s troops under Quintus Lucretius Ofella?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) MARIUS THE YOUNGER / MARIUS MINOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Name Marius the Younger’s consular colleague, who fled from Sulla to Africa, where he was later executed by Pompey the Great.",
    "answer": "(CN. PAPIRIUS) CARBO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The name of which American state is also the 2nd person singular present active subjunctive of a Latin verb meaning “to weave”?",
    "answer": "TEXAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Using the name of a different American state, which is home to many alligators, as a Latin adjective, give the Latin nominative singular for the English phrase the rather tall flowering tree.",
    "answer": "ALTIOR FLORIDA ARBOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Using the name of a different American state, found in the former stage name of Miley Cyrus, as a Latin adjective, give the Latin nominative singular for the English phrase the 41st mountainous state.",
    "answer": "MONTĀNA CĪVITĀS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who helped Zeus seduce Nemesis by taking the form of an eagle and chasing a swan that was actually Zeus into Nemesis’ lap?",
    "answer": "APHRODITE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to the lost epic Cypria, Zeus seduced Nemesis while the goddess of revenge was in the form of what animal?",
    "answer": "GOOSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What deity was the mother of Nemesis, the Fates, and a variety of other abstract deities by her husband Erebus?",
    "answer": "NYX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "After the death of Domitian, what Roman author from Aquinum began writing five books of sixteen satires, in which he coined the famous phrase “pānem et circēnsēs”?",
    "answer": "JUVENAL / DECIMUS IUNIUS IUVENALIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "In what meter were Juvenal’s satires written?",
    "answer": "DACTYLIC HEXAMETER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Juvenal was called fācundus by what other poet of the Silver Age, who was known for his witty epigrams?",
    "answer": "Martial"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using the noun ornāmentum, ornāmentī, say in Latin: Cornelia said that her sons were her jewels.",
    "answer": "CORNĒLIA DĪXIT SUŌS FĪLIŌS SUA ŌRNĀMENTA ESSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using the verb tradō, tradere, say in Latin: It is said that Homer wrote poems.",
    "answer": "TRĀDITUR HOMĒRUM CARMINA SCRĪPSISSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence into Latin: Will you dare to kill Marius, the savior of the republic?",
    "answer": "IF THIS IS THE CASE TŪ / VŌS CAN BE OMITTED)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Sometimes adorned with statues and separating the city street from the atrium, what courtyard in the Roman house served as the gathering place of clients awaiting to be admitted to the atrium by the patron?",
    "answer": "VĒSTIBULUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What was the name for the type of atrium which contained neither an impluvium nor a compluvium?",
    "answer": "ĀTRIUM TESTŪDINĀTUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Images of which spirits of the pantry, to whom ancient Romans would set aside a portion of every family meal, were to be found in an atrium?",
    "answer": "(DĪ) PENĀTĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Holders of what position issue proclamations of “non possumus,” speak “ex cathedrā,” and are elected “ianuīs clausīs” in the Sistine Chapel?",
    "answer": "(CATHOLIC) POPE / BISHOP OF ROME / PONTIFEX MAXIMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Pope Urban II used what two-word Latin phrase, literally translating to “God wills it,” to call the First Crusade in 1095?",
    "answer": "DEUS VULT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What four-word Latin phrase describing the transitory nature of human vanities is intoned at the coronation of a pope?",
    "answer": "SĪC TRĀNSIT GLŌRIA MUNDĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What lover of alliteration gives us lines such as “at tuba terribilī sonitū taratantara dīxit” and “Ō Tite, tūte, Tati, tibi tanta, tyranne, tulīstī” in his 18-book poem, the Annālēs?",
    "answer": "(QUINTUS) ENNIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What city in the region of Calabria was the birthplace of Ennius?",
    "answer": "RUDIAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Ennius claimed to have “three hearts” because of his ability to speak two languages in addition to Latin. Name either of these languages. GREEK or OSCAN",
    "answer": "3"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who protected Eriboea from Minos and later dove into the sea to prove his parentage while journeying from Athens to Crete, where he planned to kill the Minotaur?",
    "answer": "THESEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "During his dive, Theseus met what wife of Poseidon?",
    "answer": "AMPHITRITE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What item, besides the ring, may Theseus have received from Amphitrite?",
    "answer": "ROBE / WREATH / (GOLDEN) CROWN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following nouns, if any, does not belong because of gender: mors, amor, arbor, vīs?",
    "answer": "AMOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of the following nouns, if any, is of the same gender as amor: caupō, viscera, ingenium, salūs?",
    "answer": "CAUPŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of what gender are the nouns pelagus, vulgus, and impedīmenta?",
    "answer": "NEUTER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "The Peripatetic Cratippus and the plāgōsus Orbilius both taught what Latin poet, whose involvement at the Battle of Philippi is mentioned in the third of his four books of Odes?",
    "answer": "HORACE / Q. HORATIUS FLACCUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Horace’s very first Ode opens with an dedication to what patron of his, whom Horace describes as “descended from ancient kings?”",
    "answer": "(C. CILNIUS) MAECENAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work of Horace, published simultaneously with his Epodes, includes an anecdote about a chance encounter on the Via Sacra?",
    "answer": "SATIRES / SATURAE / SERMONĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Warned that treachery would come from within his own family, what king immediately suspected the half-Greek sons of his daughter Chalciope and her Greek husband Phrixus, not realizing that it would be love, not ethnicity, that would lead his other daughter Medea to betray him?",
    "answer": "AEETES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Chalciope and Phrixus probably didn’t do much to divert this suspicion by waxing lyrical about the renowned and often divine lineages of the visiting Argonauts while introducing them to the Colchian king?",
    "answer": "ARGUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Argus later led Jason to his first meeting with Medea, who gave him a protective drug derived from a plant growing in the blood of what Titan, nailed on a cliff on Mount Caucasus for thirty thousand years?",
    "answer": "PROMETHEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between grex and prex. FLOCK / GROUP / HERD and PRAYER",
    "answer": "4"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between nimis and nemus. TOO MUCH and GLADE / (SACRED) GROVE",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning between ars and artus. SKILL / CRAFT / ART and JOINT / LIMB",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Claiming that Diana had gifted him a white fawn, which former Marian lieutenant led a revolt in Spain and managed to defeat Pompey twice before being assassinated in 73",
    "answer": "(Q.) SERTORIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was the traitor who assassinated Sertorius but was executed by Pompey when he tried to surrender?",
    "answer": "(M.) PERPERNA (VENTO)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In exchange for financial aid, to what king of Pontus did Sertorius promise to send veterans to train the king’s armies?",
    "answer": "MITHRIDATES VI / THE GREAT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a participle, say in Latin: “We must remain for three days.”",
    "answer": "NOBĪS TRĒS DIĒS (RĒ)MANENDUM EST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a participle, say in Latin: “We were going to sail to Athens in the summer.”",
    "answer": "ERĀMUS NAVIGĀTURĪ ATHĒNĀS AESTĀTE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Using a participle, say in Latin: “The consul must always spare his enemies.”",
    "answer": "HOSTIBUS / INIMĪCĪS Ā CONSULE SEMPER PARCENDUM EST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What work of Latin literature, an imitation of Hesiod’s Works and Days, is a four-book didactic poem written by Vergil to instruct his readers on various agricultural topics?",
    "answer": "GEORGICS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What mythological story features prominently in book 4 of the Georgics?",
    "answer": "ARISTAEUS AND EURYDICE / ARISTAEUS AND HIS BEES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other work of Vergil imitates Theocritus’ Idylls and consists of a set of 10 pastoral poems?",
    "answer": "BUCOLICS / ECLOGUES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin noun, with what meaning, do we derive “inveigle,” “antler,” “binoculars,” and “monocle”?",
    "answer": "OCULUS - EYE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin noun, with what meaning, do we derive “chivalry” and “cavalier”?",
    "answer": "CABALLUS - HORSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin noun, with what meaning, do we derive “easel”?",
    "answer": "ASINUS - DONKEY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, proclaimed emperor by troops in Britain, crossed over to Gaul in 197 A.D. and fought a decisive battle at Lugdunum against Septimius Severus, who would defeat him to become the unrivaled ruler of the empire?",
    "answer": "5"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other rival of Septimius Severus, who was proclaimed emperor by the troops in Syria, was killed as he was trying to flee across the Euphrates?",
    "answer": "(CAIUS) PESCENNIUS NIGER"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Name one of the three battles which Pescennius lost to Septimius Severus.",
    "answer": "CYZICUS / NICAEA / ISSUS (RIVER)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man recruited his brother, two of his nephews, his brother-in-law, and his new son-in-law, among others, to aid his other son-in-law in retaking the kingship of Thebes from his treacherous brother?",
    "answer": "ADRASTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name any three of the men cryptically referred to in the tossup.",
    "answer": "AMPHIARAUS, TYDEUS, POLYNEICES, ETEOCLES."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Adrastus had married his two daughters to Polyneices and Tydeus because a seer had told him to “yoke his daughters to a lion and a boar.” In what context had Adrastus realized that Polyneices and Tydeus were the lion and boar in question?",
    "answer": "[ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage from a narrator about a sacred shrine at Rome, which I will read twice, then answer in LATIN the question that follows: Audīvī apud Catinēnsīs esse Cereris sacrārium. In sacrārium illud virīs intrāre nōn licēre omnēs sciunt. fāma est mulierēs et virginēs ibi sacra cōnficere solēre. In eō sacrāriō fuisse signum Cereris perantīquum multī affirmant. hoc signum servōs Cicerō dīxit nocte ex illō locō sustulisse; omnibus rem atrōcissimam uīsam esse. The question: Quibus in sacrārium intrāre nōn licet?",
    "answer": "VIRĪS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quae in sacrāriō cōnficiendōrum sacrōrum causā manent?",
    "answer": "MULIERĒS ET VIRGINĒS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What beehive-shaped stone marks the spot where two eagles met to determine the center of the world?",
    "answer": "OMPHALOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What priestess sat near the Omphalos and uttered oracles?",
    "answer": "PYTHIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What general in the East proclaimed himself emperor because he heard false rumors that the emperor Marcus Aurelius had died?",
    "answer": "AVIDIUS CASSIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "At what battle in 165 A.D. did Avidius Cassius win a decisive victory against the Parthians?",
    "answer": "DURA EUROPUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What early Latin playwright is believed to have invented the genre of the fābula praetexta, which were tragic plays that dealt with Roman subjects instead of tales from Greek mythology?",
    "answer": "(GNAEUS) NAEVIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name one of Naevius’ two known fābulae praetextae.",
    "answer": "ROMULUS / CLASTIDIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What English word meaning “talkative” is derived from a third-conjugation deponent verb meaning “to speak”?",
    "answer": "LOQUACIOUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What English word meaning “subservient” is derived from a third-conjugation deponent verb meaning “to follow”?",
    "answer": "OBSEQUIOUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What English word meaning “friendly” or “easy to talk to” is derived from a first-conjugation deponent meaning “to speak”?",
    "answer": "AFFABLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb prōsum give the first person plural imperfect active indicative.",
    "answer": "PRŌDERAMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb afferō give the third person plural future perfect passive indicative.",
    "answer": "ALLĀTI/AE/A ERUNT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb malō give the second person plural present active indicative. 2018 Yale Certamen Invitational Advanced – Preliminary Round 2",
    "answer": "7"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Latin author of the first century B.C., considered the best elegist of his time by his contemporaries, addressed varied figures in his poetry, including Cerinthus, Marathus, Nemesis, and Delia?",
    "answer": "(ALBIUS) TIBULLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Tibullus’ third book of poems contains six poems by what Roman author—the only Latin poetess whose work comes down to us?",
    "answer": "SULPICIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What other Roman poet and author of the Metamorphoses was a member of Messalla Corvinus’ literary circle with Tibullus?",
    "answer": "(PUBLIUS) OVID(IUS) (NASO)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the genitive is found in phrases such as fortiōra animālium and ubicumque terrārum?",
    "answer": "PARTITIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the genitive is found in phrases such as īrae remedia and fuga labōrum?",
    "answer": "OBJECTIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the genitive is found in the following sentence: Iūstum et tenācem prōpositī virum.",
    "answer": "WITH VERBAL ADJECTIVES IN -AX / SPECIAL ADJECTIVES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After Heracles completed his twelve labors, he decided to take revenge upon those who had risen up against him. What son of Neleus did Heracles shoot down in the form of an eagle during his invasion of Pylos, since the youth had been granted the power to shapeshift by his grandfather Poseidon?",
    "answer": "PERICLYMENUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Heracles fought a war against a set of Siamese twins when he sought to raid the kingdom of what man, whom he had earlier visited for his fifth labor?",
    "answer": "AUGE(I)AS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When Heracles finally defeated Augeas, he placed which son of his upon the throne as a reward for standing up for him when his father had refused Heracles payment.",
    "answer": "PHYLEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What renegade pestered the Second Triumvirate with piracy and threats to withhold grain from Rome until Agrippa finally defeated him in 36 B.C.?",
    "answer": "SEXTUS POMPEY"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Near what Sicilian city did this battle occur?",
    "answer": "NAULOCHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What treaty had been signed in 39 B.C. between the Second Triumvirate and Sextus Pompey but failed because the Triumvirate neglected to uphold their terms?",
    "answer": "TREATY OF MISENUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give an antonym for the Latin word palam.",
    "answer": "CLAM / FŪRTIM / OCCULTĒ / CALLIM / LATENTER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give an antonym for the Latin word possum.",
    "answer": "NEQUEŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give an antonym for the Latin word quisque.",
    "answer": "NEMO / NULLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author surprisingly rejected chronological arrangement in his biographies, choosing instead to insert synchronic descriptions of the various aspects of emperors’ personalities in his Dē Vītā Caesārum?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS) SUETONIUS (TRANQUILLUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man is the last subject of the Dē Vītā Caesārum chronologically?",
    "answer": "DOMITIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To what man, Suetonius’ patron, is the work dedicated?",
    "answer": "SEPTICIUS CLARUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate this line from Book 1 of the Aeneid into English: Semper honōs nōmenque tuum laudēsque manēbunt.",
    "answer": "YOUR HONOR AND NAME AND PRAISE(S) WILL REMAIN FOREVER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this line from Book 1 of the Aeneid into English: Sunt lacrimae rērum et mentem mortālia tangunt.",
    "answer": "/ MORTAL THINGS AFFECT THE MIND"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate this line from Book 1 of the Aeneid into English: Solve metūs; feret haec aliquam tibi fāma salūtem.",
    "answer": "WILL BEAR SOME HEALTH / SAFETY FOR YOU"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name the dynasty described by the following clues. The pale-faced progenitor of this dynasty perished in modern-day York. The most prominent member of this dynasty had three sons who all ruled Rome. The last member of this dynasty advocated for a return to paganism at the expense of Christianity, for which he earned the title, “the Apostate”. For ten points, name this dynasty, named after the first emperor of Rome to convert to Christianity.",
    "answer": "DYNASTY OF CONSTANTINE (I / THE GREAT) / CONSTANTINIAN DYNASTY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Constantine proclaimed religious freedom for Christians in the Roman empire through what edict of 313 A.D.?",
    "answer": "EDICT OF MILAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where, in 325 A.D, did Constantine the Great summon three hundred bishops in hopes to establish unity across Christendom?",
    "answer": "9"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage, adapted from Caesar’s Dē Bellō Gallicō, which I will read twice, then answer in ENGLISH the question that follows: Caesarī omnia ūnō tempore erant agenda: vēxillum prōpōnendum, signum tubā dandum, ab opere revocandī mīlitēs, aciēs īnstruenda. Magnam partem hārum rērum brevitas temporis accessusque hostium impediēbant. Hīs difficultātibus duae rēs erant subsidiō: scientia atque ūsus mīlitum, quod proeliīs exercitātī erant. The question: name two things Caesar had to do at one time, as mentioned in the passage.",
    "answer": "TO CONSTRUCT THE BATTLE LINE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Answer in English: name two factors impeding the accomplishment of these to-dos. THE SHORTNESS OF TIME and THE APPROACH OF THE ENEMIES",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Answer in Latin: quōrum mīlitēs perītī erant?",
    "answer": "PROELIŌRUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Because she had been a devoted bacchant, what wife of Lycus was posthumously honored by Dionysus with a spring after Amphion and Zethus tied her to a bull and killed her?",
    "answer": "DIRCE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "On what Theban mountain did Dionysus create this spring?",
    "answer": "CITHAERON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In other times, Mt. Cithaeron was the haunt of what kind of animal, which either Heracles or Alcathous slew?",
    "answer": "(CITHAERONIAN) LION"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Some attorneys devote a portion of their time to cases in which they represent the indigent and thus necessarily forego payment. What is the Latin phrase for this sort of work?",
    "answer": "PRŌ BONŌ (PŪBLICŌ) / PRO BONO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A legal writ protecting an individual against arbitrary imprisonment is represented by two-word Latin phrase?",
    "answer": "HABEĀS CORPUS / HABEAS CORPUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What two-word Roman legal phrase attributed by Cicero to a judge literally means “to whom for a benefit?”",
    "answer": "10"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quoted in the epitaph of T.S. Eliot’s The Waste Land, what Roman picaresque novel in thirty books was written by a certain arbiter ēlegantiae named Petronius in Nero’s court?",
    "answer": "SATYRICON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Give the English term for the combination of prose and poetry that the Satyricon employs.",
    "answer": "MENIPPEAN SATIRE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "A story of a werewolf interrupts what scene of Petronius’ Satyricon, its longest surviving part?",
    "answer": "BANQUET OF TRIMALCHIO / CĒNA TRIMALCHIŌNIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A payment of 25,000 sesterces to every member of the Praetorian Guard allowed what emperor to rise to the throne, though he was sentenced to death by Septimius Severus soon afterward?",
    "answer": "DIDIUS JULIANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name Didius Julianus’ predecessor who took power after Commodus was strangled in 192 A.D.",
    "answer": "PERTINAX"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What father-in-law of Pertinax was Didius Julianus’ rival in this auction for the Emperorship, promising a measly 20,000 sesterces?",
    "answer": "(T. FLAVIUS CLAUDIUS) SULPICIANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence from Latin to English: “Imperātor impius in arēnam intrāvit ut gladiātor fieret.”",
    "answer": "(INTO) THE ARENA TO BECOME A GLADIATOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence from Latin to English: “Nero erat imperātor tam scelestus ut omnēs senātorēs interficere eum cuperent.”",
    "answer": "ALL THE SENATORS WANTED TO KILL HIM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence from Latin to English: “Philosophus rogat quārē hominēs iniustī sint.”",
    "answer": "THE PHILOSOPHER ASKS WHY MEN ARE UNJUST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "While living at Pelops’ court in Pisa, what man became so enamored with the beauty of Pelops’ son Chrysippus that he abducted him and brought him back to Thebes?",
    "answer": "LAIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who did Laius encounter at a crossroads on the way back from Delphi and insult, not knowing that the man was his son?",
    "answer": "OEDIPUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Everyone knows the children of Oedipus, so let’s go backwards in the family tree! What son of Cadmus was Oedipus’ paternal great-grandfather?",
    "answer": "POLYDORUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb vacō, vacāre , give the neuter plural accusative gerundive.",
    "answer": "11"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Vacanda forever! (proctor should quickly cross arms across chest) Now, give the same form for a first conjugation verb which is related to the Latin noun for “yoke” and means “to join.”",
    "answer": "IUGANDA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Since we’ve run out of African countries—real or imagined—spuriously derived from gerundives, translate the following sentence into Latin using the nouns Vakanda, Vakandae and vibrānium, vibrāniī : “The cruel thief stole vibranium from the people of Wakanda.”",
    "answer": "VIBRĀNIUM POPULŌ/HOMINIBUS VAKANDAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Along with harassing Itonian raiders and enduring meddlesome dwarves, what hero took a page out of Theseus’ book by killing an Aulian bandit with his own hoe during his stint as a cross-dressing slave of the Lydian queen Omphale?",
    "answer": "HERACLES / HERCULES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who was that Aulian bandit, who forced all visitors to till his vineyard?",
    "answer": "SYLEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What daughter of Syleus was killed along with her father?",
    "answer": "XENODICE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which of the following Latin terms is relevant to the Roman gladiatorial games: balneāticum, prōlūsiō, vesperna, ferculum?",
    "answer": "PRŌLŪSIŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What would happen if a gladiatorial fight was fought sine missione?",
    "answer": "THE GLADIATORS WOULD FIGHT TO THE DEATH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "By what name was a Samnite gladiator called when pitted against a retiarius?",
    "answer": "SECŪTOR(ĒS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What derivative of the Latin verb pandō means “to enter an owner’s land or property without permission”?",
    "answer": "TRESPASS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What derivative of the Latin verb pandō means “to surround”?",
    "answer": "ENCOMPASS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What derivative of the Latin verb pandō means “the product or offspring of a person or place”?",
    "answer": "SPAWN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What 22-book apologetic work written after the sack of Rome in 410 A.D. claims that in each individual coexist an earthly abode belonging to the devil and a heavenly locale belonging to God?",
    "answer": "12"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Name either the diocese or the birthplace of the author, Augustine. HIPPO or THAGASTE",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Nicippe and Sthenelus did Hera have born earlier than Heracles in order to foil Zeus’ prophecy?",
    "answer": "EURYSTHEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What servant of Alcmene tricked Eileithyia into uncrossing her legs and fingers so that Alcmene could give birth to Heracles?",
    "answer": "GALANTHIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What magister militum’s effective service and protection to the emperor Honorius was repaid with his own execution because of rumors of treason spread by jealous officials?",
    "answer": "STILICHO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Honorius hid in Ravenna while what Visigothic king attacked Rome?",
    "answer": "ALARIC"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give a Latin phrase which means “spontaneously.”",
    "answer": "SUŌ MOTŪ / AD LIB(ITUM) / EX TEMPORE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Give a Latin phrase which means “spontaneously.",
    "answer": "SUŌ MOTŪ / AD LIB(ITUM) / EX TEMPORE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which Roman author, a cantor Euphoriōnis who had a tumultuous relationship with Julius Caesar, wrote an epyllion on the myth of Attis and Cybele as well as love poetry to a certain Lesbia?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS VALERIUS) CATULLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Along with his fellow neoteric poet Cinna, Catullus traveled to Bithynia in the entourage of what Roman, who was married to Sulla’s daughter?",
    "answer": "(C.) MEMMIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Poem 66 in Catullus’ Carmina Docta is a translation of which Hellenistic author’s Lock of Berenice?",
    "answer": "CALLIMACHUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What would you be reading if you see the abbreviation SVV at the top of the page?",
    "answer": "LETTER [ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What does that abbreviation stand for?",
    "answer": "SĪ VALĒS, VALEŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where might one hear the phrase “prōsit” uttered?",
    "answer": "BAR / DRINKING PARTY / ETC. [IT’S A TOAST]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Iopas, Eumolpus, Marsyas, Demodocus, Thamyris, and Linus all shared what profession in mythology?",
    "answer": "MUSICIAN / BARD / ETC."
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What do the following mythological figures have in common: Pelias, Agenor, Aegyptus, Acrisius, Zetes, and Heracles?",
    "answer": "ALL TWINS / HAD TWIN BROTHERS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What do the following have in common: Haemus, Rhodope, Latmus, Idalium, Parthenius, Sipylus?",
    "answer": "ALL MOUNTAINS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Feeling his succession to the throne threatened, what Macedonian prince executed his younger brother Demetrius, a successful diplomat, and was forced by Rome with fake reparation demands to engage in the third iteration of the Macedonian Wars?",
    "answer": "PERSEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What king of Pergamum, the son of Attalus, was the chief informant against Perseus and later aided Rome against Antiochus III in the Seleucid War?",
    "answer": "EUMENES II [PROMPT ON “EUMENES”]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What adventurer claimed to be the son of Perseus and reunited Macedonia against Rome but was quickly crushed by Q. Caecilius Metellus?",
    "answer": "14"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Dēscrībāmus nunc proprietātēs dictiōnum in hāc sententiā: “quidquid id est, timeō Danaos et dona ferentīs.” Quō casū est ‘ferentīs?’",
    "answer": "ACCŪSĀTĪVŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "‘Timeo.’ Dīc mihi duo alia verba eiusdem dēfīnītiōnis.",
    "answer": "(ANY TWO VERBS MEANING TO FEAR)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quis est huius sententiae dictor?",
    "answer": "LAOCOON"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The city of Elaeüs was the site of the shrine of what Greek hero, who was allowed to briefly return from Hades to comfort his grieving wife Laodameia?",
    "answer": "PROTESILAUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "What Trojan hero had killed Protesilaus at Troy?",
    "answer": "HECTOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Generations later, when the Persians conquered Elaeüs, what greedy official looted the temple of Protesilaus and defiled its sacred precinct before paying the price for his impiety when the Athenian general Xanthippus nailed him to a cross and had his son stoned before his eyes?",
    "answer": "ARTAŸCTES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What two meanings does the Latin noun iūs have? SOUP / BROTH and LAW / RULE",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What two meanings does the Latin word adeō have? SO / TO SUCH A DEGREE and I APPROACH / GO TOWARDS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What two meanings does the Latin word sīs have? MAY YOU BE and IF YOU WISH",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the Latin term for the Roman concept which was guarded against with items such as crepundia and bullae and is known today in many cultures as “evil-eye”?",
    "answer": "FASCINĀTIŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Possibly deriving their name from the same source as the word fascinātiō, what satiric and coarse songs were often performed at various social occasions such as the Roman wedding procession?",
    "answer": "VERSŪS FESCENNĪNĪ / FESCENNINE VERSES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Speaking of words that sound like fascinātiō, how many fascēs līctōriae would a Roman dictātor have been entitled to outside the pōmērium?",
    "answer": "24"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Poēta, studiō vēnandī captus, sine morā in silvās profectus est.",
    "answer": "SET OUT INTO THE FOREST WITHOUT DELAY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate: Omnīnō imperītus armōrum gerendōrum, ab aprō ferōcī statim vulnerātus est.",
    "answer": "15"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate: Paene exanimātus, poēta tamen bēstiam fugāvit carmine intolerābilī recitandō.",
    "answer": "TO FLIGHT BY RECITING AN UNBEARABLE POEM."
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What Dalmatian-born late Latin author wrote Chronica and a Dē Virīs Illustribus but is perhaps most famous for translating the Old and New Testaments of the Christian Bible into Latin?",
    "answer": "(EUSEBIUS SOPHRONIUS) HIERONYMUS / (ST.) JEROME"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "With what previous Greek translation of the Old Testament had Jerome been dissatisfied, prompting him to go directly to the Hebrew texts as the basis of the Vulgate?",
    "answer": "THE SEPTUAGINT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The history of translation in Latin went back to what man from Tarentum, who produced a version of the Odyssey in Saturnian meter?",
    "answer": "(LIVIUS) ANDRONICUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What class of Latin nouns, sometimes used to express contempt or affection, contains nouns such as ātriolum and homunculus and is typically indicated by a suffix denoting small size?",
    "answer": "DIMINUTIVES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Consider the following sentence: “say ‘hello’ to my little friend.” Assuming the verb for “say” in that sentence is rendered as “dīc,” please give the Latin for “my little friend.”",
    "answer": "MEŌ AMĪCULŌ / MEAE AMĪCULAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "(NOTE TO PROCTOR: provide answer to first bonus before reading this question) Now, say in Latin, using a diminutive adjective: “Our fear of death is somewhat larger than the little friend.” or NOSTER TIMOR MORTIS MAIUSCULUS AMĪCULŌ/AMĪCULĀ EST",
    "answer": "NOSTER TIMOR MORTIS MAIUSCULUS QUAM AMĪCULUS/AMĪCULA EST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who grazed among the mares of king Oncius to avoid the advances of Poseidon, but could not fool him and thus became the mother of the famed horse Arion?",
    "answer": "DEMETER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other figure, whose name means “The Mistress,” was also produced by the union of Poseidon and Demeter?",
    "answer": "DESPOINA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Furious at Zeus, Poseidon, and the world in general, Demeter shut herself in a cave, until what group persuaded her to calm her anger and grief and accept the marriage of Persephone and Hades as inevitable?",
    "answer": "THE FATES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Ignoring the two princes arguing over who would be the first to kiss Tullia Minor, what Roman pretended to stumble and thereby kissed the earth, ensuring that he would hold supreme sway in Rome?",
    "answer": "LUCIUS JUNIUS BRUTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name either of those bickering princes. TITUS or ARRUNS",
    "answer": "16"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Name Tarquinius Superbus’ third son, who incited Brutus’ rebellion with his actions towards Lucretia.",
    "answer": "SEXTUS (TARQUINIUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which of the following words, if any, does not share the same Latin root as the others: difficult, confetti, exemplify, specific, crucify?",
    "answer": "CRUCIFY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin verb with what meaning is “crucify” derived?",
    "answer": "FĪGŌ – FASTEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The other four words in the tossup derive from the verb faciō. What English noun, derived from both faciō and caleō, literally means “someone who makes the car warm”?",
    "answer": "CHAUFFEUR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What historical work of the second century A.D. covered the reign of Tiberius through the death of Nero and contains famous passages about the early roots of Christianity?",
    "answer": "ANNALĒS (OF TACITUS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What work of Tacitus, probably his first, was a eulogy and biography of his late father-in-law?",
    "answer": "AGRICOLA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other early work of Tacitus, a biography of a certain Central European people, was likely published alongside the Agricola?",
    "answer": "GERMĀNIA / DĒ ORĪGINE ET SITŪ GERMĀNŌRUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate into Latin: We understood that the books had been lost but we believed that they could be found.",
    "answer": "SED CRĒDĒBĀMUS / CRĒDIDIMUS EŌS INVENĪRĪ POSSE."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate, using an indirect statement: I was hoping that you, Julia, would go to Rome and search for the books there.",
    "answer": "ET IBI LIBRŌS QUAESĪTŪRAM ESSE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Now translate: You, however, knew that the city was already being attacked by pirates.",
    "answer": "TŪ AUTEM SCIĒBĀS / SCĪVISTĪ URBEM Ā PĪRĀTĪS IAM OPPUGNĀRĪ."
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Greek hero killed all the following figures: Dionysus, Aconteus, Atlas, Acrisius, Polydectes?",
    "answer": "17"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "When Perseus led the Argives into battle against Dionysus, he killed a great many of the god’s followers and buried them in a mass grave. What Maenad did he bury separately because of her high rank?",
    "answer": "CHOREIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to versions of the story where Perseus did not kill Dionysus, the god later reconciled with the Argives, who allowed him to bury what wife of his and former Cretan princess in a temple which they dedicated to him?",
    "answer": "ARIADNE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following passage, adapted from Livy, which I will read twice, then answer in LATIN the question that follows: Ad veterem portam Palātiī Rōmulus turbā fugientium āctus, arma ad caelum tollēns, \"Iuppiter, tuīs\" inquit \"iussus omnibus hīc in Palātiō prīma urbis fundāmenta iēcī.\" arcem iam Sabīnī habent; inde hūc armātī superātā mediā valle tendunt; at tū, pater deōrum hominumque, hinc saltem prohibē hostēs; dēme terrōrem Rōmānīs fugamque turpem siste. hīc ego tibi templum voveō.\" The question: Cui deō Rōmulus supplicat?",
    "answer": "IOVĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quī Rōmulum ad veterem portam Palātiī ēgērunt?",
    "answer": "FUGIENTĒS / TURBA FUGIENTIUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Rōmulus Iovī vōvit?",
    "answer": "TEMPLUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What elegiac poet described the legend of Hercules and Cacus, the treachery of Tarpeia, the story of Vertumnus and Pomona, and a woman called Cynthia in his four book collection of poems?",
    "answer": "PROPERTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "According to Apuleius, what was Cynthia’s actual name?",
    "answer": "HOSTIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the following cities, which was furthest north: Salona, Burdigala, Olisipo, Colonia Agrippinensis.",
    "answer": "COLONIA AGRIPPINENSIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of those cities, which is farthest east?",
    "answer": "SALONA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Dē Incendiō Urbis, the Catachthonion, the Iliacon, and the Pharsalia are all works attributed to what Spanish author?",
    "answer": "(MARCUS ANNAEUS) LUCAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What famous rhetorician was the paternal grandfather of Lucan?",
    "answer": "SENECA THE ELDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: morbus equī magnō impedimentō mīlitī Rōmānō fuit.",
    "answer": "A GREAT IMPEDIMENT TO THE ROMAN SOLDIER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Mīles equum mortientem ducēs cēlāre cōnstituit, quod pugnāre volēbat.",
    "answer": "FROM HIS COMMANDERS BECAUSE HE WANTED TO FIGHT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Hostēs multō celeriōrēs mīlite Rōmānō erant, sed ille audācissimum omnium sē praebuit. 2018 Yale Certamen Invitational Advanced – Semifinal Round",
    "answer": "19"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In the Iliad, the armies of Zeleia are led by what man, who, urged by his comrade, takes up his ibex-horn bow and shoots Menelaus in the hip, breaking a truce and prolonging the war?",
    "answer": "PANDARUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "However, it turns out that that comrade, Laodocus, was actually what goddess in disguise?",
    "answer": "ATHENA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Pandarus later accompanies what hero in his chariot on a mission to kill Diomedes, but takes an Athena-guided spear to the face instead, shattering his teeth?",
    "answer": "AENEAS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which of the following words, if any, is NOT derived from the same Latin root as the others: cardinal, carnation, carnage, carrion?",
    "answer": "CARDINAL"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin noun, with what meaning, do we derive “cardinal”?",
    "answer": "CARDŌ – HINGE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the nominative singular, genitive singular, gender, and meaning of the Latin noun from which the other three words are derived.",
    "answer": "CARŌ, CARNIS, F. – FLESH / MEAT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What close friend of the emperor Vespasian is credited with many long works, including 20 books on Rome’s wars in Germany, a 31-book continuation of the histories of Aufidius Bassus, and a 37-book encyclopedia on the whole of natural history?",
    "answer": "PLINY THE ELDER / (GAIUS) PLINIUS (CAECILIUS SECUNDUS) THE ELDER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Spanish-born contemporary of Pliny the Elder and tutor to his nephew Pliny the Younger wrote twelve books about the practice and style of oratory?",
    "answer": "(MARCUS FABIUS) QUINTILIAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other work of Quintilian, no longer extant, dealt with the decline of Roman oratory?",
    "answer": "DĒ CAUSĪS CORRUPTAE ĒLOQUENTIAE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb crepō, give the 1st person plural pluperfect active subjunctive.",
    "answer": "CREPUISSĒMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give the same form for the verb maereō.",
    "answer": "DOESN’T EXIST (NO PERFECT SYSTEM)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the verb spargō, give the perfect active and passive infinitives. SPARSISSE and SPARSUM ESSE",
    "answer": "20"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man pursued insurgents from Mt. Atlas to the confines of the Sahara to suppress a revolt among the Mauretanians, but is better known for felling the sacred groves of Mona and suppressing a massive revolt of the Trinovantes and Iceni?",
    "answer": "(CAIUS) SUETONIUS PAULINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What man, defeated by Boudicca during the reign of Claudius, succeeded Vettius Bolanus as governor of Britain and defeated the divorced husband of Cartimandua?",
    "answer": "(QUINTUS PETILLIUS) CERIALIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What successor of Cerialis resumed the advance into Wales and defeated both the Silures and the Ordovices?",
    "answer": "(SEXTUS IULIUS) FRONTINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What late author, the first Latin writer to use the term trīnitās, was an active apologist for Christianity and wrote works such as Adversus Marciōnem, Ad Martyrās, and Apologēticum?",
    "answer": "TERTULLIAN / (QUINTUS SEPTIMIUS FLORENS) TERTULLIANUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which of Tertullian’s works, written in 212 A.D., was addressed to the governor of Africa Proconsularis, who was persecuting Christians?",
    "answer": "AD SCAPULAM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Tertullian spent a good portion of his career attacking heretics and protecting orthodoxy, but later joined what fanatic sect originating from Phrygia?",
    "answer": "MONTANISM / MONTANIST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of a money-dealer of equestrian rank gained the support of the governors Licinius Mucianus and Tiberius Alexander as he prepared to starve Rome into submission and become the ultimate victor of the “Year of the Four Emperors?”",
    "answer": "VESPASIAN"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "Though he was not preparing on engaging in physical battle, Vespasian was forced to when what officer of the Pannonian army and protégé of Galba dashed into Italy and handed decisive defeats to the Vitellians?",
    "answer": "ANTONIUS PRIMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Where in Italy did Primus win both victories against Valens and Caecina, after which Vitellius asked for terms of surrender?",
    "answer": "CREMONA / BEDRIACUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the words lītus, salix, torus, venia, and vīctus, which is being described in the following Latin sentence: Latrōne damnātō, forsan ōret cōnsulem ut līberētur hāc.",
    "answer": "VENIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the words lītus, salix, torus, venia, and vīctus, which is being described in the following Latin sentence: Si ēsuriās, hanc quaerās.",
    "answer": "VĪCTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Of the words lītus, salix, torus, venia, and vīctus, which is being described in the following Latin sentence: Manibus iūnctīs, amantēs saepe fruuntur hōc in locō ambulandō.",
    "answer": "21"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "When a bull from the herd of Heracles wandered into his territory, what Sicilian king challenged the stranger to wrestle but died in the ensuing match?",
    "answer": "ERYX"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Argonaut fathered Eryx with Aphrodite after the goddess saved him and transported him to the island of Sicily?",
    "answer": "BUTES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In book 5 of Vergil’s Aeneid, what Sicilian man sacrifices an ox to Eryx after defeating Dares to win the boxing match at the funeral games of Anchises?",
    "answer": "ENTELLUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "At his death, the Italian historian Paolo Sarpi used what two-word Latin phrase to bless his native Venice, not knowing it would later become the motto of Idaho?",
    "answer": "ESTŌ PERPETUA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What state’s motto also employs the imperative estō when it declares that “the welfare of the people should be the supreme law?”",
    "answer": "MISSOURI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The three-word Latin motto of what state hat state’s motto employs the form esse?",
    "answer": "NORTH CAROLINA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Which Olympian god were all the following figures associated with: a son of Demeter honored at the Eleusinian mysteries, a Thracian god whose worshippers threw a messenger onto three upright spears, and an unfortunate son of Zeus and Persephone whose heart was placed into the immortal soul of another?",
    "answer": "DIONYSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Dionysus himself was the son of Semele, who adopted what name when she became immortal?",
    "answer": "THYONE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Myth",
    "question": "There are several similarities between the myths of Dionysus and the myths of Cretan Zeus. This connection is fitting, especially when it comes to which epithet of Dionysus translating to “The Thunderer?”",
    "answer": "BROMIOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence from Latin to English: “Sī quaestiōnis oblivīscāris, rectē nōn respondeās.”",
    "answer": "YOU WOULD NOT RESPOND CORRECTLY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence from Latin to English: “Nisī illa verba locutus essēs, īrātissimus nōn factus essem.”",
    "answer": "THOSE WORDS, I WOULD NOT HAVE BECOME VERY ANGRY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate the following sentence from Latin to English: Marcus crēdidit rem publicam, sī Caesar dictator rēmansisset, casuram fuisse.",
    "answer": "22"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The story of Romulus continues. Listen carefully to the following passage, which I will read twice, then answer in ENGLISH the question that follows: Haec precātūs, \"hīc, Rōmānī,\" inquit \"Iuppiter Optimus Maximus resistere atque iterāre pugnam iubet.\" restitērunt Rōmānī tamquam caelestī vōce iussī: ipse ad prīmōrēs Rōmulus prōvolat. dux Sabīnōrum, Mettius Curtius, ab arce dēcucurrerat et effūsōs ēgerat Rōmānōs per tōtum forum. nec procul iam ā portā Palātiī erat, clāmitāns \"vīcimus perfidōs hospitēs, imbellēs hostēs; iam sciunt longē aliud esse virginēs rapere, aliud pugnāre cum virīs.\" The question: According to Mettius Curtius, what do the Romans now know after a long time?",
    "answer": "IT IS ONE THING TO SEIZE VIRGINS, ANOTHER THING TO FIGHT WITH MEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What else did Mettius Curtius shout as he neared the gate of the Palatine?",
    "answer": "GUESTS, THE PEACEFUL HOSTS"
  },
  {
    "category": "History",
    "question": "What had Romulus done when Jupiter ordered him to resume battle?",
    "answer": "HE FLEW / RACED INTO THE FRONT RANKS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Let’s get this bread. In Ancient Rome, what was the name for the very best bread, made of pure wheat flour?",
    "answer": "PĀNIS SILĪGINEUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Let’s gain this grain. What would the Romans have called the type of bread made of coarse flour, of flour and bran, or of bran alone and which was typically reserved for soldiers?",
    "answer": "PĀNIS (MĪLITĀRIS) CASTRĒNSIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Let’s yeet this yeast. What would the Romans have called the worst kind of bread, made of coarse grain and usually given to dogs?",
    "answer": "PĀNIS SORDIDUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author’s important positions in the cults of Isis and Osiris in Rome are reflected in his work, in which Isis herself intervenes by giving Lucius a garland of roses to turn him from donkey to human?",
    "answer": "APULEIUS’"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "In Apuleius’ Metamorphoses, an old woman tells Charite the story of what two lovers in a digression occupying almost three books? CUPID and PSYCHE",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The four naughty tales told to Lucius, which include “The Tale of the Tub” and “The Baker’s Wife,” are stories of what genre, which Sisenna famously translated from Greek in the 1st century B.C.?",
    "answer": "23"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What princess of Lesbos was so distraught after being raped by her father that Athena transformed her into an owl?",
    "answer": "NYCTIMENE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What woman, a lover of Apollo, was transformed into a lotus tree after she plucked a flower from the transformed Lotis, who had been pursued by Priapus?",
    "answer": "DRYOPE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What son of Priam, who interpreted the prophecy that Paris would destroy the city, was transformed into a diver bird after he chased and caused the death of Hesperia?",
    "answer": "AESACUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "We’re sure that, as advanced players, you’ve come to know and love all the Latin adverbs meaning “immediately.” Which Latin adverb meaning “immediately” is actually a lost diminutive of the Latin noun meaning “time” prefixed with “ex”?",
    "answer": "EXTEMPLŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which Latin adverb meaning “immediately” also means “on the spot” and is the compound of the Latin preposition in and a Latin noun meaning “place”?",
    "answer": "ĪLICŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which Latin adverb meaning “immediately” is likely the compound of two Latin prepositions, one which is governed by the ablative and the other which can take the genitive or the ablative?",
    "answer": "PROTĪNUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Who refused to rise when Caesar Strabo entered a meeting of the Collēgium Poetārum, claiming that Caesar’s tragedies were inferior to his own plays, which included Epinausimache, Armōrum Iūdicium, and Atreus?",
    "answer": "(L.) ACCIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Which play of Accius was banned from being performed in 44 B.C. because it celebrated the head of the revolt against the Tarquins?",
    "answer": "BRUTUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Accius came under heavy literary attack from what contemporary, who declared “ex praecordiīs ecferō versum” in one of his fragments?",
    "answer": "(C.) LUCILIUS (SAPIENS)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate into Latin this first line of the classic poem by Robert Frost: “whose woods these are I think I know.”",
    "answer": "PUTŌ MĒ SCĪRE CUIUS SILVAE HAE SINT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate into Latin this line from Norah Jones: \"I don't know why I didn't come.\"",
    "answer": "NESCIŌ CŪR NŌN VĒNERIM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Finally, translate into Latin this famous question from The Dark Knight: “Do you wanna know how I got these scars?” [or NŌNNE VĪS, or VULTISNE, or VĪN] PROCTOR: “I will now pause for one full minute to allow any outstanding challenges from Tossups 1-19 to be raised. After this pause, only challenges on Tossup 20 may be raised.”",
    "answer": "24"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What Samnite chieftain plotted to unite all of Rome’s enemies and won a victory at Camerinum but was defeated by Fabius Rullianus and Decius Mus at Sentinum later in",
    "answer": "GELLIUS EGNATIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What previous Samnite commander, most known for his victory at Caudine Forks, preceded Gellius Egnatius as general in the Second Samnite War?",
    "answer": "GAVIUS PONTIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "After defeating the Hyantes and Aones, what man established a city on a hill near the Asopus River in Boeotia named after himself?",
    "answer": "CADMUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Cadmus’ wife Harmonia is often said to be the daughter of Ares and Aphrodite, but what other couple is also said to be her parents? ZEUS and ELECTRA",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "A revolt in Numidia by Tacfarinas, the death of Germanicus, and the reign of Sejanus were all events that occurred in which emperor’s reign?",
    "answer": "TIBERIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "To what island did Tiberius, a reluctant emperor, retire in 26 AD, ruling from afar until his death in 37 AD?",
    "answer": "CAPRI"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author, born in 330 A.D., began his career as an officer under the emperor Constantius and is best known for his historical continuation of Tacitus in 31 books entitled the Rēs Gestae?",
    "answer": "AMMIANUS MARCELLINUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Whose death at Adrianople ends the Rēs Gestae?",
    "answer": "VALENS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Which of the following words, if any, is NOT derived from the same Latin root as the others: textile, detective, toilet, subtext?",
    "answer": "DETECTIVE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin verb, with what meaning, do we derive “detective”?",
    "answer": "TEGŌ – COVER"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "From what Latin verb, with what meaning, do we derive the other three words? 2.Translate the following sentence from English to Latin: “I will come home provided that dinner is ready.”",
    "answer": "VENIAM DOMUM DUM(MODO) CĒNA PARĀTA SIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate from English to Latin: “There is no doubt that I enjoy studying.”",
    "answer": "NŌN DUBIUM EST QUĪN STUDENDŌ FRUAR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate this sentence from English to Latin: “I will not hinder you from making a speech in the Forum.” 2018 Yale Certamen Invitational Advanced – Final Round",
    "answer": "ORĀTIŌNEM IN FORŌ HABEĀS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "“Just when the escalating attack was at its height, the tide began to ebb and the water gradually receded from the edge of the lagoon...those who reached the wall through the lagoon, finding the battlements deserted, ascended them and occupied the wall without striking a blow, the defenders having never conceived it possible that the enemy would reach the wall from the lagoon.” This edited translation of Polybius describes the capture of what city in 209 B.C., Scipio Africanus’ first major victory in Spain?",
    "answer": "NEW CARTHAGE / CARTHĀGŌ NOVA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Through brilliant generalship, Scipio continued to find success, including at what battle of 206 B.C., where he defeated Hasdrubal Gisgo and expelled the Carthaginians from Spain?",
    "answer": "ILIPA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "At what Spanish city did Scipio Africanus receive the Carthaginians’ official surrender?",
    "answer": "GADES / CADIZ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: tam difficile est aliīs saturam nōn scrībere quam aliīs saturam intellegere.",
    "answer": "AS (IT IS) FOR OTHERS TO UNDERSTAND SATIRE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Iuvenālis saturam facilius scrīpsit quam aliī nōmina sua scrībere possunt.",
    "answer": "SOME/OTHERS CAN WRITE THEIR NAMES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Translate into English: Nisī opera ā Rōmānīs scripta haberēmus, ignōrārēmus quam salsī Rōmānī ipsī fuissent.",
    "answer": "KNOW HOW WITTY/SASSY THE ROMANS THEMSELVES WERE / HAD BEEN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "For the following Latin works, distinguish which were written by Cato the Elder and which were written by Valerius Cato: Orīginēs, Dictynna, Lydia, Apophthegmata. ORĪGINĒS and APOPHTHEGMATA = CATO THE ELDER DICTYNNA and LYDIA = VALERIUS CATO",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Do the same for the following works of Varro Reatinus and Varro Atacinus: Leucadia, Bellum Sequanicum, Dē Linguā Latīnā, Disciplīnae. LEUCADIA and BELLUM SEQUANICUM = VARRO ATACINUS DĒ LINGUĀ LATĪNĀ and DISCIPLĪNAE = VARRO REATINUS",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Do the same for the following works of Verrius Flaccus and Valerius Flaccus: Argonautica, Rērum Etruscārum Librī, Fastī, Dē Verbōrum Significātū.",
    "answer": "27"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The descendants of Cleito and Poseidon benevolently ruled what legendary island for many generations until their divine blood was diluted and they tyrannically attempted to conquer the rest of the world?",
    "answer": "ATLANTIS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Greek city led the nations of the world in defeating the invading forces of Atlantis?",
    "answer": "ATHENS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What autochthonic first inhabitant of Atlantis was the father of Cleito and the ancestor of the Atlantean rulers?",
    "answer": "EVENOR"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Listen carefully to the following short excerpt from Juvenal, which I will read twice, then answer in ENGLISH the question that follows: Prīma ferē vōta et cūnctīs nōtissima templīs dīvitiae, crēscant ut opēs, ut maxima tōtō nostra sit arca forō. The question: according to the passage, what is almost always first prayed for at temples?",
    "answer": "RICHES / WEALTH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Now listen to this short excerpt from Juvenal, which I will read twice, then answer in ENGLISH the question that follows: Expectent ergō tribūnī, vinciant dīvitiae, sacrō nē cēdat honōrī nūper in hanc urbem pedibus quī vēnerat albīs. The question: Using your knowledge of Roman Life, tell me what specific sort of a person the passage’s narrator does not want to attain the sacred office.",
    "answer": "TO THE CITY / WITH WHITE FEET]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Now listen to this short excerpt from Juvenal, which I will read twice, then answer in ENGLISH the question that follows: tibi nōn committitur aurum, vel, sī quandō datur, cūstōs affīxus ibīdem, quī numeret gemmās, unguēs observet acūtōs. The question: When the passage’s addressee possesses a golden gup, for what two specific reasons is a guard placed over him/her? TO COUNT THE GEMS and TO KEEP WATCH",
    "answer": "ON HIS / HER SHARP FINGERNAILS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The twelve athla, the locus fortūnae, and the signs of the zodiac are all subjects covered by what author’s five book didactic astronomical poem?",
    "answer": "MANILIUS’"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Manilius echoes what school of philosophy in the Astronomica?",
    "answer": "STOICISM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What adopted son of Tiberius wrote the Aratea and Prognostica, both reworkings of poems by Aratus?",
    "answer": "GERMANICUS (JULIUS CAESAR)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "(NOTE TO PROCTOR––DO NOT READ ALOUD: Subtly make clear the “-os”sound in tigridos, as opposed to an “-as” sound). Consider the following noun forms: crūs, tigridos, lacūs, hērōa, bovīle. Which of those forms, if any, CANNOT be accusative?",
    "answer": "TIGRIDOS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Consider the following adjective forms: pientissimus, intimum, falsissima, candidissimus, maturrima. Which of those forms, if any, is NOT a valid superlative form?",
    "answer": "ALL ARE VALID SUPERLATIVE FORMS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Consider the following pronoun forms: quaevīs, quispiam, ecquis, eccillum, quodcumque. Which of those forms, if any, is NOT indefinite?",
    "answer": "ECCILLUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What aged emperor, who ruled for six months after being chosen by the Senate, won impressive victories against the Goths and the Alans before his death in 275 A.D.?",
    "answer": "(M. CLAUDIUS) TACITUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What half-brother of Tacitus proclaimed himself emperor upon Tacitus’ death but was then killed upon the accession of Probus?",
    "answer": "(M. ANNIUS) FLORIAN(US)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What military position had Probus held under Aurelian’s rule?",
    "answer": "MAGISTER EQUITUM"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Qua Latīna abbreviātūra indicat hominem sine līberīs mortuum esse?",
    "answer": "(D.)S.P. / O.S.P."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quā Latīna abbreviātūra imperat ut aegrōtus medicīnam ante quiētem accipiat?",
    "answer": "H.S."
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Qua Latīna abbreviātūra ēdocet quis hanc statuam fēcerit?",
    "answer": "29"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "As a large ship loomed in the distance, what queen put on the armor of her father Thoas and called the Lemnian women to arms, though her worries were assuaged when Aethalides approached and asked for hospitality on behalf of the Argonauts?",
    "answer": "HYPSIPYLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What nurse of Hypsipyle convinced her to allow the Argonauts to stay and to sleep with them in order to ensure that a new generation would rise to populate the island?",
    "answer": "POLYXO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Hypsipyle was later exiled because it was discovered that she had saved her father from the murder of all the men on the island. She then became the nursemaid of what king of Nemea, whose son would soon be ominously named “the bringer of doom?”",
    "answer": "LYCURGUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "They say that all roads lead to Rome. However, they seem to have forgotten about which Roman road that ran from Ariminum to Placentia?",
    "answer": "VIA AEMILIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What road in ancient Rome ran from Rome to Pisae?",
    "answer": "VIA AURELIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What road in ancient Rome ran from Capua to Messana?",
    "answer": "VIA POPILIA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning among bōs, dōs, and rōs. COW, DOWRY, and DEW [RESPECTIVELY]",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Differentiate in meaning among mūs, rūs, and tūs. MOUSE, COUNTRY(SIDE), and (FRANK)INCENSE [RESPECTIVELY]",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Give two entirely distinct meanings for the adverb ferē. FIERCELY / WILDLY and ALMOST",
    "answer": ""
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who emigrated to Rhodes with his sister to avoid the risk of patricide, but eventually killed his father Catreus when the old man came to Rhodes in an attempt to leave his Cretan kingdom to his son and was mistaken for a pirate?",
    "answer": "ALTHAEMENES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What sister did Althaemenes take with him to Rhodes but later kick to death after she was raped by Hermes and became pregnant?",
    "answer": "APEMOSYNE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What happened to Althaemenes after he killed his father?",
    "answer": "(AFTER PRAYING FOR THAT TO HAPPEN)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Translate into completely alliterative Latin: They deny that sailors are unable to obtain new knots.",
    "answer": "NEGANT NAUTĀS NEQUĪRE NŌDŌS NOVŌS NANCĪSCĪ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Now translate into completely alliterative Latin: I summoned my neighbors to keep the two-headed snake off from the fields. ACCOLĀS ARCESSĪ (ACCĪVĪ, ADVOCĀVĪ, etc.) AD ANGUEM ANCIPITEM",
    "answer": "30"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Finally, translate into completely alliterative Latin: Because he had seen their tracks, the seer was able to avoid the watchmen.",
    "answer": "VESTĪGIĪS VĪSĪS, VĀTĒS VIGILĒS VITĀRE VALUIT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "“He should be a man of letters, a skillful draftsman, a mathematician, familiar with scientific inquiries, a diligent student of philosophy, acquainted with music….” The ten-book treatise of what Augustan soldier offers this as the definition of the ideal architect?",
    "answer": "(MARCUS) VITRUVIUS (POLLIO)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "An eight-book treatise modeled on the work of Hippocrates is the only surviving work of what encyclopedist of the early Roman Empire?",
    "answer": "(AULUS CORNELIUS) CELSUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What other early Roman author, a freedman from Thrace, authored 5 books in a particular genre based on the work of Aesop?",
    "answer": "(GAIUS IULIUS) PHAEDRUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The English adjective “corrugated” is derived from what Latin noun with what meaning?",
    "answer": "RŪGA – WRINKLE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The English noun “jellyfish” is derived from what Latin noun with what meaning?",
    "answer": "GELŪ – FROST / ICE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "The English noun “paunch” is derived from what Latin noun with what meaning?",
    "answer": "PANTEX – BELLY / STOMACH"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Founded either by Zeus on the site where he wrestled Cronus and won supremacy over the gods or by Heracles the Dactyl after his emigration from Mt. Ida, what event, held every four years, honored its winners with crowns of wild olive?",
    "answer": "OLYMPIC GAMES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "During the first Olympic games, who outran Hermes and defeated Ares at boxing?",
    "answer": "APOLLO"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What other athletic competition, which took place at the same location, was open only to women?",
    "answer": "HERAEAN GAMES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "“Signīs receptīs”, “Armeniā receptā”, and “cīvibus et signīs mīlitāribus ā Parthīs recuperatīs” were mottos used by Augustus to celebrate what Parthian king’s surrender of the Roman standards lost at Carrhae?",
    "answer": "PHRAATES (IV)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "These standards were not easily won, as Phraates IV seemed to have prized them more than his own son. What rival to Phraates kidnapped his son and gave him to Augustus as a hostage for the standards, an exchange that Phraates refused?",
    "answer": "TIRIDATES"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Phraates finally handed over the standards when Tiberius took an army to place what man on the throne of Armenia?",
    "answer": "31"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What author was the main intermediary between Antiquity and the Middle Ages due to his translations of Aristotle, his advocacy of the quadrivium, and his composition of a philosophical work while imprisoned by the Gothic king Theodoric entitled Dē Consōlātiōne Philosophiae?",
    "answer": "(ANICIUS MANLIUS SEVERINUS) BOETHIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "Boethius’ Dē Institutiōne Musicā owes much to what Christian author from Treviri, often called “The Father of Church Song”?",
    "answer": "(ST.) AMBROSE / (AURELIUS) AMBROSIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What other post-Empire author wrote a Chronica from Adam to the year 519 in addition to Institutiōnēs, a two book encyclopedic handbook on sacred and profane literature, and Dē Orthographiā? PROCTOR: “I will now pause for one full minute to allow any outstanding challenges from Tossups 1-19 to be raised. After this pause, only challenges on Tossup 20 may be raised.”",
    "answer": "(FLAVIUS MAGNUS AURELIUS) CASSIODORUS (SENATOR)"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "The phrases ēdite rēgibus, genitae Pandīone, and Rhēnus oritur ex Lepontiīs all depict what use of the ablative?",
    "answer": "SOURCE / ORIGIN"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "What use of the ablative is found in this sentence, adapted from Cicero’s De Finibus: gubernātōris ars, quia navigandi ratiōnem habet, ūtilitāte, non arte laudātur.",
    "answer": "CAUSE [A&G 404]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Who hid in a thicket of asparagus thorn and shrubs and vowed never to destroy them if they would shelter her from the man who had just killed her father Sinis?",
    "answer": "PERIGUNE"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Theseus eventually convinced Perigune to come out and she later bore him what son?",
    "answer": "MELANIPPUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Moorish bareback-riding javelin men and Dalmatian and Persian horsemen made up the cavalry corps of what emperor, which he placed on par with the praetorian guard in 263 A.D.?",
    "answer": "GALLIENUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "With what group did Gallienus establish a 40-year peace that would last until the tetrarchy?",
    "answer": "CHRISTIANS [ACCEPT EQUIVALENTS]"
  },
  {
    "category": "Literature",
    "question": "What work of Latin Literature refutes comments made around 150 A.D. by the rhetorician Fronto, using the pagan Caecilius Natalis as a puppet to defeat in a debate umpired by the author Minucius Felix?",
    "answer": "OCTAVIUS"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "This feud was ironic because Fronto and Minucius Felix were both natives of what town in North Africa?",
    "answer": "CIRTA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat “balteum”?",
    "answer": "BALDRIC / SWORD BELT"
  },
  {
    "category": "Uncategorized",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat “epulum”?",
    "answer": "BANQUET / FEAST"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "Quid Anglicē significat “comitia”?",
    "answer": "ASSEMBLY / ELECTION [NOT THE LOCATION FOR ASSEMBLY"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What Latin adjective, a temporal numeral, might one use to describe a two-year-old?",
    "answer": "BĪMUS / BĪMA"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What four-letter Latin noun derived from unus can have the meanings of “a single pearl,” “a kind of single onion,” or “unity”?",
    "answer": "ŪNIŌ"
  },
  {
    "category": "Language",
    "question": "What partitive Latin adjective meaning “of three parts” could Caesar have used at the beginning of his dē Bellō Gallicō to describe Gaul? Make the adjective agree with Gallia.",
    "answer": "TERNĀRIA"
  }
]